<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="Alternate_Serial_Control">
	<info>
		<title>Alternate Serial Control</title>
		<abstract>
			<para>
		    	This tutorial describes a basic workflow in which the user will
		    	register a subscription to a serial publication, express the
		   	 distribution of copies of that publication to branches, define the
		   	 format of captions to be affixed to each issue, specify details of
		    	the publication pattern, instruct the system to predict future
		    	issues, and finally receive copies of an issue.  This tutorial is
		    	not intended to represent exhaustive documentation of Evergreen
		    	features relating to serials, as those features are continually
		    	evolving as of this writing, but it should provide a basis on which
		   	 user exploration of serials features can take place. Hopefully,
		    	that exploration will initiate feedback that will lead to the
		    	continuing improvement of serials in Evergreen.
        		</para>
        	</abstract>
	</info> 
    <simplesect>
        <title>Creating a Copy Template</title>
        <para>
            To create a serial subscription in the Alternate Serial Control
            interfaces, you're first going to need a copy template.  For many
            use cases, you can create one copy template and re-use it all the
            time, but if you don't yet have one ready, follow these steps.
        </para>
        <para>
            Find the copy template editor under the Admin menu of the staff
            client.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/find-copy-template-menu.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>Once that page has loaded, click <guibutton>New Template</guibutton>.</para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/create-copy-template.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            You don't actually need to fill out all of these fields.  If you don't
            want serial copies to get barcodes and show up individually in your
            catalog, you only need to set the first two fields, which are "owning
            library" and "name."  Note that "owning library" in this case refers
            to the library that owns the copy template itself. This has nothing to
            do with what libraries receive copies or what library manages the
            subscription. We'll get to that later.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you do want your copies to have barcodes (and perhaps to circulate)
            and to appear individually in your catalog, you will need at least to
            fill in the fields shown in the above image.
        </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>To the Catalog</title>
        <para>
            Initiate a catalog search in the staff client to find the bibliographic
            record to which you'd like to attach a subscription.  If you don't
            already have the record in your system, you can import it via any of
            your preferred methods (MARC import, Z39.50 search, etc.) and then
            look it up in the catalog.
        </para>
        <para>
            From the record detail page, click "Actions for this Record," and then
            click "Alternate Serial Control."  You note that we've used a magazine
            called Flying for our example.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/start-from-catalog.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>The Subscription</title>
        <para>
            Here you'll be presented with an interface that would show you any
            existing subscriptions against the bibliographic record you've chosen,
            if there were any.  More importantly for our purposes, it provides a
            "New Subscription" button.  Click that.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/create-sub.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            The only required fields here are <guilabel>owning library</guilabel> and <guilabel>start date.</guilabel>
            You can choose to specify and end date if you have one. <guilabel>Expected date
            offset</guilabel> means the difference between the nominal publishing date of any
            given issue and the date that you generally expect to receive your copy.
            If a publication is dated with the first of each month, but you
            generally receive it five days before that, you might enter <quote>-5 days</quote>
            into that field.
        </para>
        <para>
            Once you have created this basic subscription, you'll see that it has
            an ID number, which is display as a link that you can click.  Click
            that link to manage the subscription in greater detail.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/subscription-manage.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            Now you're looking at the Subscription Details page, which has four
            tabs.  The first tab, labeled Summary, shows information you've already
            seen.  Proceed to the next tab, Distributions, to start telling
            Evergreen where you want copies of your serial to go.
        </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Distributions</title>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/sub-details.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            Using the <guibutton>New Distribution</guibutton> button, create a distribution for each
            branch for which you expect to receive copies.  Each distribution
            needs at least a label, a <quote>holding library</quote>, and a <quote>receive unit
            template.</quote>  <quote>Receive unit template</quote> is where you select the copy
            template we created at the beginning of this tutorial.  Label can be
            anything, and will only appear at receive time.  It is not publicly
            visible.  "Holding library" refers to the library that will get copies.
        </para>
        <para>
            The last two fields have something to do with binding multiple copies
            into larger shelving units, but they are currently ignored by the
            Alternate Serial Control, which does not support such binding, and you
            should leave these fields blank.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/create-distrib.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            After saving your distribution (and creating any others for other
            libraries for which you will receive items), click on each link in the
            Label column to set up the streams for each distribution.
        </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Streams</title>
        <para>
            <quote>Streams</quote> are perhaps the most confusing concept in the Alternate
            Serials Control interfaces, but I'll try to explain them concisely: Each
            stream represents one *recurring* copy of a serial.  So if you have a
            library called Example Branch 1 (BR1 for short), and you want BR1 to
            get four copies for every issue, then you should create one
            distribution for BR1 and four streams for that distribution.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/distribs-to-streams.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            You can create streams one at a time by clicking <guibutton>New Stream</guibutton>. In this
            case you have the opportunity to give each stream a routing label. This
            routing label only shows up at receive time and on routing lists, and
            is not visible in the catalog or anywhere publicly viewable.  The
            routing label is entirely optional.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/new-stream.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            If you don't care about routing labels, or need to create more than
            just a couple of steams, use the <guibutton>Create Many Streams</guibutton> button to create
            several at once.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/create-many-streams.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            If you wish to set up routing lists, use the checkboxes on the left
            side of the grid interface to select one stream at a time, and click
            <guibutton>Routing List for Selected Stream</guibutton>.  If you don't care about routing
            lists, you may skip to the Captions and Patterns heading of this
            document.
        </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Setting Up Routing Lists</title>
        <para>
            <emphasis>
                As of this writing, routing lists features have been written,
                but have not yet been slated for inclusion in a 2.0 series
                Evergreen release.
            </emphasis>
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/routing-list-manage.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            A routing list is made up of <guilabel>users</guilabel>, who will presumably get their
            hands on a copy of a serial before that copy hits its regular shelving
            location.  Those users can be either <guilabel>readers</guilabel>, meaning actual
            Evergreen users with a barcode, or <guilabel>departments</guilabel>, which can really be
            anything and are represented by a free-form text field.  There is also
            a <guilabel>note</guilabel> field available in either case.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/routing-list-add.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            Enter any combination of <guilabel>readers</guilabel> and <guilabel>departments</guilabel> you need using
            the supplied fields and the "Add" button.  Readers are specified by
            their barcodes in the appropriately labeled field.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/routing-list-drag.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            You can re-arrange users in the list by dragging and dropping each
            numbered row.  When you've got the list you want, click <guibutton>Save Changes</guibutton>.
            You can remove unwanted users by clicking the <guibutton>[X]</guibutton> link by that
            user's list order number.
        </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Captions and Patterns</title>
        <para>
            After you've set up all the streams you need on all of your
            distributions, it's time to move on to the next tab in the Subscription
            Details interface: the <guilabel>Captions and Patterns</guilabel> tab.
        </para>

        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/caption-pattern-tab.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            Caption and Pattern objects define the same material that would be
            described in an 853, 854, or 855 MARC tag.  Here you define how your
            issues will be captioned and how often you get them.
        </para>
        <para>
            Click the "Add Caption and Pattern" to get a blank row to work with,
            and set the leftmost dropdown to Basic, Supplement, or Index, depending
            on what you want to define the pattern for.  For common periodicals,
            Basic is often all that's needed.
        </para>
        <para>
            Next, unless you know how to type a JSON representation of your 85X
            tags by hand, click the <guibutton>Wizard</guibutton> button.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/scap-wiz-page-1.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            This Caption and Pattern Wizard is where you'll enter information
            according to Library of Congress-specified standards about how this
            serial works.  The first page of the wizard is for specifying
            enumeration captions (commonly involving particles labeled <guilabel>v.</guilabel> and
            <guilabel>no.</guilabel>).
        </para>
        <para>
            You can have up to six levels of enumeration captions and two
            alternate levels.  Each level except the first and first alternate
            come with attendant questions about how many units of this level
            belong to the higher level.  This is all directly based on subfields
            $a through $h and $u and $v of the MFHD standard.
        </para>
        <para>
            The wizard has several pages, and after you fill out each page the
            way you want, click <guibutton>Next</guibutton> in the upper right corner.  You can go
            back if you've forgotten something by using the <guibutton>Prev</guibutton> button.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/scap-wiz-page-2.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            The wizard's second page is concerned with calendar changes (i.e., at
            what point on the calendar does the highest level enumeration unit
            change).  You can add as many of these as you like, and each one can be
            one of a) the start of a given month, b) the start of a given season,
            or c) a specific date.  This all corresponds to subfield $x of the MFHD
            standard.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/scap-wiz-page-3.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            The wizard's third page is for defining chronology captions.  Make sure
            that each chronology caption you specify is smaller than the last. Only
            mark the <guilabel>Display in Holding Field</guilabel> checkbox if you want the literal
            words <quote>year</quote> and <quote>month</quote> and so on to appear next to values like <quote>2010</quote>
            and <quote>Nov.</quote>
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/scap-wiz-page-4.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            The fourth page of the wizard deals with indicator codes and the
            subfield $w from the MFHD standard.  I recommend setting the first two
            dropdowns as shown in the above image, unless you are a serials
            librarian who knows your stuff and you have a good reason to do
            otherwise. Set your frequency ($w) to the appropriate value for your
            publication.  For truly irregular frequencies, you may wish to select
            <guilabel>use number of issues per year</guilabel>, in which case you enter a raw number
            of issues per year.
        </para>
        <para>
            After you have finished the wizard and clicked Compile Pattern Code,"
            make sure the <guilabel>Active</guilabel> checkbox is marked for the caption and pattern
            object you have just created, and click <guibutton>Save Changes</guibutton>.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/save-scap.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>On to Issuances</title>
        <para>
            We're finally close to the point where we define an initial issuance
            and let Evergreen predict a run of issuances, and attendant items, from
            there.
        </para>
        <para>
            Proceed to the Issuances tab of the Subscription Detail interface, and
            click on <guibutton>New Issuance</guibutton>.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/create-iss-1.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            What we're doing here is hand-entering one example issuance, and you
            should use the *last issuance you have before you want prediction to
            take over.*  So if you want to predict all the issues of a monthly
            periodical beginning with November 2010, enter the information for your
            October 2010 issue.
        </para>
        <para>
            In the holding code section of the New Issuance dialog, click the 
            <guibutton>Wizard</guibutton> button to get a fields tailor-made for the caption and pattern
            you're using, and fill in the information that's appropriate for the
            example issuance you're using. Click <guibutton>Compile</guibutton> when you have all those
            fields filled in.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/create-iss-2.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            Once everything is filled in on your example issue, click <guibutton>Save</guibutton>.  You
            have now given the system everything it needs to predict a run of
            issues (and the attendant copies that will go to your branches).
        </para>
        <para>
            Click the <guibutton>Generate Predictions</guibutton> button.  You'll get a mini-dialog
            asking you how many issues to predict.  If your subscription has an
            end date, you can choose to predict until the subscription's end date.
            If your subscription doesn't have an end date, you can indicate how
            many issues you want the system to predict (so enter 12 if you want
            a year's worth of issues on a monthly publication).
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/predict-how-many.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            After you click <guibutton>Generate</guibutton>, the system should take a moment to predict
            your run of issuances and copies, and then you should see the grid of
            issuances populated below.
        </para>
        <para>
            You can now delete the example issuance that we created for the
            system to base its prediction on.  Mark its checkbox on the left side
            of the grid and click<guibutton>Delete Selected</guibutton>.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/generated-iss-delete-dummy.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            Your subscription is now completely set up.  Let's receive some
            copies.
        </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>
            Batch Receiving
        </title>
        <para>
            The Subscription Details interface has a <guibutton>Batch Item Receive</guibutton> button
            that will take you to the Batch Receiving interface for this
            subscription.
        </para>
        <para>
            Generally, you won't need to edit anything pertaining to the
            subscription itself when receiving items, so you can also get to
            Batch Receiving through the <guimenuitem>Actions for this Item</guimenuitem> menu when
            viewing a record in the catalog (right next to <guimenuitem>Alternate Serial
            Control</guimenuitem> from earlier in this tutorial).
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/batch-receive-choose-iss.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            The Batch Receiving interface will present you with a selection of
            as-yet unreceived issuances.  The earliest expected issuance with
            any as-yet unreceived copies will always be at the top of the list,
            so generally you will click next here.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/batch-receive-simple.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            <quote>Simple</quote> mode for Batch Receiving gives you few options - this is
            how you receive items that won't have barcodes and won't appear
            individually in the catalog.  Each item can have a optional note
            (stored internally; not displayed anywhere as of this writing, but
            not ultimately intended as a publicly-viewable note), and you can
            unmark any rows in the table for items that you have not received.
        </para>
        <para>
            More discussion on how to indicate that you haven't received all the
            items you were expecting will follow a few paragraphs later in this
            tutorial.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you do want to barcode your items, check the <guilabel>Create Units for
            Received Items</guilabel> checkbox in the extreme lower right of the
            interface.
            Units are copy-equivalent objects that will hold a barcode and can
            appear in the catalog (and even be targeted for holds).  Marking
            this checkbox will give you many more fields on each row of the
            receiving table.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/batch-receive-autogen-1.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            If you have a printed stack of barcodes available, you can scan
            each one into the barcode field of each row of the table.  You can
            also let the system generate your barcodes automatically, if you
            so desire.  To accomplish this, mark the auto-generate checkbox,
            and enter your first barcode into the first row of the table. Then
            press the tab key.
        </para>
        <para>
            The rest of the barcode fields will automatically populate with the
            next barcodes in sequence, including check digits.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/batch-receive-autogen-2.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            As for the other fields in the table besides barcode, you can set
            them to whatever values you need. Note that anything with a
            barcode must also have a call number, so you'll have to put
            something there.  Drop-downs for call numbers will be populated
            with any existing call-number associated with the bibliographic
            record for your serial.  You can choose from these call numbers,
            or, if perhaps you're using a call-number-per-issue policy, you
            can create a new call number to apply to the table of items every
            time you receive a batch.
        </para>
        <para>
            To spare you the pain of setting potentially dozens of fields in the
            receiving table individually, you can enter a value into the very
            top row and click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> at the far right to apply that same value
            to its entire column throughout the table.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/batch-receive-apply.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            Now, as for the question of what to do when you didn't receive all
            the items you were supposed to get, you can choose what rows in
            the table you want to represent the unreceived items.  So if you
            only received six out of the expected eight, and you're trying to
            distribute items evenly between two branches, you might unmark two
            checkboxes as shown in the image below.
        </para>
        <para>
            Not only does unmarking the checkbox turn the row grey and prevent
            that item from being received when you later click <guibutton>Receive Selected
            Items</guibutton> later, but the system also remembers which items you have not
            yet received, so that you can receive them later if they arrive
            separately.  The system's keeping track of unreceived items will
            also facilitate a claiming interface, when that is designed and
            implemented.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/batch-receive-partial.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            When you've filled in all the item rows, look in the lower left of
            the interface for the <guibutton>Receive Selected Items</guibutton> button and click
            that.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/batch-receive-receive.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            You see that the items that were marked for receipt are now cleared
            from this interface, as they have been received.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/batch-receive-received.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            Since we left all <guilabel>Routing List</guilabel> checkboxes marked, if any of the items
            we just received actually have a routing list, we now have another tab
            open with a routing list ready to print.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/batch-receive-print-routing.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <para>
            If you set up a routing list as described earlier in this tutorial,
            yours will look like this.  Multiple routing lists will automatically
            print on separate pages.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you received some items with a barcode (and if the copy template
            and shelving location you used are OPAC visible), you can now see the
            items you received in the catalog.
        </para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../media/received-items-in-catalog.png" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </simplesect>
</chapter>

