<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="cataloging" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="EN"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<title>Cataloging</title>
<section xml:id="adding_holdings">
<title>Adding Holdings</title>
	<simplesect xml:id="Unified_Volume_Copy_Creator" >
		<title>Unified Volume Copy Creator</title>
		<simpara>The cataloging module in Evergreen version 2.1 now includes a unified volume/copy creator that enables a user to create volumes and copies in a 
		unified screen.  This function consolidates the process of creating volume and copy records.</simpara>
		<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Administrative Settings</emphasis></simpara>
		<simpara>By default, the cataloging interface that existed in 2.0 will display in 2.1.  To use the <emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis>, 
		you must turn it on in the Admin module.  You must log out of Evergreen and log back in for the changes to take effect.</simpara>
		<simpara>To turn on the <emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis>:</simpara>
		<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Select <emphasis role="strong">Admin &#8594; Local Administration &#8594; Library Settings Editor</emphasis>
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Scroll down to <emphasis role="strong">GUI: Unified Volume/Item Creator/Editor</emphasis>, and click <emphasis role="strong">Edit</emphasis>.
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Select <emphasis role="strong">True</emphasis> to turn on the editor.
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<simpara>After you turn on the <emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis>, it will display, by default, in a vertical panel. You may display the 
		<emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis> in a horizontal panel.  You must log out of Evergreen and log back in for the changes to take effect.
		</simpara>
		<simpara>To choose the horizontal display of the <emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis>:</simpara>

		<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Select <emphasis role="strong">Admin &#8594; Local Administration &#8594; Library Settings Editor</emphasis>.
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Scroll down to <emphasis role="strong">GUI: Horizontal layout for Volume/Copy Creator/Editor</emphasis>, and click <emphasis role="strong">Edit</emphasis>.
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Select <emphasis role="strong">True</emphasis> to view the panel horizontally.
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Add volumes and items using the Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis></simpara>
		<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis> enables you to edit call numbers and copy information in separate panes on a single,
		unified screen.</simpara>
		<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis> appears when you access the following links:</simpara>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Holdings Maintenance &#8594; Add items
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Holdings Maintenance &#8594; Add volumes
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Holdings Maintenance &#8594; Edit items
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Holdings Maintenance &#8594; Replace barcode
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Create New MARC Record &#8594; Fast Item Add
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		Record Summary &#8594; Add Volumes. 
		</simpara>
		<note>
		<simpara>The ability to <emphasis role="strong">Add Volumes</emphasis> from the <emphasis role="strong">Record Summary</emphasis> 
		is also a new functionality in 2.1.</simpara>
		</note>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<simpara>In the following example, you will use the <emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis> to add multiple volumes and copies to 
		bibliographic record from the Holdings Maintenance screen:</simpara>
		<orderedlist>
		<listitem><simpara>Retrieve a record.</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Click the <emphasis role="strong">Actions for this Record -&#8594; Holdings Maintenance</emphasis></simpara></listitem>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/unified_volume_copy_creator1.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		<listitem>
		<simpara>On the <emphasis role="strong">Holdings Maintenance</emphasis> screen, highlight the branch(es) to which you would like to add volumes.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Right click, and click <emphasis role="strong">Add Volumes.</emphasis></simpara>
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/unified_volume_copy_creator2.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis> opens.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">Record Summary</emphasis> appears in the top panel.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		The <emphasis role="strong">Copy Templates</emphasis> enables you to predefine copy settings.  This panel displayed in the 
		<emphasis role="strong">Copy Editor</emphasis> 
		in 2.0.
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		The <emphasis role="strong">Volume and Copy Creator</emphasis> enables you to add volumes and copies individually or in batch.
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>
		The <emphasis role="strong">Copy Viewer</emphasis> enables you to set parameters for each copy.
		</simpara>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<listitem><simpara>A <emphasis role="strong">Classification</emphasis> and a <emphasis role="strong">Call Number</emphasis> appear for each volume.</simpara>
		<note>
		<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">Classification</emphasis> is derived from following setting in the Admin module: <emphasis role="strong">Admin</emphasis> 
		&#8594; <emphasis role="strong">Local Administration</emphasis> &#8594; <emphasis role="strong">Library Settings Editor</emphasis> &#8594; 
		<emphasis role="strong">Cataloging: Default Classification Scheme</emphasis>.  The <emphasis role="strong">Call Number</emphasis> is derived from the MARC 
		record.</simpara>
		</note>
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/unified_volume_copy_creator3.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>You can add volume and copy information to each row individually or in batch.  In the dark gray row, select a classification, prefix, call number, 
		and suffix (if needed) from the drop down menus and apply those settings in batch to all of the volumes that you created.  Click 
		<emphasis role="strong">Apply</emphasis>.</simpara>
		<note><simpara>The prefix and suffix drop down menus are populated by entries in the <emphasis role="strong">Admin</emphasis> menu.  See 
		<link linkend="Call_Number_Prefixes_and_Suffixes">Call Number Prefixes and Suffixes</link>.
		</simpara></note>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/unified_volume_copy_creator4.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Enter the number of copies and barcodes that you want to add. The barcodes that you enter will populate in the 
		<emphasis role="strong">Copy Editor</emphasis>.</simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/unified_volume_copy_creator5.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>If desired, select a copy template from the template drop down menu, and click <emphasis role="strong">Apply</emphasis>. 
		 Changes to copies appear in green.</simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/unified_volume_copy_creator6.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Make any other changes that you would like to make in the <emphasis role="strong">Copy Editor</emphasis>.</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Click <emphasis role="strong">Create Volumes/Items.</emphasis></simpara></listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">Holdings Maintenance</emphasis> screen will refresh to show the addition of the volumes and copies.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</simplesect>
	<simplesect xml:id="monograph_parts">
		<title>Monograph Parts</title>
		<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Monograph Parts</emphasis> enables you to differentiate between parts of monographs or other multi-part items.  This feature 
		enables catalogers to describe items more precisely by labeling the parts of an item.  For example, catalogers might identify the parts of a monograph or the 
		discs of a DVD set.  This feature also allows patrons more flexibility when placing holds on multi-part items.  A patron could place a hold on a specific disc 
		of a DVD set if they want to access a specific season or episode rather than an entire series.</simpara>
		<simpara>No new permissions or administrative settings are needed to use this feature.</simpara>
		<simpara>To add a monograph part to an existing record in the catalog:</simpara>
		<orderedlist>		
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Retrieve a record.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for this Record &#8594; Manage Parts</emphasis></simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/monograph_parts1.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		  <textobject><phrase>monograph_parts1</phrase></textobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Click <emphasis role="strong">New Monograph Part</emphasis></simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Enter the <emphasis role="strong">label</emphasis> that you want to appear to the user in the catalog, and 
		click <emphasis role="strong">Save</emphasis>.</simpara> 
		<simpara>This will create a list of monograph parts from which you can choose when you create a volume and copy.</simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/monograph_parts2.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem> 
		<listitem>		
		<simpara>Add a volume and copy.  To add a volume and copy to your workstation library, click the <emphasis role="strong">Add Volumes</emphasis> link in the 
		<emphasis role="strong">Record Summary</emphasis> at the top of the bibliographic record, or click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for this Record &#8594; Add 
		Volumes</emphasis>.</simpara>
		<simpara>To add a volume and copy to your workstation library or other libraries, click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for this Record &#8594; Holdings 
		Maintenance &#8594; Add Volumes</emphasis>.</simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/monograph_parts3.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis> opens. Enter the number of volumes that you want to add to the catalog and 
		the volume description.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Enter the number of copies and barcode(s) of each item.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Select the <emphasis role="strong">part designation</emphasis> from the drop down menu adjacent to the barcode field.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Apply a template to the copies, or edit fields in the <emphasis role="strong">Copy Editor</emphasis>.</simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/monograph_parts4.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Click <emphasis role="strong">Create Volumes/Items</emphasis>.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">Holdings Maintenance</emphasis> screen will refresh to demonstrate the addition of the volume, copy, and part.  
		These fields also appear in the OPAC View.</simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/monograph_parts5.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</simplesect>
	<simplesect xml:id="conjoined_items">
    		<title>Conjoined Items</title>
		<simpara>Prior to Evergreen version 2.1, items could be attached to only one bibliographic record.  The Conjoined Items feature in Evergreen 2.1 enables catalogers to 
		link items to multiple bibliographic records.  This feature will enable more precise cataloging.  For example, catalogers will be able to indicate items that 
		are printed back to back, are bilingual, are part of a bound volume, are part of a set, or are available as an e-reader pre-load.  This feature will also help the 
		user retrieve more relevant search results.  For example, a librarian catalogs a multi-volume festschrift.  She can create a bibliographic record for the 
		festschrift and a record for each volume.  She can link the items on each volume to the festschrift record so that a patron could search for a volume or the 
		festschrift and retrieve information about both works.
		In the example below, a librarian has created a bibliographic record for two bestselling items.  These books are available as physical copies in the library, and they 
		are available as e-reader downloads.  The librarian will link the copy of the Kindle to the bibliographic records that are available on the e-reader.</simpara>
		<simpara>The Conjoined Items feature was designed so that you can link items between bibliographic records when you have the item in hand, or when the item is 
		not physically present.  Both processes are described here.  The steps are fewer if you have the item in hand, but both processes accomplish the same task.  
		This documentalso demonstrates the process to edit or delete links between items and bibliographic records. Finally, the permission a cataloger needs to use 
		this feature is listed.</simpara>
		<formalpara><title>Scenario 1: I want to link an item to another bibliographic record, but I do not have the item in hand</title><para>1) Retrieve the 
		bibliographic record to which you would like to link an item.</para></formalpara>
		<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for this Record &#8594; Mark as Target for Conjoined Items.</emphasis></simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
 		 <imageobject>
  			<imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/conj1.jpg"/>
 		 </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>A confirmation message will appear.  Click <emphasis role="strong">OK.</emphasis></simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>In a new tab, retrieve the bibliographic record with the item that you want to link to the other record.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for this Record &#8594; Holdings Maintenance.</emphasis></simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Select the copy that you want to link to the other bibliographic record.  Right-click, or click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for Selected 
		Rows &#8594; Link as Conjoined Items to Previously Marked Bib Record.</emphasis></simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/conj2.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">Manage Conjoined Items</emphasis> interface opens in a new tab.  This interface enables you to confirm the success of 
		the link, and to change the peer type if desired.  The <emphasis role="strong">Result</emphasis> column indicates that you created a successful link between 
		the item and the bib record.</simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/conj3.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		<simpara>The default peer type, <emphasis role="strong">Back-to-back</emphasis>, was set as the peer type for our item.  To change a peer type after the 
		link has been created, right-click or click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for Selected Items &#8594; Change Peer Type</emphasis>.  A drop down menu 
		will appear.  Select the desired peer type, and click <emphasis role="strong">OK.</emphasis></simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/conj4.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">Result</emphasis> column will indicate that the <emphasis role="strong">Peer Type</emphasis> [has been] 
		<emphasis role="strong">Updated.</emphasis></simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/conj5.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>To confirm the link between the item and the desired bib record, reload the tab containing the bib record to which you linked the item. Click the link 
		for <emphasis role="strong">Linked Titles.</emphasis></simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/conj6.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>To view the copy details, including the peer type, click <emphasis role="strong">Copy Details.</emphasis></simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/conj7.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		<simpara>Items can be linked to multiple bibliographic records simultaneously.  If you click the linked titles button in the copy details, then you 
		will retrieve a list of bibliographic records to which this item is linked.</simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/conj8.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<formalpara><title>Scenario 2: I want to link an item to another bibliographic record, and I do have the item in hand</title><para>1) Retrieve the bibliographic 
		record to which you would like to add the item.</para></formalpara>
		<orderedlist>
		<listitem>		
		<simpara>Click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for this Record &#8594; Manage Conjoined Items.</emphasis></simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/conj9.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>A note in the bottom left corner of the screen will confirm that the record was targeted for linkage with conjoined items, and the 
		<emphasis role="strong">Manage Conjoined Items</emphasis> screen will appear.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Select the peer type from the drop down menu, and scan in the barcode of the item that you want to link to this record.</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Click <emphasis role="strong">Link to Bib (Submit).</emphasis></simpara>
		
		<mediaobject>
		  <imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../media/conj10.jpg"/>
		  </imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>The linked item will appear in the screen. The <emphasis role="strong">Result</emphasis> column indicates Success.</simpara>
		</listitem>	
		<listitem>
		<simpara>To confirm the linkage, click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for this Record &#8594; OPAC View.</emphasis></simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>When the bibliographic record appears, click <emphasis role="strong">Reload.  Linked Titles</emphasis> will show the linked title and item.</simpara>
		<formalpara><title>Scenario 3: I want to edit or break the link between a copy and a bibliographic record</title><para>1) Retrieve the bibliographic record 
		that has a copy linked to it.</para></formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for this Record &#8594; Manage Conjoined Items.</emphasis></simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Select the copy that you want to edit, and right-click or click <emphasis role="strong">Actions for Selected Items.</emphasis></simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<simpara>Make any changes, and click <emphasis role="strong">OK.</emphasis></simpara>
		</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<simpara>Required permission: UPDATE_COPY  -  Link items to bibliographic records</simpara>
	</simplesect>
</section>
<section xml:id="Call_Number_Prefixes_and_Suffixes">
	 <title>Call Number Prefixes and Suffixes</title>
	<simpara>In Evergreen version 2.1, you can configure call number prefixes and suffixes in the Admin module.  This feature ensures more precise cataloging because each 
	cataloger will have access to an identical drop down menu of call number prefixes and suffixes that are used at his library.  In addition, it may streamline 
	cataloging workflow.  Catalogers can use a drop down menu to enter call number prefixes and suffixes rather than entering them manually.  You can also run reports on 
	call number prefixes and suffixes that would facilitate collection development and maintenance.</simpara>
	<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Configure call number prefixes</emphasis>:</simpara>
	<simpara>Call number prefixes are codes that precede a call number.</simpara>
	<simpara>To configure call number prefixes:</simpara>
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	<listitem>
	<simpara>
	Select <emphasis role="strong">Admin &#8594; Server Administration &#8594; Call Number Prefixes</emphasis>.
	</simpara>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<simpara>
	Click <emphasis role="strong">New Prefix</emphasis>.
	</simpara>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<simpara>
	Enter the <emphasis role="strong">call number label</emphasis> that will appear on the item.
	</simpara>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<simpara>
	Select the <emphasis role="strong">owning library</emphasis> from the drop down menu. Staff at this library, and its descendant org units, with the appropriate 
	permissions, will be able to apply this call number prefix.
	</simpara>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<simpara>
	Click <emphasis role="strong">Save</emphasis>.
	</simpara>
	</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../media/Call_Number_Prefixes_and_Suffixes_2_22.jpg"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	
	<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Configure call number suffixes</emphasis>:</simpara>
	<simpara>Call number suffixes are codes that succeed a call number.</simpara>
	<simpara>To configure call number suffixes:</simpara>
	<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
	<listitem>
	<simpara>
	Select <emphasis role="strong">Admin &#8594; Server Administration &#8594; Call Number Suffixes</emphasis>.
	</simpara>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<simpara>
	Click <emphasis role="strong">New Suffix</emphasis>.
	</simpara>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<simpara>
	Enter the <emphasis role="strong">call number label</emphasis> that will appear on the item.
	</simpara>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<simpara>
	Select the <emphasis role="strong">owning library</emphasis> from the drop down menu. Staff at this library, and its descendant org units, with the appropriate 
	permissions, will be able to apply this call number suffix.
	</simpara>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<simpara>
	Click <emphasis role="strong">Save</emphasis>.
	</simpara>
	</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../media/Call_Number_Prefixes_and_Suffixes_2_21.jpg"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	
	<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Apply Call Number Prefixes and Suffixes</emphasis></simpara>
	<simpara>You can apply call number prefixes and suffixes to items from a pre-configured list in the <emphasis role="strong">Unified Volume/Copy Creator</emphasis>.  See 
	the section, <link linkend="Unified_Volume_Copy_Creator">Unified Volume Copy Creator</link>, for an example.</simpara>
</section>
</chapter>


