<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<sect1 version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" 
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

	<title>Grammar of JSON Queries</title>

	<para>
		<author>
			<personname>
				<firstname>Scott</firstname>
				<surname>McKellar</surname>
			</personname>
			<affiliation>
				<orgname>Equinox Software, Inc.</orgname>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</para>


	<sect2>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para> The format of this grammar approximates Extended Backus-Naur notation. However it is
			intended as input to human beings, not to parser generators such as Lex or Yacc. Do not
			expect formal rigor. Sometimes narrative text will explain things that are clumsy to
			express in formal notation. More often, the text will restate or summarize the formal
			productions. </para>
		<para> Conventions: </para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The grammar is a series of productions.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A production consists of a name, followed by "::=", followed by a definition
					for the name. The name identifies a grammatical construct that can appear on the
					right side of another production.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Literals (including punctuation) are enclosed in 'single quotes', or in
					"double quotes" if case is not significant.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A single quotation mark within a literal is escaped with a preceding
					backslash: 'dog\'s tail'.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>If a construct can be defined more than one way, then the alternatives may
					appear in separate productions; or, they may appear in the same production,
					separated by pipe symbols. The choice between these representations is of only
					cosmetic significance.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A construct enclosed within square brackets is optional.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A construct enclosed within curly braces may be repeated zero or more
					times.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>JSON allows arbitrary white space between tokens. To avoid ugly clutter, this
					grammar ignores the optional white space. </para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>In many cases a production defines a JSON object, i.e. a list of name-value
					pairs, separated by commas. Since the order of these name/value pairs is not
					significant, the grammar will not try to show all the possible sequences. In
					general it will present the required pairs first, if any, followed by any
					optional elements.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para> Since both EBNF and JSON use curly braces and square brackets, pay close attention to
			whether these characters are in single quotes. If they're in single quotes, they are
			literal elements of the JSON notation. Otherwise they are elements of the EBNF notation.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>Primitives</title>
		<para> We'll start by defining some primitives, to get them out of the way. They're mostly
			just what you would expect. </para>

		<productionset>
			<production xml:id="ebnf.string">
				<lhs> string </lhs>
				<rhs> '"' chars '"' </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.chars">
				<lhs> chars </lhs>
				<rhs> any valid sequence of UTF-8 characters, with certain special characters
					escaped according to JSON rules </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.integer_literal">
				<lhs> integer_literal </lhs>
				<rhs> [ sign ] digit { digit } </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.sign">
				<lhs> sign </lhs>
				<rhs> '+' | '-' </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.digit">
				<lhs> digit </lhs>
				<rhs>digit = '0' | '1' | '2' | '3' | '4' | '5' | '6' | '7' | '8' | '9'</rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.integer_string">
				<lhs> integer_string </lhs>
				<rhs> '"' integer_literal '"' </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.integer">
				<lhs> integer </lhs>
				<rhs> integer_literal | integer_string </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.number">
				<lhs> number </lhs>
				<rhs> any valid character sequence that is numeric according to JSON rules </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> When json_query requires an integral value, it will usually accept a quoted string
			and convert it to an integer by brute force – to zero if necessary. Likewise it may
			truncate a floating point number to an integral value. Scientific notation will be
			accepted but may not give the intended results. </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.boolean">
				<lhs> boolean </lhs>
				<rhs> 'true' | 'false' | string | number </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The preferred way to encode a boolean is with the JSON reserved word true or false,
			in lower case without quotation marks. The string <literal>true</literal>, in upper,
			lower, or mixed case, is another way to encode true. Any other string evaluates to
			false. </para>
		<para> As an accommodation to perl, numbers may be used as booleans. A numeric value of 1
			means true, and any other numeric value means false. </para>
		<para> Any other valid JSON value, such as an array, will be accepted as a boolean but
			interpreted as false. </para>
		<para> The last couple of primitives aren't really very primitive, but we introduce them
			here for convenience: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.class_name">
				<lhs> class_name </lhs>
				<rhs> string </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> A class_name is a special case of a string: the name of a class as defined by the
			IDL. The class may refer either to a database table or to a source_definition, which is
			a subquery. </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.field_name">
				<lhs> field_name </lhs>
				<rhs> string </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> A field_name is another special case of a string: the name of a non-virtual field as
			defined by the IDL. A field_name is also a column name for the table corresponding to
			the relevant class. </para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>Query</title>

		<para> The following production applies not only to the main query but also to most
			subqueries. </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.query">
				<lhs> query </lhs>
				<rhs> '{'<sbr/> '"from"' ':' from_list<sbr/> [ ',' '"select"' ':' select_list
					]<sbr/> [ ',' '"where"' ':' where_condition ]<sbr/> [ ',' '"having"' ':'
					where_condition ]<sbr/> [ ',' '"order_by"' ':' order_by_list ]<sbr/> [ ','
					'"limit"' ':' integer ]<sbr/> [ ',' '"offset"' ':' integer ]<sbr/> [ ','
					'"distinct"' ':' boolean ]<sbr/> [ ',' '"no_i18n"' ':' boolean ]<sbr/> '}'
				</rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> Except for the <literal>"distinct"</literal> and <literal>no_i18n</literal> entries,
			each name/value pair represents a major clause of the SELECT statement. The name/value
			pairs may appear in any order. </para>
		<para> There is no name/value pair for the GROUP BY clause, because json_query generates it
			automatically according to information encoded elsewhere. </para>
		<para> The <literal>"distinct"</literal> entry, if present and true, tells json_query that
			it may have to create a GROUP BY clause. If not present, it defaults to false. </para>
		<para> The <literal>"no_i18n"</literal> entry, if present and true, tells json_query to
			suppress internationalization. If not present, it defaults to false. (Note that
				<literal>"no_i18n"</literal> contains the digit one, not the letter ell.) </para>
		<para> The values for <literal>limit</literal> and <literal>offset</literal> provide the
			arguments of the LIMIT and OFFSET clauses, respectively, of the SQL statement. Each
			value should be non-negative, if present, or else the SQL won't work. </para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2><title>FROM Clause</title>
		<para>
			The object identified by <literal>“from”</literal> encodes the FROM clause of
			the SQL.  The associated value may be a string, an array, or a JSON object.
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.from_list_0">
				<lhs> from_list </lhs>
				<rhs> class_name </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			If <literal>from_list</literal> is a <literal>class_name</literal>, the
			json_query inserts the corresponding table name or subquery into the FROM
			clause, using the <literal>class_name</literal> as an alias for the table
			or subquery.  The class must be defined as non-virtual in the IDL.
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.from_list_1">
				<lhs> from_list </lhs>
				<rhs> '['  string  {  ','  parameter  }  ']' </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.parameter">
				<lhs> parameter </lhs>
				<rhs> string  |  number  |  'null' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			If from_list is a JSON array, then it represents a table-like function from
			which the SQL statement will select rows, using a SELECT clause consisting
			of “SELECT *” (regardless of the select_list supplied by the method parameter).
		</para>
		<para>
			The first entry in the array is the name of the function.  It must be a string
			naming a stored function.  Each subsequent entry is a function parameter.  If
			it is a string or a number, json_query will insert it into a comma-separated
			parameter list, enclosed in quotes, with any special characters escaped as needed.
			If it is the JSON reserved word <literal>null</literal>, json_query will insert
			it into the parameter list as a null value.
		</para>
		<para>
			If <literal>from_list</literal> is a JSON object, it must contain exactly one entry.
			The key of this entry must be the name of a non-virtual class defined in the IDL.
			This class will be the top-level class of the FROM clause, the only one named
			outside of a JOIN clause.
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.from_list_2">
				<lhs> from_list </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' class_name ':' join_list '}' </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.join_list_0">
				<lhs> join_list </lhs>
				<rhs> class_name </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.join_list_1">
				<lhs> join_list </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' join_def { ',' join_def } '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			If the associated data is a <literal>class_name</literal>, json_query will
			construct an INNER JOIN clause joining the class to the top-level clause,
			using the columns specified by the IDL for such a join.
		</para>
		<para>
			Otherwise, the associated data must be a JSON object with one or more entries,
			each entry defining a join:
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.join_def">
				<lhs> join_def </lhs>
				<rhs>
					class_name  ':'<sbr/>
					'{'<sbr/>
					[  '”type”'      ':'  string      ]<sbr/>
					[  '”field”'     ':'  field_name  ]<sbr/>
					[  '”fkey”'      ':'  field_name  ]<sbr/>
					[  '”filter”'    ':'  where_condition  ]<sbr/>
					[  '”filter_op”' ':'  string      ]<sbr/>
					[  '”join”'      ':'  join_list   ]<sbr/>
					'}'
				</rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			The data portion of the <literal>“join_type”</literal> entry tells json_query
			whether to use a left join, right join, full join, or inner join.  The values
			<literal>“left”</literal>, <literal>“right”</literal>, and <literal>“full”</literal>,
			in upper, lower, or mixed case, have the obvious meanings.  If the
			<literal>“join_type”</literal> entry has any other value, or is not present,
			json_query constructs an inner join.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>“field”</literal> and <literal>“fkey”</literal> attributes specify the
			columns to be equated in the join condition.  The <literal>“field”</literal>
			attribute refers to the column in the joined table, i.e. the one named by the
			<literal>join_def</literal>.  The <literal>“fkey”</literal> attribute refers to the
			corresponding column in the other table, i.e. the one named outside the
			<literal>join_def</literal> – either the top-level table or a table named by some
			other <literal>join_def</literal>.
		</para>
		<para>
			It may be tempting to suppose that <literal>“fkey”</literal> stands for “foreign key”,
			and therefore refers to a column in the child table that points to the key of a
			parent table.  Resist the temptation; the labels are arbitrary.  The json_query
			method doesn't care which table is the parent and which is the child.
		</para>
		<para>
			These relationships are best explained with an example.  The following
			<literal>from_list</literal>:
		</para>

		<informalexample>
			<programlisting language="JSON">
	{
	    "aou": {
	        "asv": {
	            "type" : "left",
	            "fkey" : "id",
	            "field" : "owner"
	        }
	    }
	}
			</programlisting>
		</informalexample>

		<para>
			...turns into the following FROM clause:
		</para>

		<informalexample>
			<programlisting language="SQL">
	FROM
	    actor.org_unit AS "aou"
	        LEFT JOIN action.survey AS "asv"
	            ON ( "asv".owner = "aou".id )
			</programlisting>
		</informalexample>

		<para>
			Note in this example that <literal>“fkey”</literal> refers to a column of the
			class <literal>“aou”</literal>, and <literal>“field”</literal> refers to a
			column of the class <literal>“asv”</literal>.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you specify only one of the two columns, json_query will try to identify the
			other one from the IDL. However, if you specify only the column from the parent
			table, this attempt will probably fail.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you specify both columns, json_query will use the column names you specify,
			without verifying them with a lookup in the IDL.  By this means you can perform
			a join using a linkage that the IDL doesn't define.  Of course, if the columns
			don't exist in the database, the query will fail when json_query tries to execute it.
		</para>
		<para>
			Using the columns specified, either explicitly or implicitly, the json_query
			method constructs a join condition.  With raw SQL it is possible (though
			rarely useful) to join two tables by an inequality.  However the json_query
			method always uses a simple equality condition.
		</para>
		<para>
			Using a <literal>“filter”</literal> entry in the join_def, you can apply one
			or more additional conditions to the JOIN clause, typically to restrict the
			join to certain rows of the joined table.  The data associated with the
			<literal>“filter”</literal> key is the same sort of
			<literal>where_condition</literal> that you use for a WHERE clause
			(discussed below).
		</para>
		<para>
			If the string associated with the <literal>“filter_op”</literal> entry is
			<literal>“OR”</literal> in upper, lower, or mixed case, then the json_query
			method uses OR to connect the standard join condition to any additional
			conditions supplied by a <literal>“filter”</literal> entry.
		</para>
		<para>
			(Note that if the <literal>where_condition</literal> supplies multiple
			conditions, they will be connected by AND.  You will probably want to move
			them down a layer – enclose them in parentheses, in effect – to avoid a
			confusing mixture of ANDs and ORs.)
		</para>
		<para>
			If the <literal>“filter_op”</literal> entry carries any other value, or if
			it is absent, then the json_query method uses AND.  In the absence of a
			<literal>“filter”</literal> entry, <literal>“filter_op”</literal> has no effect.
		</para>
		<para>
			A <literal>“join”</literal> entry in a <literal>join_def</literal> specifies
			another layer of join.  The class named in the subjoin is joined to the class
			named by the <literal>join_def</literal> to which it is subordinate.  By this
			means you can encode multiple joins in a hierarchy.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2><title>SELECT Clause</title>
		<para>
			If a query does not contain an entry for <literal>“select”</literal>, json_query
			will construct a default SELECT clause.  The default includes every non-virtual
			field from the top-level class of the FROM clause, as defined by the IDL.  The
			result is similar to SELECT *, except:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The default includes only the fields defined in the IDL.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The columns will appear in the same order in which they appear in the IDL,
				regardless of the order in which the database defines them.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>
			There are other ways to specify a default SELECT list, as shown below.
		</para>
		<para>
			If a <literal>"select"</literal> entry is present, the associated value must
			be a JSON object, keyed on class names:
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.select_list">
				<lhs> select_list </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' class_name ':' field_list { ',' class_name ':' field_list } '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			The <literal>class_name</literal> must identify either the top-level class or
			a class belonging to one of the joins.  Otherwise json_query will silently
			ignore the <literal>select_list</literal>.
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.field_list_0">
				<lhs> field_list </lhs>
				<rhs> 'null'  |  '”*”' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			If a field_list is either the JSON reserved word <literal>null</literal>
			(in lower case) or an asterisk in double quotes, json_query constructs a
			default SELECT list – provided that the class is the top-level class of the
			query.  If the class belongs to a join somewhere, json_query ignores the
			<literal>field_list</literal>.
		</para>
		<para>
			More commonly, the <literal>field_list</literal> is a JSON array of zero or
			more field specifications:
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.field_list_1">
				<lhs> field_list </lhs>
				<rhs> '['  [  field_spec  {  ','  field_spec  }  ]  ']' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			If the array is empty, json_query will construct a default SELECT list for
			the class – again, provided that the class is the top-level class in the query.
		</para>
		<para>
			In the simplest case, a field specification may name a non-virtual field
			defined in the IDL:
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.field_spec_0">
				<lhs> field_spec </lhs>
				<rhs> field_name </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			In some cases json_query constructs a call to the
			<literal>oils_i18n_xlate</literal> function to internationalize the value of the
			selected column.  Specifically, it does so if all the following are true:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>the settings file defines a locale;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>in the field definition for the field in the IDL, the tag
				<literal>“il8n”</literal> is present and true;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>the query does <emphasis>not</emphasis> include the
				<literal>"no_il8n"</literal> tag (or includes it with a value of false).</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>
			A field specification may be a JSON object:
		</para>
		
		<productionset>
			
			<production xml:id="ebnf.field_spec_1">
				<lhs> field_spec </lhs>
				<rhs>
					'{'<sbr/>
					'”column”'  ':'  <sbr/>
					[ ',' '”alias”'  ':'  string  ]<sbr/>
					[ ',' '”aggregate”'  ':'  boolean  ]<sbr/>
					[ ',' transform_spec  ]<sbr/>
					'}'
				</rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			The <literal>“column”</literal> entry provides the column name, which must
			be defined as non-virtual in the IDL.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>“alias”</literal> entry provides a column alias.  If no alias
			is specified, json_query uses the column name as its own alias.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>“aggregate”</literal> entry has no effect on the SELECT clause
			itself.  Rather, it affects the construction of a GROUP BY class.  If there
			is an <literal>“aggregate”</literal> entry for any field, then json_query builds
			a GROUP BY clause listing every column that is <emphasis>not</emphasis> tagged
			for aggregation (or that carries an <literal>“aggregate”</literal> entry with
			a value of false).  If <emphasis>all</emphasis> columns are tagged for
			aggregation, then json_query omits the GROUP BY clause.
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.transform_spec_0">
				<lhs> transform_spec </lhs>
				<rhs>
					'”transform”'  ':'  string  ]<sbr/>
					[ ',' '”result_field”  ':'  string  ]<sbr/>
					[ ',' '”params”  ':' param_list  ]
				</rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			When a <literal>transform_spec</literal> is present, json_query selects the
			return value of a function instead of selecting the column directly.  The entry
			for <literal>“transform”</literal> provides the name of the function, and the
			column name (as specified by the <literal>“column”</literal> tag), qualified by
			the class name, is the argument to the function.  For example, you might use such
			a function to format a date or time, or otherwise transform a column value.
			You might also use an aggregate function such as SUM, COUNT, or MAX (possibly
			together with the <literal>“aggregate”</literal> tag).
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>“result_field”</literal> entry, when present, specifies a subcolumn
			of the function's return value.  The resulting SQL encloses the function call
			in parentheses, and follows it with a period and the subcolumn name.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>“params”</literal> entry, if present, provides a possibly empty
			array of additional parameter values, either strings, numbers, or nulls:
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.param_list">
				<lhs> param_list </lhs>
				<rhs> '['  [  parameter  {  ','  parameter  }  ]  ']' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para>
			Such parameter values are enclosed in single quotes, with any special characters
			escaped as needed, and inserted after the column name as additional parameters
			to the function.  You might, for example, use an additional parameter to provide
			a format string for a reformatting function.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2><title>WHERE Clause</title>
		<para> There are two types of <literal>where_condition</literal>: objects and arrays.
			Of these, the object type is the more fundamental, and occurs at some level in every
			<literal>where_condition</literal>.  The array type is mainly a way of circumventing
			a limitation of the object type. </para>
 		<para> The object type of <literal>where_condition</literal> is a comma-separated list
			of one or more <literal>conditions</literal>: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.where_condition_0">
				<lhs> where_condition </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' condition { ',' condition } '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The generated SQL will include a code fragment for each <literal>condition</literal>,
			joined by AND (or in some cases by OR, as described below). </para>
		<para> As usual for entries in a JSON object, each <literal>condition</literal> consists
			of a unique string to serve as a key, a colon, and an associated value. </para>
		<para> The key string may be the name of a column belonging to the relevant table, or
			it may be an operator string.  In order to distinguish it from any possible column
			name, an operator string always begins with a plus sign or minus sign. </para>
		<para> JSON requires that every key string be unique within an object.  This requirement
			imposes some awkward limitations on a JSON query.  For example, you might want to
			express two conditions for the same column: id &gt; 10 and id != 25.  Since each of
			those conditions would have the same key string, namely “id”, you can't put them
			into the same JSON object. </para>
		<para> The solution is to put such conflicting conditions in separate JSON objects, and
			put the objects into an array: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.where_condition_1">
				<lhs> where_condition </lhs>
				<rhs> '[' where_condition { ',' where_condition } ']' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The resulting SQL encloses each subordinate set of <literal>conditions</literal>
			in parentheses, and connects the sets with AND (or in some cases OR, as described
			below).  It's possible to put only a single <literal>where_condition</literal> in
			the array; the result is to add a layer of parentheses around the condition. </para>
		<para> There are two kinds of <literal>condition</literal> where the operator begins
			with a plus sign.  In the simpler case, the associated data is simply a column name:
		</para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.condition_0">
				<lhs> condition </lhs>
				<rhs> plus_class ':' field_name </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> A <literal>plus_class</literal> is a string that begins with a plus sign.
			The rest of the string, after the plus sign, must be the class name for the table
			to which the column belongs. </para>
		<para> If the column is a boolean, then the resulting SQL uses it (as qualified by the
			class name) as a stand-alone condition. </para>
		<para> Otherwise, this kind of syntax provides a way to place a column on the right side
			of a comparison operator.  For example: </para>

		<informalexample>
			<programlisting language="JSON">
	{
	    "from":"aou",
	    "select": { "aou":[ "id", "name" ] },
	    "where": {
	        "id": {
	            "&gt;": { "+aou":"parent_ou" }
	        }
	    }
	}
			</programlisting>
		</informalexample>

		<para> The resulting SQL: </para>

		<informalexample>
			<programlisting language="SQL">
	SELECT
	    "aou".id AS "id",
	    "aou".name AS "name"
	FROM
	    actor.org_unit AS "aou"
	WHERE
	    (
	        "aou".id &gt; (  "aou".parent_ou  )
	    );
			</programlisting>
		</informalexample>

		<para> The other type of <literal>condition</literal> that uses a
			<literal>plus_class</literal> applies a specified class name to a
			<literal>where_condition</literal>: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.condition_1">
				<lhs> condition </lhs>
				<rhs> plus_class ':' where_condition </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The resulting SQL is enclosed in parentheses, and qualifies the columns with
			the specified class name.  This syntax provides a mechanism to shift the class
			context – i.e. to refer to one class in a context that would otherwise refer to
			a different class. </para>
		<para> Ordinarily the class name must be a valid non-virtual class defined in the IDL,
			and applicable to the associated <literal>where_condition</literal>.  There is at
			least one peculiar exception.  The JSON fragment: </para>

		<informalexample>
			<programlisting language="JSON">
	"+abc": { "+xyz":"frobozz" }
			</programlisting>
		</informalexample>

		<para> ...is rendered as: </para>

		<informalexample>
			<programlisting language="SQL">
	(  "xyz".frobozz  )
			</programlisting>
		</informalexample>

		<para> ...even though neither <literal>“abc”</literal>, nor <literal>“xyz”</literal>,
			nor <literal>“frobozz”</literal> is defined in the IDL.  The class name
			<literal>“abc”</literal> isn't used at all because the <literal>“+xyz”</literal>
			operator overrides it.  Such a query won't fail until json_query tries
			to execute it in the database. </para>
		<para> The other operators that may occur at this level all begin with a minus sign,
			and they all represent familiar SQL operators.  For example, the
			<literal>“-or”</literal> operator joins the conditions within a
			<literal>where_condition</literal> by OR (instead of the default AND), and
			encloses them all in parentheses: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.condition_2">
				<lhs> condition </lhs>
				<rhs> '”-or”' ':' where_condition </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> In fact the <literal>“-or”</literal> operator is the only way to get OR into
			the WHERE clause. </para>
		<para> The <literal>“-and”</literal> operator is similar, except that it uses AND: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.condition_3">
				<lhs> condition </lhs>
				<rhs> '”-and”' ':'  where_condition </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> Arguably the <literal>“-and”</literal> operator is redundant, because you can
			get the same effect by wrapping the subordinate <literal>where_condition</literal>
			in a JSON array.  Either technique merely adds a layer of parentheses, since AND
			connects successive conditions by default. </para>
		<para> The <literal>“-not”</literal> operator expands the subordinate
			<literal>where_condition</literal> within parentheses, and prefaces the result
			with NOT: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.condition_4">
				<lhs> condition </lhs>
				<rhs> '”-not”' ':'  where_condition </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The <literal>“-exists”</literal> or <literal>“-not-exists”</literal> operator
			constructs a subquery within an EXISTS  or NOT EXISTS clause, respectively: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.condition_5">
				<lhs> condition </lhs>
				<rhs> '”-exists”' ':' query </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.condition_6">
				<lhs> condition </lhs>
				<rhs> '”-not-exists”' ':' query </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The remaining kinds of <literal>condition</literal> all have a
			<literal>field_name</literal> on the left and some kind of <literal>predicate</literal>
			on the right.  A <literal>predicate</literal> places a constraint on the value of
			the column – or, in some cases, on the value of the column as transformed by some
			function call: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.condition_7">
				<lhs> condition </lhs>
				<rhs> field_name ':' predicate </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The simplest such constraint is to require that the column have a specific value,
			or be null: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.predicate_0">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> lit_value | 'null' </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.lit_value">
				<lhs> lit_value </lhs>
				<rhs> string | number </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> You can also compare a column to a literal value using some kind of inequality.
			However it's a bit more complicated because you have to specify what kind of comparison
			to make: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.compare_op_0">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' compare_op ':' lit_value '}' </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.compare_op_1">
				<lhs> compare_op </lhs>
				<rhs> string </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> A <literal>compare_op</literal> is a string that defines a comparison operator.
			Valid values include the following: </para>

		<programlisting language="SQL">
	=    &lt;&gt;   !=
	&lt;    &gt;    &lt;=   &gt;=
	~    ~*   !~   !~*
	like      ilike
	similar to
		</programlisting>

		<para> Strictly speaking, json_query accepts any <literal>compare_op</literal>
			that doesn't contain semicolons or white space (or
			<literal>“similar to”</literal> as a special exception).  As a result, it
			is possible – and potentially useful – to use a custom operator like
			<literal>“&gt;100*”</literal> in order to insert an expression that would
			otherwise be difficult or impossible to create through a JSON query.  The ban
			on semicolons and white space prevents certain kinds of SQL injection. </para>
		<para> Note that json_query does <emphasis>not</emphasis> accept two operators that
			PostgreSQL <emphasis>does</emphasis> accept: <literal>“is distinct from”</literal>
			and <literal>“is not distinct from”</literal>. </para>
		<para> You can also compare a column to a null value: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.predicate_1">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' compare_op ':' 'null' '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The equality operator <literal>“=”</literal> turns into IS NULL.  Any other
			operator turns into IS NOT NULL. </para>
		<para> When a <literal>compare_op</literal> is paired with an array, it defines a
			function call: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.predicate_2">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' compare_op ':' '[' string { ',' parameter } ']' '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The first entry in the array is the function's name.  Subsequent entries in
			the array, if any, represent the parameters of the function call.  They may be
			strings, numbers, or nulls.  In the generated SQL, the function call appears on
			the right of the comparison. </para>
		<para> The <literal>“between”</literal> operator creates a BETWEEN clause: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.predicate_3">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> '{'  “between”  ':'  '['  lit_value  ','  lit_value  ']'  '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> Although PostgreSQL allows a null value in a BETWEEN clause, json_query
			requires literal non-null values.  It isn't sensible to use null values in a
			BETWEEN clause.  A few experiments show that the results of the comparison are
			peculiar and erratic. </para>
		<para> There are two ways to create an IN list of allowed values.  The simplest is
			to put literal values into a JSON array: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.predicate_4">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> '[' lit_value { ',' lit_value }  ']' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> As with BETWEEN clauses, json_query does not accept null values in an IN list,
			even though PostgreSQL does allow them.  Nulls are not sensible in this context
			because they never match anything. </para>
		<para>  </para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2><title>Having Clause</title>
		<para>For the HAVING clause, json_query accepts exactly the same syntax as it accepts for
			the WHERE clause.</para>
		<para> The other way to create an IN list is to use an explicit
			<literal>“in”</literal> operator with an array of literal values.  This format
			also works for the <literal>“not in”</literal> operator: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.predicate_5">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' in_operator ';'  '[' lit_value [ ',' lit_value ]  ']'  '}' </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.in_operator">
				<lhs> in_operator </lhs>
				<rhs> “in”  |  “not in” </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> Another kind of IN or NOT IN clause uses a subquery instead of a list of
			values: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.predicate_6">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' in_operator ':'  query  '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The remaining types of <literal>predicate</literal> can put a function call on
			the left of the comparison, by using a <literal>transform_spec</literal> together
			with a <literal>“value”</literal> tag.   The <literal>transform_spec</literal> is
			optional, and if you don't need it, the same SQL would in many cases be easier to
			express by other means. </para>
		<para> The <literal>transform_spec</literal> construct was described earlier in
			connection with the SELECT clause, but here it is again: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.transform_spec_1">
				<lhs> transform_spec </lhs>
				<rhs>
					'”transform”'  ':'  string  ]<sbr/>
					[ ',' '”result_field”  ':'  string  ]<sbr/>
					[ ',' '”params”  ':' param_list  ]
				</rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> As in the SELECT clause, the <literal>“transform”</literal> string names the
			function.  The first parameter is always the column identified by the field_name.
			Additional parameters, if any, appear in the <literal>param_list</literal>.  The
			<literal>“result_field”</literal> string, if present, identifies one column of a
			multicolumn return value. </para>
		<para> Here's a second way to compare a value to a literal value (but not to a null
			value): </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.predicate_7">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' compare_op ':' '{' '”value”' ':' lit_value<sbr/>
					[ transform_spec ] '}' '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> ...and a way to compare a value to a boolean expression: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.predicate_8">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' compare_op ':' '{' '”value”' ':' '{'<sbr/>
					condition { ',' condition } [ transform_spec ] '}' '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The final predicate is another way to put a function call on the right side
			of the comparison: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.predicate_9">
				<lhs> predicate </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' compare_op ':' '{' '”value”' ':' '['<sbr/>
					string { ',' parameter } ']' [ transform_spec ] '}' '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> This format is available for the sake of consistency, but offers no advantage
			over the simpler version. </para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2><title>ORDER BY Clause</title>
		<para> There are two ways to encode an ORDER BY clause: as an array, or as a list.
			Either may be empty, in which case the generated SQL will not include an ORDER BY
			clause: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.order_by_list_0">
				<lhs> order_by_list </lhs>
				<rhs> '['  ']'  |  '{'  '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> If not empty, the array contains one or more objects, each defining a sort
			field: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.order_by_list_1">
				<lhs> order_by_list </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' sort_field_def  {  ','  sort_field_def }  '}' </rhs>
			</production>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.sort_field_def">
				<lhs> sort_field_def </lhs>
				<rhs> '{'<sbr/>
					'”class”'  ':'  class_name<sbr/>
					','  '”field”'  ':'  field_name<sbr/>
					[  ','  '”direction”'  ':'  lit_value  ]<sbr/>
					[  ','  transform_spec  ]<sbr/>
					'}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> The <literal>“class”</literal> and <literal>“field”</literal> entries are
			required, and of course the field must belong to the class.  Furthermore, at
			least one field from the class must appear in the SELECT clause. </para>
		<para> The <literal>“direction”</literal> entry, if present, specifies whether the
			sort will be ascending or descending for the column in question.  If the associated
			value begins with “D” or “d”, the sort will be descending; otherwise the sort will
			be ascending.  If the value is a number, it will be treated as a string that does not
			start with “D” or “d”, resulting in an ascending sort. </para>
		<para> In the absence of a <literal>“direction”</literal> entry, the sort will be
			ascending. </para>
		<para> The <literal>transform_spec</literal> works here the same way it works in the
			SELECT clause and the WHERE clause, enabling you to pass the column through a
			transforming function before the sort: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.transform_spec_2">
				<lhs> transform_spec </lhs>
				<rhs>
					'”transform”'  ':'  string  ]<sbr/>
					[ ',' '”result_field”  ':'  string  ]<sbr/>
					[ ',' '”params”  ':' param_list  ]
				</rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> When the <literal>order_by_list</literal> is an object instead of an array,
			the syntax is less verbose, but also less flexible.  The keys for the object are
			class names: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.order_by_list_2">
				<lhs> order_by_list </lhs>
				<rhs> '{' class_name ':' sort_class_def<sbr/>
					{ ',' class_name ':' sort_class_def } '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> Each class must be referenced in the SELECT clause. </para>
		<para> As in the SELECT clause, all the fields for a given class must be grouped
			together.  You can't sort by a column from one table, then a column from a second
			table, then another column from the first table. If you need this kind of sort,
			you must encode the ORDER BY clause as an array instead of an object. </para>
		<para> The data associated with a <literal>class_name</literal> may be either an array
			or an object.  If an array, it's simply a list of field names, and each field must
			belong to the class: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.sort_class_def_0">
				<lhs> sort_class_def </lhs>
				<rhs> '['  field_name  { ','  field_name }  ']' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> With this syntax, the direction of sorting will always be ascending. </para>
		<para> If the data is an object, the keys are field names, and as usual the fields
			must belong to the class: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.sort_class_def_1">
				<lhs> sort_class_def </lhs>
				<rhs> '{'  field_name  ':' sort_class_subdef<sbr/>
					{ ','  field_name  ':' sort_class_subdef  }  '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> Since the <literal>field_name</literal> is the key for the object, it cannot
			appear more than once.  As a result, some kinds of sorts are not possible with this
			syntax.  For example, one might want to sort by UPPER( family_name ), and then by
			family_name with case unchanged, to make sure that “diBona” comes before “Dibona”.
			For situations like this, you must encode the ORDER BY clause as an array rather
			than an object. </para>
		<para> The data associated with each <literal>field_name</literal> may take either of
			two forms.  In the simplest case, it's a literal value to specify the direction
			of sorting: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.sort_class_subdef_0">
				<lhs> sort_class_subdef </lhs>
				<rhs> lit_value </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> If the literal is a string starting with “D” or “d”, json_query sorts the field
			in descending order.  Otherwise it sorts the field in ascending order. </para>
		<para> In other cases, the <literal>field_name</literal> may be paired with an object
			to specify more details: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.sort_class_subdef_1">
				<lhs> sort_class_subdef </lhs>
				<rhs> '{'<sbr/>
					[  '”direction”'  ':'  lit_value ]<sbr/>
					[  transform_spec  ]<sbr/>
					'}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>

		<para> As before, the value tagged as <literal>“direction”</literal> specifies the
			direction of the sort, depending on the first character.  If not otherwise
			specified, the sort direction defaults to ascending. </para>
		<para> Also as before, the <literal>transform_spec</literal> may specify a function
			through which to pass the column. </para>
		<para> Since both the <literal>“direction”</literal> tag and the
			<literal>transform_spec</literal> are optional, the object may be empty: </para>

		<productionset>

			<production xml:id="ebnf.sort_class_subdef_2">
				<lhs> sort_class_subdef </lhs>
				<rhs> '{'  '}' </rhs>
			</production>

		</productionset>
	</sect2>

</sect1>
