<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="requirements" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="EN"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <title>System Requirements and Recommended Configurations</title>
    </info>

    <para>Evergreen is extremely scalable and can serve the need of a large range of libraries. The specific requirements and configuration of your system should be determined based on your 
	specific needs of your organization or consortium.</para>
    
	<section xml:id="requirements_server">
	        <info>
	            <title>Server Minimum Requirements</title>
	        </info>	
	       
		<simplesect>
			 <para>The following are the base requirements setting Evergreen up on a test server:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>An available desktop, server or virtual image</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>512MB RAM</para></listitem>			
				<listitem><para>Linux Operating System</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<tip><para>Debian and Ubuntu are the most widely used Linux distributions for installing Evergreen and most development takes place on Debian based systems. If you are new 
			to Linux, it is strongly recommended that you install Evergreen on the latest stable server edition of Debian (<ulink url="http://www.debian.org/">http://www.debian.org/</ulink>)
			or Ubuntu 10.04 Server(<ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/">http://www.ubuntu.com/</ulink>) since the installation instructions have been tested on these distributions. Debian and 				Ubuntu are free distributions of Linux.</para></tip>  
		</simplesect> 
		<simplesect>
			<info>
            			<title>Server Network Configurations</title>
			</info>
        		<para>As apparent in the previous section, the base hardware requirements for running a functional Evergreen server are extremely minimal. It is also possible
			to scale up your evergreen configuration to be spread your Evergreen resources and services over many servers in a clustered approach. This allows very large consortia to share 
			one Evergreen system with hundreds of libraries with millions of records and millions of users making the scalability of Evergreen almost infinite.</para>
			<para>Here are some example scenarios for a server network configuration:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>A small public library or school library with 1 location, under 25,000 items and a few thousand users could easily run Evergreen on a single server 
				(1 machine).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>A college or university with 1 million items and 20,000 users could run an Evergreen system using several servers balancing the load on their 
				system by spreading services over multiple servers. It could also run  
				PostgreSQL on a separate server. They could also cluster the Evergreen services in a way to minimize or eliminate any necessary downtown when upgrading Evergreen, 
				the operating system or the database software.</para></listitem>			
				<listitem><para>A large library consortium with several public library systems and/or academic libraries with millions of users and items could run an Evergreen 
				system over many servers, balancing the load on the system while sharing resource costs. At the same time, it gives users searching capabilities to search 
				several library systems simultaneously.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
      			<para>The key to Evergreen scalability is in the openSRF configuration files <filename>/openils/conf/opensrf.xml</filename> and 
			<filename>/openils/conf/opensrf_core.xml</filename>. 
			By editing these files an administrator could quickly cluster evergreen services over multiple servers, change the server running a specific service 
			or change the server of the postgreSQL database.</para> 

			<note><para>The default configuration of Evergreen in the installation instructions assumes a single <emphasis>localhost</emphasis> server setup. For more complex 
			multi-server configurations, some server administration and database administration experience or knowledge may be required.</para></note>		
    		</simplesect>    
 	</section>
	<section xml:id="requirements_staffclient">
	        <info>
	            <title>Staff Client Requirements</title>
	        </info>
	
	        <para> Staff terminals connect to the central database using the Evergreen staff client, available for download from <link xlink:href="http://www.open-ils.org/downloads.php">The Evergreen 
		download page</link>. The staff client must be installed on each staff workstation and requires at minimum: </para>
		<itemizedlist>
    			<listitem><para>Windows (XP, Vista, or 7), Mac OS X, or Linux operating system</para></listitem>
    			<listitem><para>a reliable high speed internet connection</para></listitem>
   			<listitem><para>512Mb of RAM</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
  		<simplesect>
			<info>
            			<title>Barcode Scanners</title>   
			</info>
        			<para>Evergreen will work with virtually any barcode scanner – if it worked with your legacy system it should work on Evergreen.</para>
    		</simplesect>
		<simplesect>
			<info>
            			<title>Printers</title>
			</info>
        		<para>Evergreen can use any printer configured for your terminal to print receipts, check-out slips, holds
            		lists, etc. The single exception is spine label printing, which is still under development. Evergreen
            		currently formats spine labels for output to a label roll printer. If you do not have a roll printer
           		 manual formatting may be required.  For more on configuring receipt printers, see <link linkend="lsa-printer">Printer Settings</link>.</para>    
    		</simplesect>    
 	</section>
</chapter>
