<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="releasenotes" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="EN"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<chapterinfo>
	<title>2.1 Release Notes</title>
	</chapterinfo>

<simplesect id="_installation_enhancements">
<title>Installation enhancements</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<literal>eg_db_config.pl</literal> now has a <literal>--create-database</literal> option to automatically create
  the database and add the required contrib modules/extensions, rather than
  requiring users to carry out a number of error-prone manual steps.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The OpenILS Perl modules are now installed in the system Perl package
  directories.  In prior versions, they were typically installed in
  <literal>/openils/lib/perl5</literal>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
README is now the single source of install instructions
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_administration_enhancements">
<title>Administration enhancements</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Automatic client updates: It is now possible to build staff clients that,
  when they connect to the Evergreen server, automatically check to see if
  the staff client has been updated. If so, the staff client can download just
  the files that have been updated and replace those files in the existing
  staff client.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Printing subsystem: Changes to the staff client should improve the print
  functionality (both speed and likelihood of success).
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
To protect against exploits between a shared staff client session via
  operator change, add the requirement for the DEBUG_CLIENT permission to
  invoke debugging functions such as the Javascript Shell or DOM Inspector
   in the staff client.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_cataloging_enhancements">
<title>Cataloging enhancements</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Unified copy / call number editor: The default holdings maintenance interface
  now enables cataloguers to edit copies and call numbers on a single screen.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Call number prefixes and suffixes: While previous releases of Evergreen
  supported the automatic prepending or appending of prefixes and suffixes to
  call numbers based on their shelving location, the functionality was limited
  primarily to printing spine labels.  As of 2.1, you also have the option to
  assign prefixes or suffixes for individual call numbers; these will be
  displayed in the public catalogue and other interfaces, but prefixes in
  particular do not affect shelf browsing, which is based entirely on the
  label.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Bibliographic parts: This feature adds the ability to designate specific
  "part" roles for the items attached to a given bibliographic record, such
  that a user can place holds on a specific kind of item without limiting it
  to an individual item. For example, libraries may assign parts to each DVD
  in a season of a popular TV show; or to individual volumes of an
  encyclopedia. This feature also introduces "part holds".
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Conjoined items: This feature adds the ability to associate a single barcode
  with multiple bibliographic records, so that the availability of those
  records is updated based on that copy. For example, libraries may make an
  electronic reader available for loan that is preloaded with 1000 electronic
  books; they can add 1000 bibliographic records to the library system and
  associate them all with a single barcode, so that when the electronic reader
  is signed out, the availability for all 1000 records changes to "Checked out".
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_circulation_improvements">
<title>Circulation improvements</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Transfer selected holds to a different title: It is now possible to select
  multiple holds on a given title and transfer them to a different title.
  Use case: Your library acquires another copy of "Pride and Prejudice and
  Zombies", but as it is a new edition it must be cataloged as a new
  bibliographic record; however, you would like to spread out some of the holds
  queue from your current edition to the new edition.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Mark patron as exempt from billing collections: It is now possible to mark a
  patron as being exempt from being sent to collections.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Hold-driven recalls: It is now possible to define a loan
  period threshold (such as 60 days) so that if a hold is placed on an item with
  a loan period beyond that threshold, the system will automatically shorten the
  loan period to a specified value; change the fine rules; and send email
  notification to the person who currently holds the item saying "A hold has
  been placed on this item, get it back before &lt;new_due_date&gt;".
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Weighting of the individual fields of the in-database circulation and holds
  rules can now be configured, rather than using hard-coded values. This allows
  the importance of each field to be adjusted as needed through the circulation
  matrix weighting, hold matrix weighting, and weighting associations settings.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The in-database circulation rules support "fall-through" wherein some
  information can be left out of more specific rules and filled in from less
  specific rules. For example, disabling fines for staff could be accomplished
  with a single rule setting only the fine rate and/or max fine rules, without
  having to duplicate all duration related rules in the system.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Grace periods are now stored in the database and set via circulation rules,
  rather than passed into the fine generation code, and can thus differ between
  different rules. They are also no longer based on a number of fine intervals,
  but are instead defined by their own specific interval. This can eliminate
  problems with closed date interpretation during grace periods.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_public_interface_improvements">
<title>Public interface improvements</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Spell-checking suggestions are now case-insensitive, to avoid generating
  terms which would yield the same result set.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Part holds: patrons are guided to select a specific part if they are
  placing a hold on a bibliographic record that has parts assigned to its
  copies.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Located URI visibility: Located URIs (856 fields with a subfield $9
  specifying the shortname of the owning library) now show up in a search with
  a context library of its owning library or below. For example, a Located URI
  with an owner of SYS1 <emphasis role="strong">will</emphasis> cause its record to show up in a search with a
  context OU of BR1 or SYS1, regardless of depth scoping.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Set a JavaScript cache token when <literal>autogen.sh</literal> is run, so that a subsequent
  run of <literal>autogen.sh</literal> will automatically cause browsers to fetch refreshed
  copies of generated files. This improves the usability of the catalog after
  upgrades or certain configuration changes by preventing browsers from relying
  on stale cached copies of these files.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_serials_enhancements">
<title>Serials enhancements</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Routing lists: it is now possible to define and print routing lists for
  subscriptions.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Clone subscriptions: new functionality available in the alternate
  serials control view to clone subscriptions, thereby speeding initial
  setup of a lot of subscriptions.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
MFHD/Distribution summary methods: enable the summary method field for
  generating summary holdings statements from the distribution and/or
  the record entry (i.e., the MFHD).  The four options that are available are:
</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Add to record entry
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Merge with record entry
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use record entry only
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Do not use record entry
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Advanced receiving: rename the previous serials receiving interface
  to "advanced receiving".  The new "receive" interface will now show items
  from an entire subscription, but not allow you to receive directly into
  a specific unit.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Unit-less receiving: new option for receiving serials into a <emphasis>no unit</emphasis>,
  allowing items to be received but not unitized (i.e., created as a
  circulating copy record).  This allows issues to be received for
  reading room or non-circulating use.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Caption/pattern enhancements:
</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The Caption/Pattern Wizard now includes a graphical way to include
     regularity information (that is, the values typically conveyed in the <literal>85x</literal>
     subfield <literal>$y</literal>).
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The Alternate Serials Control interface can now import caption and pattern
     information from the 85x fields of the MFHD record, allowing the
     Caption/Pattern Wizard to be bypassed.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Can now create one-off issuances for unpredicted or unexpected serial issues.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Improvements to the copy template editor for serials, including the addition
  of reasonable default values for some fields.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Various minor interface improvements, including new links between various pages
  in the serials control interfaces and removing redundant questions from the holding code
  mini-wizard.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Bugfixes to the batch receive interface.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_staff_client_improvements">
<title>Staff client improvements</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The client supports new hotkey sets that are selectable per workstation. In
  addition, there is now a toggle for temporarily disabling hotkeys available
  on the toolbar and in the admin menu.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The client has a second toolbar for cataloging functions as well as options
  controlling the presence and size of icons and presence and position of
  labels. To support the preferences of individual staff, each workstation can
  be configured differently. See the <emphasis role="strong">Admin &#8594; Workstation Administration &#8594;
  Toolbars</emphasis> sub-menu for options.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Patron registration now supports "Suggested" fields that are configurable
  per library. In addition, library settings allow required fields to be
  adjusted, and it is possible to specify regular expressions to validate
  input for many fields in the patron registration interface. Open <emphasis role="strong">Admin &#8594;
  Local Administration &#8594; Library Settings Editor</emphasis> and filter on <literal>GUI</literal>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_new_configuration_and_administration_settings">
<title>New configuration and administration settings</title>
<simplesect id="_new_literal_opensrf_xml_literal_settings">
<title>New <literal>opensrf.xml</literal> settings</title>
<simpara>(The path to these settings is relative to <literal>/opensrf/default/apps/</literal>).</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<literal>open-ils.search/app_settings/default_CD_modifiers</literal>: parameters to
  the cover density ranking function used to calculate relevance during
  bibliographic searches.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<literal>open-ils.trigger/app_settings/parallel/collect</literal>: number of parallel
  processes that <literal>action_trigger_runner.pl</literal> should use when collecting events.
  Setting this can decrease the time it takes for Action/Trigger processing to
  run on large Evergreen databases.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<literal>open-ils.trigger/app_settings/parallel/react</literal>: number of parallel
  processes that <literal>action_trigger_runner.pl</literal> should use when processing event reactors.
  Setting this can decrease the time it takes for Action/Trigger processing to
  run on large Evergreen databases.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<literal>open-ils.resolver/app_settings/cache_timeout</literal>: how long to cache results
  from your OpenURL resolver.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<literal>open-ils.resolver/app_settings/default_url_base</literal>: set to the base URL
  of your OpenURL resolver.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>In addition, the <literal>default_preferred_language</literal> and <literal>default_preferred_language_weight</literal>
settings have been moved from the <literal>open-ils.storage</literal> simplesect to the <literal>open-ils.search</literal>
simplesect of <literal>opensrf.xml</literal>.</simpara>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_new_administration_pages">
<title>New administration pages</title>
<simpara>The following new administration pages can all be accessed
from the <literal>Admin | Server Administration</literal> menu item in the staff client:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Call Number Prefixes: Populates a drop down menu in the new Unified Copy /
  Call Number Editor
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Call Number Suffixes: Populates a drop down menu in the new Unified Copy /
  Call Number Editor
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Circulation Matchpoint Weights: Related to the in-database Circulation and
  Hold Rule configuration changes
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Hold Matchpoint Weights: Related to the in-database Circulation and
  Hold Rule configuration changes
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
MARC Coded Value Maps: Sets labels for fixed fields and extends the set of
  values for display
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
MARC Record Attributes: Sets labels for fixed fields and extends the set of
  values for display
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Weights Associations: Related to the in-database Circulation and
  Hold Rule configuration changes
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_new_library_settings">
<title>New library settings</title>
<informaltable
frame="all"
rowsep="1" colsep="1"
>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colname="col_1" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="col_2" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"> Label </entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"> Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Cataloging: Default copy status (fast add)</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Default status when a copy is created using the "Fast Add" interface.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Cataloging: Default copy status (normal)</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Default status when a copy is created using the normal volume/copy creator interface.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Default Hotkeyset</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Default Hotkeyset for clients (filename without the .keyset).  Examples: Default, Minimal, and None</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Default showing suggested patron registration fields</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Instead of All fields, show just suggested fields in patron registration by default.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Example for day_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Example for validation on the day_phone field in patron registration.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Example for email field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Example for validation on the email field in patron registration.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Example for evening_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Example for validation on the evening_phone field in patron registration.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Example for other_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Example for validation on the other_phone field in patron registration.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Example for phone fields on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Example for validation on phone fields in patron registration. Applies to all phone fields without their own setting.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Example for post_code field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Example for validation on the post_code field in patron registration.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Horizontal layout for Volume/Copy Creator/Editor.</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The main entry point for this interface is in Holdings Maintenance, Actions for Selected Rows, Edit Item Attributes / Call Numbers / Replace Barcodes.  This setting changes the top and bottom panes for that interface into left and right panes.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Regex for day_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Regular Expression for validation on the day_phone field in patron registration.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Regex for email field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Regular Expression for validation on the email field in patron registration.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Regex for evening_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Regular Expression for validation on the evening_phone field in patron registration.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Regex for other_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Regular Expression for validation on the other_phone field in patron registration.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Regex for phone fields on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Regular Expression for validation on phone fields in patron registration. Applies to all phone fields without their own setting.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Regex for post_code field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The Regular Expression for validation on the post_code field in patron registration.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Require county field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The county field will be required on the patron registration screen.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Require day_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The day_phone field will be required on the patron registration screen.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Require dob field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The dob field will be required on the patron registration screen.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Require email field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The email field will be required on the patron registration screen.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Require evening_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The evening_phone field will be required on the patron registration screen.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Require other_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The other_phone field will be required on the patron registration screen.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show active field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The active field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show alert_message field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The alert_message field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show alias field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The alias field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show barred field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The barred field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show calendar widget for dob field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>If set the calendar widget will appear when editing the dob field on the patron registration form.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show claims_never_checked_out_count field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The claims_never_checked_out_count field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show claims_returned_count field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The claims_returned_count field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show day_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The day_phone field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show dob field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The dob field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show email field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The email field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show evening_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The evening_phone field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show ident_value field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The ident_value field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show ident_value2 field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The ident_value2 field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show juvenile field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The juvenile field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show master_account field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The master_account field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show other_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The other_phone field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show second_given_name field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The second_given_name field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Show suffix field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The suffix field will be shown on the patron registration screen. Showing a field makes it appear with required fields even when not required. If the field is required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest active field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The active field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest alert_message field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The alert_message field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest alias field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The alias field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest barred field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The barred field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest claims_never_checked_out_count field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The claims_never_checked_out_count field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest claims_returned_count field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The claims_returned_count field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest day_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The day_phone field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest dob field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The dob field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest email field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The email field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest evening_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The evening_phone field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest ident_value field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The ident_value field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest ident_value2 field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The ident_value2 field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest juvenile field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The juvenile field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest master_account field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The master_account field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest other_phone field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The other_phone field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest second_given_name field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The second_given_name field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Suggest suffix field on patron registration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>The suffix field will be suggested on the patron registration screen. Suggesting a field makes it appear when suggested fields are shown. If the field is shown or required this setting is ignored.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>GUI: Unified Volume/Item Creator/Editor</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>If true combines the Volume/Copy Creator and Item Attribute Editor in some instances.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Printing: Custom Javascript File</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Full URL path to a Javascript File to be loaded when printing. Should implement a print_custom function for DOM manipulation. Can change the value of the do_print variable to false to cancel printing.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Recalls: An array of fine amount, fine interval, and maximum fine.</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Recalls: An array of fine amount, fine interval, and maximum fine. For example, to specify a new fine rule of $5.00 per day, with a maximum fine of $50.00, use: [5.00,"1 day",50.00]</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Recalls: Circulation duration that triggers a recall.</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Recalls: A hold placed on an item with a circulation duration longer than this will trigger a recall. For example, "14 days" or "3 weeks".</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Recalls: Truncated loan period.</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Recalls: When a recall is triggered, this defines the adjusted loan period for the item. For example, "4 days" or "1 week".</simpara></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</simplesect>
<simplesect id="_new_user_permissions">
<title>New user permissions</title>
<informaltable
frame="all"
rowsep="1" colsep="1"
>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colname="col_1" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="col_2" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"> Code </entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"> Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>ADMIN_CODED_VALUE</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Create/Update/Delete SVF Record Attribute Coded Value Map</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>ADMIN_SERIAL_ITEM</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Create/Retrieve/Update/Delete Serial Item</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>ADMIN_SVF</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Create/Update/Delete SVF Record Attribute Defintion</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>CREATE_BIB_PTYPE</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Create Bibliographic Record Peer Type</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>CREATE_MONOGRAPH_PART</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Create monograph part definition.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>CREATE_PURCHASE_REQUEST</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Create User Purchase Request</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>CREATE_VOLUME_PREFIX</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Create prefix label definition.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>CREATE_VOLUME_SUFFIX</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Create suffix label definition.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>DEBUG_CLIENT</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Allows a user to use debug functions in the staff client</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>DELETE_BIB_PTYPE</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Delete Bibliographic Record Peer Type</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>DELETE_MONOGRAPH_PART</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Delete monograph part definition.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>DELETE_VOLUME_PREFIX</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Delete prefix label definition.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>DELETE_VOLUME_SUFFIX</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Delete suffix label definition.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>MAP_MONOGRAPH_PART</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Create/Update/Delete Copy Monograph Part Map</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>MARK_ITEM_MISSING_PIECES</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Allows the Mark Item Missing Pieces action.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>UPDATE_BIB_PTYPE</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Update Bibliographic Record Peer Type</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>UPDATE_HOLD_REQUEST_TIME</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Allows editing of a hold&#8217;s request time, and/or its Cut-in-line/Top-of-queue flag.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>UPDATE_MONOGRAPH_PART</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Update monograph part definition.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>UPDATE_PATRON_COLLECTIONS_EXEMPT</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Allows a user to indicate that a patron is exempt from collections processing</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>UPDATE_PICKLIST</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Allows update/re-use of an acquisitions pick/selection list.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>UPDATE_VOLUME_PREFIX</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Update prefix label definition.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>UPDATE_VOLUME_SUFFIX</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Update suffix label definition.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>UPDATE_WORKSTATION</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Allows update of a workstation during workstation registration override.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>VIEW_USER_SETTING_TYPE</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Allows viewing of configurable user setting types.</simpara></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</simplesect>
</simplesect>
</chapter>
