<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
   xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="admin-booking">
   <info>
      <title>Booking Module Administration</title>
      <legalnotice>
         <para><emphasis role="bold">Adapted with permission from original material by the <link
                  xlink:title="http://docs.evergreen-ils.org/1.6/draft/html/"
                  xlink:href="http://docs.evergreen-ils.org/1.6/draft/html/">Evergreen
                  Community</link></emphasis></para>
      </legalnotice>

      <abstract>
         <para>The Evergreen booking module is included in Evergreen 1.6.1.x and above.The following
            documentation will include information about making cataloged items bookable; making
            non-bibliographic items bookable; and setting permissions in the booking module for
            staff.</para>
      </abstract>
   </info>
   <section xml:id="MakeCataloguedItemBookable">
      <title>Make a Cataloged Item Bookable in Advance</title>
	<indexterm><primary>booking reservation</primary><secondary>making a cataloged item bookable</secondary></indexterm>
      <para>If their permission settings allow, staff members can make items bookable. Staff members
         can do this in advance of a booking request, or they can do it on the fly.</para>
      <para>If you know in advance of the request that an item will need to be booked, you can make
         the item bookable.</para>


      <procedure>
         <step>
            <para>In the staff client, select <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Search</guimenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Search the Catalog</guimenuitem>
               </menuchoice></para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Begin a title search to find an item.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Click the title of the item that you want to book.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>The <guilabel>Record Summary</guilabel> will appear. In this view you can see
               information about the item and its locations. Click <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Holdings Maintenance</guimenuitem>
               </menuchoice> in the top right corner of the screen.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>The <guilabel>Holdings Maintenance</guilabel> screen will appear. In this screen,
               you can view the volumes and copies of an item avaialable at each branch. To view the
               barcodes and other information for each copy, click the arrow adjacent to the branch
               with the copy that you need to view. Click on successive arrows until you find the
               copy that you need to view.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Select the item that you want to make bookable. Right click to open the menu, and
               click <guimenuitem>Make Item Bookable</guimenuitem>.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>The item has now been added to the list of resources that are bookable. To book
               the item, return to the <guilabel>Record Summary</guilabel>, and proceed with
               booking..</para>
         </step>

      </procedure>
      <note>
         <para>In Evergreen 1.6.1, there is no way to make an item “unbookable” after it has been
            made bookable and has been reserved. The <guibutton>Delete Selected</guibutton> button
            on this screen deletes the resource from the screen, but the item will be able to be
            booked after it has been returned.</para>
      </note>

   </section>
   <section xml:id="MakeItemBookableOnTheFly">
      <title>Make a Cataloged Item Bookable On the Fly</title>
      <para>If a patron wants to book an item immediately that does not have bookable status, you
         can book the item on the fly if you have the appropriate permissions.</para>

      <procedure>
         <step>
            <para>Follow steps one through five in <xref linkend="MakeCataloguedItemBookable"
               />.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Select the item that you want to make bookable. Right click to open the menu, and
               click <guimenuitem>Book Item Now</guimenuitem>.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>A <guilabel>Reservations</guilabel> screen will appear in a new tab, and you can
               make the reservation.</para>
         </step>

      </procedure>

   </section>
   <section xml:id="MakeNon-CataloguedItemBookable">
      <title>Create a Bookable Status for Non-Bibliographic Items</title>
	<indexterm><primary>booking reservation</primary><secondary>non-bibliographic items</secondary></indexterm>
      <para>Staff with the required permissions can create a bookable status for non-bibliographic
         items. For example, staff can book conference rooms or laptops. You will be able to create
         types of resources, specify the names of individual resources within each type, and set
         attributes to describe those resources. You can then bring the values together through the
            <guilabel>Resource Attribute Map</guilabel>.</para>
      <procedure>
         <step>
            <para>First, create the type of resource that you want to make bookable. Select <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Admin</guimenu>
                  <guisubmenu>Server Administration</guisubmenu>
                  <guisubmenu>Booking</guisubmenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Resource Types</guimenuitem>
               </menuchoice>.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>A list of resource types will appear. You may also see titles of cataloged items
               on this screen if they were added using the <guilabel>Make Item Bookable</guilabel>
               or <guilabel>Book Now</guilabel> links. You should not attempt to add cataloged items
               on this screen; it is best to use the aforementioned links to make those items
               bookable. In this screen, you will create a type of resource.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>In the right corner, click <guibutton>New Resource Type</guibutton>.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>A box will appear in which you will create a type of resource. In this box, you
               can set fines, determine “elbow room” periods between reservations on this type of
               resource, and indicate if this type of resource can be transferred to another
               library. Click <guibutton>Save</guibutton> when you have entered the needed
               information.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>After you click <guibutton>Save</guibutton>, the box will disappear. Refresh the
               screen to see the item that you have added.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Next, set the attributes for the type of resource that you have created. Select <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Server Administration</guimenu>
                  <guisubmenu>Booking</guisubmenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Resource Attributes</guimenuitem>
               </menuchoice>.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>Click <guibutton>New Resource Attribute</guibutton>.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>A box will appear in which you can add the attributes of the resource. Attributes
               are descriptive information that is provided to the staff member when the booking
               request is made. For example, an attribute of the projector may be a cart that allows
               for its transportation. Other attributes might be number of seats available in a
               room, or MAC or PC attributes for a laptop. Click <guibutton>Save</guibutton> when
               the necessary information has been entered.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>The box will disappear. Refresh the screen to see the added attribute.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>Next, add the values for the resource attributes. A value can be a number, yes/no,
               or any other meaningful information. Select <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Server Administration</guimenu>
                  <guisubmenu>Booking</guisubmenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Resource Attribute Values</guimenuitem>
               </menuchoice>.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>Select <guibutton>New Resource Attribute Value</guibutton>.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>A pop up box will appear. Select the <guilabel>Resource Attribute</guilabel> from
               the drop down box. Add the value. You can add multiple values for this field. Click
                  <guibutton>Save</guibutton> when the required information has been added.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>If you refresh the screen, the attribute value may not appear, but it has been
               saved.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>Next, identify the specific objects that are associated with this resource type.
               Click <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Admin</guimenu>
                  <guisubmenu>Server Administration</guisubmenu>
                  <guisubmenu>Booking</guisubmenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Resources</guimenuitem>
               </menuchoice>.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>Click <guibutton>New Resource</guibutton>.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>A pop-up box will appear. Add information for the resource and click
                  <guibutton>Save</guibutton>. Repeat this process for each resource.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>Refresh the screen, and the resource(s) that you added will appear.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>Finally, use <guilabel>Resource Attribute Maps</guilabel> to bring together the
               resource and its attributes. Select <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Admin</guimenu>
                  <guisubmenu>Server Administration</guisubmenu>
                  <guisubmenu>Booking</guisubmenu>
                  <guimenuitem>Resource Attribute Maps</guimenuitem>
               </menuchoice>.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>Select <guibutton>New Resource Attribute Map</guibutton></para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>Select the resource that you want to match with its attributes, then click
                  <guibutton>Save</guibutton>. Repeat for all applicable resources.</para>
         </step>

         <step>
            <para>You have now created bookable, non-bibliographic resource(s) with
               attributes.</para>
         </step>

      </procedure>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="SettingBookingPermissions">
      <title>Setting Booking Permissions</title>
	<indexterm><primary>booking reservation</primary><secondary>setting booking permissions</secondary></indexterm>
      <para>Administrators can set permissions so that staff members can view reservations, make
         reservations, and make bibliographic or non-bibliographic items bookable.</para>

      <para>If a staff member attempts to book an item for which they do not have the appropriate
         permissions, they will receive an error message.</para>

      <para>To set permissions, select <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Admin</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Server Administration</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Permissions</guimenuitem>
         </menuchoice>.</para>

      <para>Staff members should be assigned the following permissions to do common tasks in the
         booking module. These permissions could be assigned to front line staff members, such as
         circulation staff. Permissions with an asterisk (<emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis>) are
         already included in the <emphasis role="bold">Staff</emphasis> permission group. All other
         booking permissions must be applied individually.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">View Reservations:</emphasis> VIEW_TRANSACTION*</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Use the pull list:</emphasis>
               RETRIEVE_RESERVATION_PULL_LIST</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Capture reservations:</emphasis> CAPTURE_RESERVATION</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Assist patrons with pickup and return:</emphasis>
               VIEW_USER*</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Create/update/delete reservations:</emphasis>
               ADMIN_BOOKING_RESERVATION</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following permissions allow users to do more advanced tasks, such as making items
         bookable, booking items on the fly, and creating non-bibliographic resources for
         booking.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Create/update/delete booking resource type:</emphasis>
               ADMIN_BOOKING_RESOURCE_TYPE</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Create/update/delete booking resource attributes:</emphasis>
               ADMIN_BOOKING_RESOURCE_ATTR</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Create/update/delete booking resource attribute
                  values:</emphasis> ADMIN_BOOKING_RESOURCE_ATTR_VALUE</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Create/update/delete booking resource:</emphasis>
               ADMIN_BOOKING_RESOURCE</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Create/update/delete booking resource attribute
                  maps:</emphasis> ADMIN_BOOKING_RESOURCE_ATTR_MAP</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In addition to having the permissions listed above, staff members will need a valid
         working location in their profiles. This should be done when registering new staff members.</para>

      <!-- Pages 14-16 of source document from http://evergreen-ils.org/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=booking ommitted at conversion (Jeremy Buhler, Oct 6 2010).  Rationale: subject is covered elsewhere in the Book of Evergreen and it confuses 'working location' with 'home library', both of which should already be set for all staff accounts. -->

   </section>
</chapter>
