<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="staffclientinstallation" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<info>
		<title>Installation of Evergreen Staff Client Software</title>
		<abstract>
			<para>This section describes installation of the Evergreen Staff Client software.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>
	<section xml:id="staffclientinstallation-installing-staffclient">
		<title>Installing the Staff Client</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>staff client</primary>
			<secondary>installing</secondary>
		</indexterm>
		<section xml:id="staffclientinstallation-installing-prebuilt">
			<title>Installing a Pre-Built Staff Client</title>
			<para>A pre-built Staff Client is available for <systemitem class="osname">Windows</systemitem>,
			<systemitem class="osname">Mac</systemitem> or Linux systems. Installing the Staff Client in
			each of these environments is described in the following sections.</para>
			<section xml:id="staffclientinstallation-installing-windows">
				<title>Installing on <systemitem class="osname">Windows</systemitem></title>
				<indexterm>
					<primary>staff client</primary>
					<secondary>installing</secondary>
					<tertiary>Windows</tertiary>
				</indexterm>
				<para>In this section we describe the process of installing the Staff Client on the
				<systemitem class="osname">Microsoft Windows</systemitem> operating system.</para>
				<para>Visit the downloads section of the Evergreen website at
				<ulink url="http://www.evergreen-ils.org/downloads.php">http://www.evergreen-ils.org/downloads.php</ulink>
				and find the standard <systemitem class="osname">Microsoft Windows</systemitem> Installer
				that contains the current version of the Staff Client. Download the Installer, then run
				it. A screen that looks similar to this should appear:</para>
				<mediaobject>
					<alt>
						<phrase>Running the Staff Client installer</phrase>
					</alt>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="../media/staffclientinstallation-staffclient-1.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
				<para>Click <guibutton>'Next'</guibutton> to continue through the guided install
				process. The Install Wizard will ask you to agree to the end-user license, ask you where
				to install the software, ask about where to place icons, and then will automatically
				install the software on your workstation.</para>
				<para>When you run the Staff Client for the first time, a screen similar to this should
				appear:</para>
				<mediaobject>
					<alt>
						<phrase>Running the Staff Client for the first time</phrase>
					</alt>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="../media/staffclientinstallation-staffclient-2.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
				<para>First, add the name of your Evergreen server to the field 
				<emphasis role="bold">Hostname</emphasis> in the <emphasis role="bold">Server</emphasis>
				section. For example, the PINES demo system is 
				<ulink url="http://demo.gapines.org">http://demo.gapines.org</ulink>. 
				After adding the server name, click <guibutton>'Re-Test Server'</guibutton>.</para>
				<para>Because this is the initial run of the Staff Client, you will see a warning in the
				upper-right saying: <emphasis role="bold">Not yet configured for the specified
				server</emphasis>. The first thing you must do to the Staff Client on every workstation
				is to assign it a workstation name. This is covered in 
				<xref linkend="staffclientinstallation-workstationnames"/>.</para>
					<note><para>Users must have the <literal>REGISTER_WORKSTATION</literal> permission and be assigned the appropriate working location(s) in order to 
					register a workstation.</para></note> 
					<para>To add working locations to a user’s account:</para>
					<orderedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>Retrieve the user through a patron search and select <menuchoice><guimenu>Other</guimenu><guimenuitem>User Permission 
							Editor</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select the boxes for the locations necessary.</para> 
							<para>Save the user record.</para>
							<note>
								<para>Making modifications to <guilabel>Working Locations</guilabel> while changing permission settings does not work – when this 
								workflow is performed, permission changes will not be applied to the database.</para>
							</note>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Alternately, from the <guimenu>Admin</guimenu> menu, select <guimenuitem>User Permission Editor</guimenuitem> and retrieve the user by 
							barcode.</para>  
							<para>Make changes to working locations as described above.</para>
						</listitem>
					</orderedlist>
			</section>
		</section>

	</section>
</chapter>
