<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cataloguing">
	<info>
	<title>Cataloguing</title>
		<abstract>
			<para>This chapter explains the cataloguing procedures carried out from the staff client.</para>
        	</abstract>
	</info>    
	<section xml:id="locatingrecords">
		<title>Locating Records</title>
		<simplesect xml:id="staffclientrecordsearch">
			<title>Search</title>
			<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>locating records</secondary></indexterm>
			<para>Search functionality may be functioned through:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><menuchoice><guimenu>Cataloging</guimenu><guimenuitem>Search the Catalog</guimenuitem></menuchoice> </listitem>
					<listitem><menuchoice><guimenu>Search</guimenu><guimenuitem>the Catalog</guimenuitem></menuchoice></listitem>
					<listitem>Press <keycap>F3</keycap></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>Specialized search functionality for catalogers is located on the left-hand side of the search screen (<guibutton>Quick Search</guibutton>).</para>
			<procedure>
				<step><para>Enter search criteria.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Submit</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click on the title link for the desired record.</para></step>
				<step><para>The complete record will display in the OPAC view.</para></step>
				<step><para>Use the <guilabel>Actions for this Record</guilabel> dropdown menu to manipulate the record.</para></step>
			</procedure>
			<tip><para>Use <emphasis>ocn</emphasis> as a prefix for nine digit OCLC numbers. (e.g. ocn123456789)
			Use <emphasis>ocm</emphasis> as a prefix for OCLC numbers that are eight digits or shorter. Evergreen will automatically prefix the number with zeros so that it is nine digits. 
			(e.g. ocm01234567, or ocm00123456)
			Do not use hyphens when searching by LCCN.  Substitute a <emphasis>0</emphasis> in place of the hyphen. (e.g. 2001001234)</para></tip>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="MARCexpertsearch">
			<title>MARC Expert Search</title>
			<para>Located beneath the “Quick Search” box on the catalog search screen.</para>
			<procedure>
				<step><para>Enter tag definitions and search criteria.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Submit</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Search multiple tags by clicking <guibutton>Add Row</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click the title link to display the full record.</para></step>
			</procedure>
			<tip><para>To set default record views for a username, select <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Set bottom interface as 
			Default</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></tip>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="addingandeditingitems">
			<title>Adding and Editing Items</title>
			<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>adding and editing items</secondary></indexterm>
			<simplesect xml:id="adingholdingstotitlerecords">
				<title>Adding Holdings to Title Rrcords</title>	
				<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>adding holdings</secondary></indexterm>		
				<procedure>
					<step><para>Retrieve an existing bibliographic record.</para></step>
					<step><para>Actions for this Record->Holdings Maintenance.</para></step>
					<step><para>The Record opens in <emphasis>record summary</emphasis> view. To display existing volume and copy records, check the boxes for 
					<emphasis>Show Volumes</emphasis> and <emphasis>Show Items.</emphasis> 
					These boxes are <emphasis>sticky</emphasis> and will remain checked for the login until manually de-selected.</para></step>
					
					<step><para>Highlight the appropriate library from the display.</para></step>
					<step><para>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for Selected Rows</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Add Volumes</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>
					<step><para>Use Tab or Enter to move through the displayed fields (# of volumes, call number, copies, and barcodes).</para></step>
					<note><para>New boxes will display after Enter or Tab is selected. If a call number exists in the MARC record, use Apply to bring it in to the volume 
					record.</para></note>
					<step><para>After entering the barcode number(s), click Edit then Create. </para></step>
					<step><para>The Copy Editor opens in a new window. Move through the fields to edit information as necessary. Click Apply on every edit. </para></step>
					<step><para>When finished, click Create Copies.</para></step>
				</procedure>
			<note><para>New items are assigned a status of In Process. Items must be checked in to become Available.  Alternatively, use Edit Item Attributes from the Actions for Selected 
			Rows to change statuses to Available once records have been created and saved to database. The creation and use of item record templates is recommended. </para></note>
			</simplesect>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="copyalertsandnotes">
			<title>Copy Alerts and Notes</title>
			
			<simplesect xml:id="copyalerts">
				<title>Copy Alerts</title>
				<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>copy alerts</secondary></indexterm>	
				<para>Copy alerts are useful alerts for physical item copies.</para>
				<para>Staff must be granted permission to override alerts at checkout or checkin.</para> 
					
				<procedure>
					<title>Creating copy alerts:</title>						
					<step><para><menuchoice><guimenu>Search</guimenu><guimenuitem>for copies by Barcode</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>
					<step><para>Enter an item barcode.</para></step>
					<step><para>Select the row.</para></step>
					<step><para><menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for Selected Items</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Edit Item Attributes</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>
					<step><para>Click in the alert message box and enter text.</para></step>
					<step><para>Click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>.</para></step>
					<step><para>Click <guibutton>Modify Copies</guibutton>.</para></step>
				</procedure>
				<note><para>Copy alerts must be manually removed. Follow the same process, but delete the text in the Alert Message box, to remove copy alerts.</para></note>				
				<procedure>
					<title>Adding or removing copy alerts to or from multiple items:</title>
					<step><para>Retrieve items to the <emphasis>Item Status</emphasis> screen.</para></step>
					<step><para>Select all items to be changed by highlighting the first item in the list, holding down the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key, and clicking on the last item. 						Select several, non-sequential items, by holding down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key and clicking on the required items.</para></step>
					<step><para>Continue to <emphasis>Edit Item Attributes</emphasis>, as above.</para></step>
				</procedure>
			</simplesect>
			<simplesect xml:id="viewingcopyalerts">
				<title>Viewing Copy Alerts</title>
				<para>Copy alerts may be viewed from the <emphasis>Item Status</emphasis> screen, at checkin, and at checkout.</para>
				<para>To view alerts from the <emphasis>Item Status</emphasis>, enter the barcode number.  Select the item and click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for Selected 
				Items</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Show Item Details</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para> 
				<para>To view alerts from the Item Status, enter the barcode number.  Select the item and click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for Selected Items</guimenu> 
				<guimenuitem>Show Item Details</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
				<para>The copy alert will display automatically at checkout and checkin.</para>
			</simplesect>
			<simplesect xml:id="copynotes">
				<title>Copy Notes</title>
				<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>copy notes</secondary></indexterm>
				<para>Copy notes are informational only. They may be internal or made available to the public in the OPAC.</para>	
				<procedure>
					<title>Accessing copy notes from the copy editor:</title>
					<step><para>Click <guibutton>Copy Notes</guibutton>.</para></step>
					<step><para>If a note exists, it will display with a yellow background.</para></step>
					<step><para>Click <guibutton>Add Note</guibutton> to create a new copy note.  Select the <guilabel>Public</guilabel> checkbox to make the note visible in 
					the OPAC.</para></step>
					<step><para>Click <guibutton>Add Note</guibutton> to display the new note.</para></step>
					<step><para>Use the <guibutton>Delete This Note</guibutton> button to remove a note from a copy record.</para></step>
				</procedure>			
			</simplesect>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="addingnewbibliographicrecords">
		<title>Adding New Bibliographic Records</title>
		<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>adding bibliographic records</secondary></indexterm>
		<para>Evergreen allows new bibliographic records to be added to the database through Z39.50 searching, MARC record file uploads, and original cataloging.</para> 
		<simplesect xml:id="ImportingMARCRecords-Z39">
			<title>Importing MARC Records via the Z39.50 Interface</title>
			<indexterm><primary>Z39.50</primary><secondary>importing records</secondary></indexterm>
			<procedure>
				<step><para><menuchoice><guimenu>Cataloging</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Import Record from Z39.50</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></step>
				<step><para>Select single or multiple pre configured Z39.50 targets from the list. Only subscription services require logins. Once databases have 
				been selected, click <guibutton>Save as Default</guibutton> to save the services to be searched and any usernames/passwords. These will be automatically selected the next 
				time the Z39.50 screen is opened.</para></step>
				<step><para>Fill in search criteria for the item and <guibutton>click Search</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<note><para>Active search fields will adjust to the selected targets. Keyword and Subject will only be active if the local catalog is selected. If multiple 
				targets are selected for a search, an active box may apply to only one target.</para></note>
				<step><para>Search results display in the bottom pane. To view long lists of results, use <guibutton>Hide Top Pane</guibutton> to view the results. Information about 
				each record retrieved appears on a separate summary line, with various columns of information. </para></step>
				<note><para>The <emphasis>Service</emphasis> column indicates where the record was found. If <emphasis>nativeevergreen-catalog</emphasis> is listed in the service 
				column, the record is already in the Evergreen database.</para></note>
				<step><para>From this screen users may: 
							
				</para></step>
			</procedure>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>Retrieve further results, if applicable</listitem>
					<listitem>View MARC records</listitem>
					<listitem>Export MARC records</listitem>
					<listitem>Import or overlay MARC records</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>			
		</simplesect>		
		<simplesect xml:id="importingrecords">
			<title>Importing Records</title>
			<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>importing records</secondary></indexterm>
			<procedure>
				<step><para>Highlight the record and click <guibutton>MARC Editor for Import</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>The record opens in the MARC Editor. Edit fixed and bibliographic fields. </para></step>
				<step><para>When finished, click <guibutton>Import Record</guibutton>.</para></step>		
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>If Fast Item Add was used, the copy editor will display.  Make necessary adjustments and click <guibutton>Create Copies</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>The record will display in the catalog view. </para></step>
				<note><para>If you did not utilize Fast Item Add as described above, you may now attach holdings as described in Adding holdings to title records.</para></note>
			</procedure>
			<note><para>Select <guilabel>Fast Item Add</guilabel> to input the call number and barcode data from this screen. This box is 
				<emphasis>sticky</emphasis> for the login. Please note that the status of items created this way is 
				<emphasis role="bold">Available</emphasis> rather than In Process.</para></note>
		</simplesect>	
		<simplesect xml:id="uploadingMARCfiles">
			<title>Uploading MARC Files</title>
			<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>uploading MARC files</secondary></indexterm>
			<para>Title records that do not already exist in the Evergreen database may be uploaded directly to the catalog through vendor-supplied MARC files. Multiple title records 
			can be uploaded and added at the same time.</para>
			<procedure>
				<step><para><menuchoice><guimenu>Cataloging</guimenu> <guimenuitem>MARC Batch Import/Export</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>
				<step><para>The MARC File Upload page opens and displays the Import Records form.</para></step>
				<step><para>Complete the form, creating a new Upload Queue. 
					<substeps>
				
						<step><para>Select <guilabel>Auto-Import Non-Colliding Records</guilabel> to automatically import MARC records from the file, if they are not already 
						in the Evergreen database. </para></step>	
						<step><para>Leave <guilabel>Select a Record Source</guilabel> defaulted to the OCLC setting. </para></step>
						<step><para>Click <guibutton>Browse...</guibutton> to choose the source MARC file. </para></step>
						<step><para>Click <guibutton>Upload</guibutton>.</para></step>
					</substeps>
				</para></step>	
				<step><para>Details from the file upload will appear. By default <guilabel>Limit to Non-Imported Records</guilabel> is selected and the table only displays MARC 
				records that conflict with others already in Evergreen. You may click <guilabel>Matches</guilabel> to view the conflicting Evergreen records. If the matched records 
				are not true matches, it is still possible to upload the selected records using the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> drop-down menu.</para></step>
				<note><para>The <guimenuitem>Import Attached Holdings</guimenuitem> option requires additional server configuration.</para></note>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>			
		<simplesect xml:id="creatingnewMARCrecords">
			<title>Creating New MARC Records</title>
			<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>creating new MARC records</secondary></indexterm>
			<para>New MARC records may be created in Evergreen using MARC templates. For detailed information on MARC standards, visit the Library of Congress website: 
			<ulink url='http://www.loc.gov/marc/'>http://www.loc.gov/marc/</ulink></para>
			<procedure>
				<step><para><menuchoice><guimenu>Cataloging</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Create New Marc Record</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>
				<step><para>The MARC Template screen will open.</para></step>
				<step><para>Select the appropriate template and click <guibutton>Load</guibutton>.</para></step>	
				<step><para>A blank MARC record will load. </para></step>
				<step><para>Complete the MARC record according to library policy. Tags and subfields may be added or deleted as required (right click on a field to view 
				available options). 
					<note><para>If the Fast Item Add box is selected, enter a call number and barcode.</para></note>
				</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Create Record</guibutton>.</para></step>	
				<step><para>The record is created and will open in the current default view. Holdings may now be added.</para></step>
				<note><para>If the <guilabel>Fast Item Add</guilabel> box was selected, the copy editor will open after <guibutton>Create Record</guibutton> is clicked.</para></note>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="MARCeditor">
		<title>Working with the MARC Editor</title>
		<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>MARC editor</secondary></indexterm>
		<para>The MARC Editor allows MARC tags, sub-fields, and indicators to be edited.</para> 
		<para>OPAC icons for text, moving pictures and sound rely on correct MARC coding in the leader and the 008, as do OPAC search filters such as publication date, item type, or 
		target audience. Bibliographic matching and de-duplicating also rely on correct MARC coding and consistency in use and content in particular MARC tags.</para> 
		<simplesect xml:id="editingMARCrecords">
			<title>Editing MARC Records</title>
			<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>editing MARC records</secondary></indexterm>
			<procedure>
				<step><para>Retrieve the record.</para></step>
				<step><para><menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu> <guimenuitem>MARC Edit</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. </para></step>
				<step><para>The MARC record will display. </para></step>
	
				<step><para>Select <guilabel>Stack</guilabel> subfields to alter subfields display.</para></step>
						<step><para>Right click into a tag field to add/remove rows or replace tags.</para></step>
						<step><para>To work with the data in a tag or indicator, click or <keycap>Tab</keycap> into the required field.  <emphasis>Right click</emphasis> to 
						view acceptable tags or indicators.</para></step>
				<step><para>When finished, click <guibutton>Save Record</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>	
			</procedure>
			<tip><para>The MARC Editor may be navigated using keyboard shortcuts. Click <guibutton>Help</guibutton> to see the shortcut menu from within the MARC Editor.</para></tip>
		</simplesect>	
		<simplesect xml:id="MARCrecordleader">
			<title>MARC Record Leader and MARC fixed field 008</title>
			<indexterm><primary>MARC</primary><secondary>MARC leader</secondary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>MARC</primary><secondary>fixed field 008</secondary></indexterm>
			<para>Parts of the leader and the 008 field can be edited in the MARC Editor via the fixed field editor box displayed above the MARC record. Information about the leader and 
			the 008 can be found on the Library of Congress’s MARC Standards page at <ulink url='http://www.loc.gov/marc/'>http://www.loc.gov/marc/</ulink>.</para>
					
			<procedure>
				<title>To edit the MARC record leader</title>				
				<step><para>Retrieve and display the appropriate record in MARC Edit view.</para></step>
				<step><para><emphasis>Click</emphasis> into any box displayed in the fixed field editor.</para></step>
				<step><para>Press <keycap>Tab</keycap> or use the mouse to move between fields. </para></step>			
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Save Record</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to save record edits.</para></step>
				<step><para>The OPAC icon for the appropriate material type will display.</para></step>	
			</procedure>
			<tip><para>The MARC Editor may be navigated using keyboard shortcuts. Click <guibutton>Help</guibutton> to see the shortcut menu from within the MARC Editor.</para></tip>
		</simplesect>	
		<simplesect xml:id="overlayingMARCrecords">
			<title>Overlaying MARC Records</title>
			<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>overlaying MARC records</secondary></indexterm>
			<para>Overlaying a MARC record replaces an existing MARC record while leaving all holdings, holds, active circulations, bills, and fines intact.</para>
			<para>In Evergreen, a record must be <emphasis>marked</emphasis> for overlay. The mark for overlay is by login. Only one record at a time may be marked for overlay. When another 
			record is marked for overlay, the previously marked item is <emphasis>de-marked</emphasis>. Once a record is marked, it remains marked until overlaid or until the user logs out 
			of Evergreen.</para> 
					
			<procedure>
				<title>Marking a record for overlay</title>
				<step><para>Search for and retrieve a record for overlay.</para></step>
				<step><para>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Mark for Overlay</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Record is now 
				<emphasis>marked</emphasis>.</para></step>
			</procedure>	
			<procedure>
				<title>Overlaying the marked record</title>
				<step><para>Once the record is marked for overlay, proceed to search for and import the new record from a Z39.50 target.</para></step>
				<step><para>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Cataloging</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Import Record from Z39.50</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Choose targets and enter search terms.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>MARC Editor for Overlay</guibutton>. The TCN of the Evergreen record marked for overlay is displayed.</para></step>
				<step><para>The record displays in MARC Edit view. Edit the record as necessary. </para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Overlay Record</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>The existing record will display along with a prompt to confirm the overlay. Panes may be moved to view the record in entirety, if required.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Overlay</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Confirm the overlay. The record in Evergreen is overlaid with the new MARC record. All preexisting holdings remain intact.</para></step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="cattemplates">
		<title>Cataloging Templates</title>
		<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>templates</secondary></indexterm>
		<para>This simplesect explains creating, using, exporting, and importing item record templates for cataloging. Use of templates enhances item creation and helps ensure 
		consistency in record format in the database.</para> 
				
		<procedure>
			<title>Creating item templates</title>
			<step><para>Search for and retrieve a record.</para></step>
			<step><para>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Holdings Maintenance</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Select an item record in list and click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for Selected Rows</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Edit Item Attributes</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
			</para></step>
			<step><para>The Copy Editor will open. Select the required template attributes by moving through fields and clicking <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> 
			for every edit. </para></step>	
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Save</guibutton> when edits are complete.</para></step>
			<step><para>Enter a template name at the prompt</para></step>	
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>
			<step><para>The template is now saved. Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>
			<step><para>This template may now be selected from the drop down menu.</para></step>
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to exit the Copy Editor.</para></step>			
		</procedure>
		<para>Once item templates have been created, they may be employed when items are added to the database.</para>
				
		<procedure>
			<title>Using item templates:</title>
			<step><para>Retrieve a record and display volumes.</para></step>
			<step><para>Select the appropriate volume.</para></step>	
			<step><para><menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for this Row</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Add Items</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>
			<step><para>Enter the number of copies and barcode(s).</para></step>	
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> then <guibutton>Create</guibutton> to open the Copy Editor.</para></step>
			<step><para>Choose the appropriate template from the drop down menu.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>.</para></step>
			<step><para>Make edit as necessary. When finished, click <guibutton>Create Copies</guibutton>.</para></step>
			<step><para>Items are created.</para></step>
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>			
		</procedure>
		<para>Saved templates are only viewable by the login that created them. Templates must be exported in order to share templates amongst staff members.</para>
		<para>Exporting Item Templates</para>		
		<procedure>
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Export</guibutton> in the top left hand corner of the Copy Editor. This will export all templates for the user.</para></step>
			<step><para>Select where the template should be saved on the workstation, name the file, and click <guibutton>Save</guibutton>. </para></step>	
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>					
		</procedure>
				
		<procedure>
			<title>Importing templates:</title>
			<step><para>Click on <guibutton>Import</guibutton> in the top left hand corner of the Copy Editor.</para></step>
			<step><para>Navigate to the file’s location, select the file and click <guibutton>Open</guibutton>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>					
		</procedure>
	</section>					
	<section xml:id="buckets">
		<title>Buckets</title>
		<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>buckets</secondary></indexterm>
		<para>The Buckets function in Evergreen groups records together and allows for batch changes and the creation of pull lists.</para> 
		<para>Batch changes allow many records to be grouped together for changes to be enacted on them all at once, instead performing individual edits. Buckets allow materials to be 
		tracked and worked by multiple staff members. </para> 	
		<para>Possible bucket uses include batch editing/deleting and grouping like records (e.g. Christmas items) to temporarily change their statuses.  Buckets may also be used to 
		create bibliographies and/or pull lists. </para> 
		<para>Buckets are useful to group records together over a period of time. Evergreen’s bucket functionality allows records to be added to new or existing buckets where they remain 
		until they are manually ungrouped. An item’s location in a bucket does not affect normal library functions such as circulation.  Being in a bucket is not an item status.</para> 
		<para>Buckets may be shared or private and are associated with a login.</para> 
		<note><para>When working with buckets, it is important to ensure that record type corresponds with bucket type. Copy records may not be added to bibliographic 
		record buckets and vice versa.</para></note>
		<para>Buckets may be created independently of accessing records or they may be created from a record view.</para>
		<procedure>
			<step><para><menuchoice><guimenu>Cataloging</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Manage Record Buckets</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>
			<step><para><menuchoice><guimenu>Bucket Actions </guimenu> <guimenuitem> New Bucket</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Name the bucket and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Confirm the action.</para></step>
			<step><para>The Bucket View changes to display the new bucket as the <emphasis>active</emphasis> bucket. The bucket is numbered and the creating owner is 
			identified.</para></step>	
			<step><para>All buckets created by this login are available in the drop down menu.</para></step>					
		</procedure>
				
		<procedure>
			<title>Creating record buckets from within a record</title>
			<step><para>Search for, retrieve, and display the desired bibliographic record.</para></step>
			<step><para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Add to Bucket</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Select <guimenuitem>Add to New Bucket</guimenuitem>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Name the bucket and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The results are the same as creating a bucket using the steps above.</para></step>		
		</procedure>
		<para>Once a bucket has been added, records may be added to it.</para>
		<procedure>
			<step><para>Search for, retrieve, and display the desired bibliographic record.</para></step>
			<step><para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Add to Bucket</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Select the appropriate bucket and click <guibutton>Add to Selected Bucket</guibutton>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>To confirm this action, go back to the Record Bucket tab. The bucket now contains the record.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Continue to add records, if required.</para></step>	
		</procedure>	
		<procedure>
			<title>To work from within the buckets module</title>	
			<step><para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Cataloging </guimenu> <guimenuitem> Manage Record Buckets</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>
			<step><para>Select the Record Query tab on the left side of the screen.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Select the appropriate bucket and click <guibutton>Add to Selected Bucket</guibutton>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Use <guibutton>Add All to Pending Records</guibutton> or select individual records and <guibutton>Add Selected to Pending Records</guibutton>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Select the Pending Records tab.</para></step>
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Add All to current Bucket</guibutton> or <guibutton>Add Selected to current Bucket</guibutton>.</para></step>	
		</procedure>
		<tip>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>The column picker allows the data display to be manipulated within the bucket.</listitem>
				<listitem>Clicking on <menuchoice><guimenu>List Actions </guimenu> <guimenuitem> Save List CSV to File</guimenuitem></menuchoice> exports all column headers and 
				displayed data to the workstation in a text file format. 
				This feature may be used to create bibliographies or similar lists.</listitem>
				<listitem>Clicking on <menuchoice><guimenu>List Actions </guimenu> <guimenuitem> Print List CSV</guimenuitem></menuchoice> prints column headers and 
				displayed data.</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</tip>
		<simplesect xml:id="addingcopyrecordscopybuckets">
			<title>Adding Copy Records to Copy Buckets</title>
			<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>copy buckets</secondary></indexterm>
			<para>While creating copy buckets is similar to creating record buckets (simply choose Copy Buckets in the menu choice), there are significant differences in adding copy 
			records to a bucket. Records must be added to copy buckets from the copy record level. This may be done from several locations within the Evergreen client.</para>	
					
			<procedure>
				<title>Adding copy records from the holdings maintenance record summary screen:</title>
				<step><para>Select the required record and choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for Selected Rows</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Add Items to Buckets</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Add the record to an existing bucket or create a new bucket on the fly.</para></step>	
				<step><para>The copy record is now in the selected bucket. The displayed data differs slightly from the Record Bucket view.</para></step>	
			</procedure>
				
			<procedure>
				<title>Adding copy records from the item status screen:</title>	
				<step><para>Select the required record(s) and choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for Catalogers</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Add Items to Buckets</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> or choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for Selected Items</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Add to Item Bucket</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Select the desired bucket and click <guibutton>Add to Selected Bucket</guibutton> or <guibutton>Create a New Bucket</guibutton>.</para></step>	
			</procedure>	
			<procedure>
				<title>Adding copy records from within the copy buckets module:</title>
				<step><para>Enter item barcode(s) into the Pending Copies barcode box.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Submit</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Item(s) will display. </para></step>
				<step><para>Use <guibutton>Add All</guibutton> or select the appropriate items and <guibutton>Add Selected</guibutton> to move items to the bucket displayed in the 
				bottom pane.</para></step>	
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="WorkingwithRecordsinaBucket">
			<title>Working with Records in a Bucket</title>
			<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>record buckets</secondary></indexterm>
			<para>Once records have been placed in a bucket, a variety of functions may be performed. </para>	
					
			<procedure>
				<title>To batch edit records:</title>
				<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>record buckets</secondary><tertiary>batch edit</tertiary></indexterm>
				<step><para>Access the Copy Bucket view by choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu> 
				<guimenuitem>Copy Buckets</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Select the appropriate bucket from the drop down menu.</para></step>	
				<step><para>When the bucket is displayed click <guibutton>Edit Item Attributes</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>The Copy Editor window opens. Note that all the barcodes, call numbers, 
				and shelving locations display.</para></step>
				<step><para>Make the desired edits.</para></step>	
				<step><para>Apply each change.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Modify Copies</guibutton> to save all changes.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>	
				<step><para>The desired changes are made for all selected items.</para></step>			
			</procedure>
			<caution><para>Use caution when using the <guilabel>Transfer to Specific Volume</guilabel> action.</para></caution>  	
			<procedure>
				<title>Removing records from buckets</title>
				<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>buckets</secondary><tertiary>removing records</tertiary></indexterm>
				<step><para>Select the desired record.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Remove Selected from Bucket</guibutton></para></step>
			</procedure>
			<para>The same procedure is used for both Record and Copy Buckets</para>
				
			<procedure>
				<title>Retrieving </title>
				<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>shared buckets</secondary></indexterm>
				<step><para>Access the copy or record bucket management screen as described above.</para></step>
				<step><para>In drop down menu beside <guimenu>Choose a bucket…</guimenu> select <guimenuitem>Retrieve shared bucket</guimenuitem>.</para></step>
				<step><para>Enter the desired bucket number and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>
				<step><para>The requested bucket now displays. The bucket number (assigned by Evergreen) and owner displays.</para></step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="MergingBibliographicRecords">
		<title>Merging Bibliographic Records</title>
		<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>merging bibliographic records</secondary></indexterm>
		<para>A common application for the merge function in Evergreen is to replace brief records with full records. This is only necessary when a full record cannot be located 
		in a Z39.50 target.</para>
		<para>Any volume and copy records or holds associated with the brief record will be transferred to the full record upon merging.</para>	
		<procedure>
			<step><para>Create a bucket for the records you wish to merge.</para></step>
			<step><para>Identify records to be merged and add them to the bucket.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Retrieve the bucket by selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Record Buckets</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Merge All Records</guibutton>.</para></step>
			<step><para>Select one record as the Lead Record.  (Generally, the better quality, full record.)</para></step>
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Merge</guibutton>. </para></step>
			<step><para>The brief record is subsumed by the full record. All of the volumes, copies and holds associated with the brief record are now attached to the full 
			record.</para></step>			
		</procedure>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="Addingholdings">
	     	<title>Adding holdings to title records</title>
		<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>adding holdings</secondary></indexterm>
		<para>This lesson demonstrates adding your library’s volume and copy records to a title record. </para>
		<procedure>
		      <step>
			 <para>Search the catalogue for a record that matches the item in hand, as described in <xref linkend="locatingrecords"/>.</para>
		      </step>
		      <step>
			 <informalfigure>
			    <para>When record is displayed, select <menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Holdings Maintenance</guimenuitem>
			       </menuchoice>.</para>
			    <para>
			       <mediaobject>
				  <alt>screenshot of staff client</alt>
				  <imageobject>
				     <imagedata scalefit="0" fileref="../media/add_holdings-1.png"/>
				  </imageobject>

			       </mediaobject>
			    </para>
			 </informalfigure>
		      </step>
	      		<step>
			 <informalfigure>
			    <para>Record opens in <guilabel>record summary</guilabel> view. Select your library from
			       the list and click <menuchoice>
				  <guimenu>Actions for Selected Rows</guimenu>
				  <guimenuitem>Add Volumes</guimenuitem>
			       </menuchoice>.</para>
			    <para>
			       <mediaobject>
				  <alt>screenshot of staff client</alt>
				  <imageobject>
				     <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/add_holdings-2.png"/>
				  </imageobject>
			       </mediaobject>
			    </para>
			 </informalfigure>
		      </step>
		      <step>
			 <informalfigure>
			    <para>Enter amount in <guilabel># of volumes</guilabel> field, type in a call number, or
			       if the call number pulled from MARC record is acceptable click
				  <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to bring call number down to call number field, enter
			       number of copies, scan barcode, and click <guibutton>Edit then Create</guibutton>.
			       Use <keycap>Tab</keycap> or <keycap>Enter</keycap> to move through fields.</para>
			    <para>
			       <mediaobject>
				  <alt>screenshot of staff client</alt>
				  <imageobject role="html">
				     <imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/add_holdings-3.png"/>
				  </imageobject>
				  <imageobject role="fo">
				     <imagedata scale="70" fileref="../media/add_holdings-3.png"/>
				  </imageobject>
			       </mediaobject>
			    </para>
			 </informalfigure>
		      </step>
		      <step>
			 <informalfigure>
			    <para>The <guilabel>Copy Editor</guilabel> opens. Make all necessary edits by moving
			       through fields and clicking <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> on every edit, and click
				  <guibutton>Create Copies</guibutton></para>
			    <para>
			       <mediaobject xml:id="add-editor">
				  <alt>screenshot of staff client</alt>
				  <imageobject role="html">
				     <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/add_holdings-4.png"/>
				  </imageobject>
			       </mediaobject>

			    </para>
			 </informalfigure>
		      </step>
		      <step>
			 <informalfigure>
			    <para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
			    <para>
			       <mediaobject>
				  <alt>screenshot of staff client</alt>
				  <imageobject role="html">
				     <imagedata scalefit="0" fileref="../media/add_holdings-5.png"/>
				  </imageobject>
				  <imageobject role="fo">
				     <imagedata scale="80" fileref="../media/add_holdings-5.png"/>
				  </imageobject>
			       </mediaobject>
			    </para>
			 </informalfigure>
		      </step>
		   	</procedure>
			   <tip>
			      <para>Once an item is created it is assigned a status of <emphasis>In Process</emphasis>. Item
				 must be checked in to become <emphasis>Available</emphasis> or cataloguer can choose to
				    <guimenuitem>Edit Item Attributes</guimenuitem> and change status to
				    <emphasis>Available</emphasis> once record has been created and saved to
				 database.</para>
			      <para>Creation and use of item record templates is recommended. See <xref linkend="cattemplates"/> for
				 more information.</para>
			   </tip>
		   <simplesect xml:id="add-hold">
		      <title>New Copies and Holds</title>
		      <para>Because of the way Evergreen targets holds new copies are not guaranteed to fulfill
			 pre-existing holds correctly until 24 hours after cataloguing. If your cataloguing
			 turn-around time is shorter than 24 hours you can ensure the new copy is captured correctly
			 at check in with the steps below.</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					       <para>After adding the item select <menuchoice>
						     <guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu>
						     <guimenuitem>View Holds</guimenuitem>
						  </menuchoice></para>
				</step>
				 <step>
				       <para>If there are outstanding hold requests, select the hold that is next in line
					  then choose <menuchoice>
					     <guimenu>Actions for Selected Holds</guimenu>
					     <guimenuitem>Find Another Target</guimenuitem>
					  </menuchoice>. This forces Evergreen to re-target the hold and recognize the newly
					  catalogued item.</para> 
				 </step>
				 <step>
				    <para> Check in the new item to capture it for the selected hold.</para>
				 </step>
			</procedure>
   		</simplesect>
	</section>	
	<section xml:id="electronicresourcesvisible">	
		<title>Cataloguing Electronic Resources -- Finding Them in OPAC searches</title>
		<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>electronic resources</secondary></indexterm>
		<para>For electronic resources to be visible in the catalog, you should add the <literal>9</literal> subfield in the <literal>856</literal> data field to indicate
		 which organizational units will be able to find the resource.</para>
		<procedure>
		  	 <step>
				<para>Open the record in the cataloging module</para>
			</step>
		 	 <step>
				<para>Add the <literal>9</literal> subfield to the record and enter the short name of the organizational unit for the value. For example:</para>
<screen>856 40 $u http://lwn.net $y Linux Weekly News $9 BR1</screen>
				<para>would make this item visible to people searching in a library scope that contains <literal>BR1</literal>.</para>
				<note><para>You can enter more than one <literal>9</literal> subfield or you can enter the parent organizational unit to make this item visible in more than 
				one organizational unit under the same parent organizational unit.</para></note>
			</step>
		 	
		 	 <step>
				<para>Save the record</para>
				<para>After a short time the electronic resource should appear in OPAC searches</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="PrintingSpineandPocketLabels">
		<title>Printing Spine and Pocket Labels</title>
		<indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>spine</secondary></indexterm>
		<indexterm><primary>labels</primary><secondary>pocket</secondary></indexterm>
		<para>Copy buckets may be used to group items requiring labels.</para>	
		<procedure>
			<step><para>Locate the correct copy bucket.</para></step>
			<step><para>Select <guimenuitem>Show Status</guimenuitem>.</para></step>
			<step><para>Items display in the Item Status screen.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Select items requiring labels (hold the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key down and click the required items to select multiple items; if all items require labels, hold the 
			<keycap>Shift</keycap> key down while clicking the first and last items in the list).</para></step>	
			<step><para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for Selected Items </guimenu> <guimenuitem> Print Spine Labels</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.</para></step>
			<step><para>The Spine Labels screen will display.</para></step>
			<step><para>Use the form on the left of the screen to modify spine and pocket label display. </para></step>
			<step><para>Select <guimenuitem>Re-Generate</guimenuitem> to view changes. (Checkbox selections are saved for a login, but Re-Generate must be clicked to view these changes. 
			<emphasis>On line:</emphasis> selections are not saved.)</para></step>		
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Available Macros</guibutton> to view auto-fill options for custom lines.</para></step>
			<step><para>When finished, click <guibutton>Preview</guibutton> and <guibutton>Print</guibutton>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>From the Print Preview screen, select <guimenuitem>Print Page</guimenuitem>.</para></step>		
		</procedure>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="DeletingRecords">
		<title>Deleting Records</title>
			<indexterm><primary>cataloguing</primary><secondary>deleting records</secondary></indexterm>	
		<procedure>
			<title>Batch deletions:</title>
			<step><para>Create a copy bucket for the items to be deleted (<menuchoice><guimenu>Cataloging</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Manage Copy Buckets</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>; create a New Bucket</para></step>		
			<step><para>Enter the barcodes for the to-be-deleted items into the Pending Copies simplesect of the Copy Buckets screen.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Add All of the items to the selected bucket.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Delete All from Catalog.</para></step>
			<step><para>The Deleted? status for each item will change from <emphasis>No</emphasis> to <emphasis>Yes</emphasis>.</para></step>	
		</procedure>
		<para>When all items have been deleted from a bibliographic record, the bibliographic record is also deleted from the system.  The record may still be retrieved through the client, 
		but will display as Deleted.  These records will not display in the OPAC.</para>
		<para>Individual item records may be deleted from the Holdings Maintenance screen.</para>
				
		<procedure>
			<title>To delete individual records:</title>
			<step><para>Highlight the item (barcode) to be deleted.</para></step>		
			<step><para>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for Selected Rows</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Delete Items</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Confirm.</para></step>	
		</procedure>
		<para>If the deleted item was the last item attached to the MARC record, the MARC record will be automatically deleted.</para>
		<para>Occasionally, a bibliographic record may need to be deleted (e.g. an incorrect record was imported to the system).</para>
		<procedure>	
			<step><para>Retrieve the record.</para></step>		
			<step><para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Delete Record</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.</para></step>		
		</procedure>
				
		<procedure>
			<title>To restore records:</title>
			<step><para>Retrieve the record through the staff client.</para></step>		
			<step><para><menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for this record</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Undelete Record</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></step>	
			<step><para>Confirm the action by selecting the checkbox and Undelete in the resulting popup box.</para></step>	
		</procedure>
	</section>
	
</chapter>
