<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="authoring">
    <title>Authoring Documentation</title>
    <info>
        <abstract>
            <para>DocBook ....</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Structure: Concept, Task, Reference</title>
        <para> Every chapter in Evergreen documentation, and in some cases sections, should begin by
            explaining this chapter's concepts, or core ideas, to the reader. This gives you the
            opportunity to clarify new or ambiguous terminology for otherwise experienced readers:
            for example, in a circulation overview you will want to differentiate non-cataloged
            items vs. pre-cataloged items. Explaining concepts also gives less experienced readers a
            chance to fill in gaps in their knowledge. </para>
        <para> For example, in the circulation section of the manual, you may write the following
            set of tasks: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Checking out an item Checking in an item Renewing items Recording in-house
                    uses</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para> Separating the concepts from the tasks gives your readers the chance to jump directly
            to the task they want to complete, if they are already familiar with the concepts. </para>
        <para> When you write your task information, try to organize it as a set of numbered steps
            that covers the most common cases. Compose each step in two sentences: first, describe
            the action the reader must complete, followed by a sentence describing the results of
            successfully performing the action if applicable. Preface optional steps with
            (Optional):. For example: </para>
        <para> To check out a cataloged item to a patron: </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>In the staff client, select Circulation→Check Out Items. The Check Out tab
                    appears.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Enter the patron barcode in the Barcode text field. The system retrieves and
                    displays the patron information, with the Check Out button highlighted in the
                    action bar.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Enter the item barcode in the text field beside the Barcode: selection in the
                    drop-down menu.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <!-- the following was copied from the wiki and has not been marked up yet. It is wrapped
        with para elements so that it will not trigger the XML validator -->
        
        <para>(Optional): Select a different due date from the date selector. 4. Click Submit to
            check out the item to the patron. The item barcode, due date, and title appear in the
            transaction summary table. 5. Repeat steps 3 and 4 for each additional item the patron
            wants to borrow. 6. (Optional): Click Print Receipt to print a receipt summarizing the
            transactions for the patron. The Print Receipt window opens. Reference Reference
            information consists of lists of commands, configuration files and settings, software
            prerequisites, APIs, etc that need to be rigorously documented to support use cases
            outside the core task documentation. Reference information is typically organized by
            type, then by alphabetical order. For example, all system commands will be documented in
            their own section of the manual in alphabetical order, and all APIs will be documented
            in their own section of the manual in alphabetical order. System commmands: * autogen.sh
            * import_holdings.pl * marc2bre.pl * osrf_ctl.sh * … APIs: *
            open-ils.auth.authenticate.complete * open-ils.auth.authenticate.init * … Discuss how
            each system feature would be used by each scenario institution If applicable, provide an
            example of how each institutional scenario (Le Grande University vs. Metropolitan Public
            Library Consortium) would likely put the feature being discussed into use. You will
            probably want to include this information in the concept topic(s) introducing the
            feature, or as a separate concept topic or set of topics following the introductory
            concept topic. The scenarios give you a few different facets to describe when explaining
            the topic to your reader: * academic vs. public libraries * consortiums vs. standalone
            libraries * libraries with large collections vs. libraries with small collections Style
            guidelines Use the active voice Avoid the passive voice. For example: Rather than: The
            barcode is checked for a valid check digit when it is scanned. Use the active voice:
            When you scan the barcode, the system checks for a valid check digit. If your sentence
            contains “is”, be careful: it might be using the passive voice. Write concise sentences
            Try to keep your sentences brief. Avoiding complex phrases with related clauses helps
            readers concentrate on a single idea at a time. It also helps translators. Prefix
            conditional clauses If your sentence is conditional, place the conditional clause at the
            beginning of the sentence. When your reader skims your text and only sees the first part
            of the sentence, they might take the wrong action. For example: Rather than: Click the
            **Cancel** button to prevent the changes from being applied if the results did not match
            your expectations. Use: If the results did not match your expectations, click the
            **Cancel** button to prevent the changes from being applied. Contractions,
            abbreviations, and acronyms Do not use contractions (“you're”, “we've”, “it's”) or Latin
            abbreviations (e.g., etc., i.e.). These can be hard to translate and hard to read. If
            you use an acronym, provide the full form of the acronym and include the acronym in
            parentheses in the first use in your topic. After the acronym has been introduced, you
            can use the acronym on its own for the remainder of the topic. Highlighting Use bold to
            highlight the names of GUI elements such as field and button labels, window names, and
            menu options. </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
