<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="indexterms">
  <title>Marking Terms for Dynamic Index Creation</title>
  <info>
    <abstract>
      <para>This chapter describes how to mark up terms for generating a dynamic index of Evergreen
        documentation. </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section>
    <title>Marking Terms for Index Entry</title>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <para>DocBook supports two methods for generating an index. One is to explicitly create the
        index. The other is to generate the index when the book is published based on elements
        included in the text. We use the second approach. </para>
      <para>Authors are not required to mark up index elements; editors will complete any index
        tagging not accomplished at the authoring stage.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Specifying index entries</title>
      <para>Index entries are specified by adding <tag class="element">indexterm</tag> elements in
        the text of the book. An index entry must contain one <tag class="element">primary</tag>
        element. The value of the <tag class="element">primary</tag> element is the top-level entry
        that will appear in the generated index.</para>
      <para>In addition, an <tag class="element">indexterm</tag> element can contain the following
        optional elements:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>One <tag class="element">secondary</tag> element that specifies a second level entry
            in the generated index.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>One <tag class="element">tertiary</tag> element that specifies a third level index
            entry.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>One <tag class="element">see</tag> element that specifies an alternate entry to
            which the reader is redirected.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>One <tag class="element">seealso</tag> element that specifies an additional entry
            with relevant information.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>If you want to mark an <tag class="element">indexterm</tag> and you aren't sure what
        elements to assign it, use the <tag>primary</tag> element.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Example: Marking a Primary Index Term</title>
      <para>The Open Scalable Request Framework (<indexterm>
          <primary>OpenSRF</primary>
        </indexterm>, pronounced 'open surf'), is a stateful, decentralized service architecture
        that allows developers to create applications for Evergreen with a minimum of knowledge of
        its structure.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Example: Marking a Secondary Index Term</title>
      <para> Indexed-field weighting, which controls relevance ranking in Evergreen, is configured
        in the 'weight' column of the <indexterm>
          <primary>Evergreen Tables</primary>
          <secondary>config.metabib_field</secondary>
        </indexterm> table of the Evergreen database.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Specifying where the Index is Generated</title>
      <para>In order for the index to auto-generate, every Evergreen book has an <tag
          class="emptytag">index</tag> element. The index will be generated in the position that
        corresponds to the element's location in the book file. The <tag class="emptytag"
          >index</tag> element follows all other chapters and appendices.</para>
    </simplesect>
  </section>
</chapter>
