<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="filenames">
  <title>File Structure and Filenames</title>
 
  <info>
    <abstract>
      <para>This chapter describes the physical file structure for Evergreen documentation and file
        naming conventions, including the  <tag class="element">olink</tag> element. </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section>
    <title>File Structure for Evergreen Documentation</title>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <para>The files for Evergreen documentation reside within a public directory on
        evergreen-ils.org. </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>File structure for Evergreen documents</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The set is represented by set.xml, a single file in the docs subdirectory of
            evergreen-ils.org</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The two book elements are in separate subdirectories under the docs subdirectory,
            and are labeled book1.xml and book2.xml</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Chapter elements are in their own separate subdirectories under their respective
            book directories</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Glossaries and similar chapter-like elements are treated like chapters, and are in
            separate subdirectories under their respective book directories</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Images and similar media files are placed in subdirectories under their respective
            folders.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Filename conventions</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Evergreen filenames are in lower case without underscores or periods.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The folders for images and other multimedia are named media. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The XML id for the chapter is the same as the XML filename, such as sysadmin. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conventions for olinks</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To simplify the creation of olinks between between books, every Evergreen file has a
            <glossterm>document id</glossterm> that parallels the file's filename and xml:id
          attribute. Therefore, a book-level file called book2.xml has an xml:id of book2 and a
          document id of book2, while a chapter file called sysadmin.xml has an xml:id of sysadmin
          and also a document id of sysadmin.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The document id is the first element within the file after the xml declaration, and
          has the structure element id="name".</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
