<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="overview">
  <title>Evergreen and DocBook</title>
  <section>
    <title>About our approach</title>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <para>This is the style guide for documentation produced for the Evergreen open-source library
        software project. This manual is intended to help everyone involved in the documentation
        "supply chain" by providing guidance wherever a decision about documentation formats needs
        to be made, from image size to file-naming conventions and the approved lists of tags and
        XSL stylesheets. </para>
      <para>This is a living document in a fairly new endeavor, so your feedback on areas that need
        correction or expansion is encouraged and warmly appreciated. </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>History</title>
      <para>In May, 2009, the Evergreen Documentation Interest Group committed to single-source,
        XML, using the DocBook 5.0 documentation standard, for all Evergreen-wide documentation, and
        committed to working as a group. </para>
      <para>The rationales for this approach were as follows:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Evergreen project needed to move past the gaps and duplicated efforts of having
            documentation written within local library systems and leverage its size and skills
            toward a common goal.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The commitment to single-source documentation means that core Evergreen
            documentation would be could be repurposed as necessary into many different formats --
            one core set of files, many outputs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>XML provides structure to a document and semantic "meaningfulness." </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The DocBook standard is a commonly-used documentation standard that has the
            advantages over other standards of relative ease of use and a long, well-established
            history of development and stewardship. DocBook is also the de facto standard XML schema
            and publishing tool set for a number of open source projects, so we will be able to
            capitalize on the work others have done before us.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>DocBook 5.0</title>
      <para>DocBook 5.0 is the authoring language for Evergreen documentation. DocBook 5.0 provides
        a structured XML-based grammar for writing complex technical documentation. It is also an
        OASIS standard. The remainder of this style guide discusses how Evergreen uses
        DocBook.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Our production model in a nutshell</title>
      <para>(Note: this primarily applies to documentation that is making its way into the Evergreen
        documentation XML toolchain for the first time. We have not yet developed a production model
        for revising XML documents.) </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Documentation writers</emphasis> author Evergreen
              documentation in whatever format they choose (this is a guiding principal of the
              Evergreen documentation project), using the editors of their choice. While authors are
              encouraged to produce documentation in DocBook 5.0, we will accept new documentation
              in any form the author chooses to write it (and however "localized" it may be). Note
              that the DIG project will be providing heavily-commented template files for DocBook
              XML production. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Authors submit documents to the <emphasis role="bold">intake team</emphasis>, who
              will submit the documentation to functional testing and revise content accordingly.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If documentation needs conversion from its format to DocBook 5.0, the DIG
                <emphasis role="bold">XML conversion team</emphasis> wrangles it.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>One the files are in valid, well-formed XML conforming to the DocBook 5.0
              standard, <emphasis role="bold">DIG XML editors</emphasis> (the human kind of editors)
              review the files for conformance with Evergreen documentation style guidelines.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>When the XML files are ready, the <emphasis role="bold">DIG transform
                team</emphasis> members use a variety of back-end tools to process the files (or, in
              DocBook and XML terminology, <glossterm>transform</glossterm> the files) into HTML,
              PDF, and other formats. <emphasis role="bold">Web designers</emphasis> play a crucial
              role at this stage as well, creating and maintaining the Cascading Stylesheets (CSS)
              that make the documentation aesthetically pleasing and more user-friendly. Finally, a
              small group of <emphasis role="bold">"the buck stops here" editors</emphasis> move the
              HTML and PDF files into their folders on the website.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
      </para>
    </simplesect>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Formatting XML</title>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <para>Documentation writers who author in XML generally fall into two camps: those who prefer
        a full-featured WYSIWYG editor with built-in validation tools, and those who prefer to code
        XML "by hand." </para>
      <para>DIG is neutral on this issue, but can recommend software for those interested in
        authoring, editing, revising, updating, or validating XML files. Documentation editors
        higher up in the XML chain will ultimately reformat all XML so it has appropriate indenting
        and wrapping. If you are using an editor such as oXygen, most of this formatting is already
        done for you by the software. If you are coding XML by hand, you are encouraged but not
        required to keep lines under 80 characters long, and to avoid leaving white space between
        elements. </para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
      <title>Validation</title>
      <para>More crucially than indenting and white space, the DIG would appreciate it if authors
        producing XML would attempt to validate their files prior to submitting them to ensure the
        markup is valid and well-formed XML that conforms with DocBook 5. However, if you run
        against insoluble validation problems, please do not let that hold you up; just submit the
        files and we will fix the problems and advise you of what we found. </para>
    </simplesect>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="info">
    <title>Other Resources</title>
    <simplesect>
      <title>DocBook References</title>
      <para>For more general references and familiarization with with DocBook, see the
        following:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xl:href="http://DocBook.org/">DocBook.org</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xl:href="http://opensource.bureau-cornavin.com/crash-course/">The Crash Course to
              DocBook</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xl:href="http://nwalsh.com/docbook/">Norman Walsh's DocBook page</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
  </section>
</chapter>
