<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="more_info">
	<info>
		<title>Getting More Information</title>
	</info>	
	<para>This documentation is just one way to learn about Evergreen and find solutions to Evergreen challenges. Below is a list of many other resources to help you find answers to almost any question 
	you might have.</para>
		<para><link xl:href="http://www.open-ils.org/">Evergreen Wiki</link> - Loads of information and the main portal to the Evergreen community.</para><indexterm><primary>wiki</primary></indexterm>
		<para><link xl:href="http://www.open-ils.org/listserv.php">Evergreen mailing lists</link> - These are excellent for initiating questions. There are several lists including:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><link xl:href="http://libmail.georgialibraries.org/mailman/listinfo/open-ils-general">General list</link> - General inquiries regarding Evergreen. If unsure about 
				which list to use, this is a good stating point.</listitem><indexterm><primary>mailing lists</primary></indexterm>
				<listitem><link xl:href="http://libmail.georgialibraries.org/mailman/listinfo/open-ils-dev">Developer list</link> - Technical questions should be asked here including 
				questions regarding installation. As well, patches can be submitted using this list and developer communication also takes place here. </listitem>
				<listitem><link xl:href="http://libmail.georgialibraries.org/mailman/listinfo/open-ils-documentation">DIG list</link> - This list is used for questions and 
				feedback regarding this documentation, the Documentation Interest Group and other documentation related ideas and issues.</listitem><indexterm><primary>Documentation Interest Group (DIG)</primary></indexterm>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para><link xl:href="http://evergreen-ils.org/blog/">Evergreen Blog</link> - Great for getting general news and updates about Evergreen. It is also an interesting historical read 
		with entries dating back to the early beginnings of Evergreen.</para>
		<para><link xl:href="http://evergreen-ils.org/irc.php">Evergreen IRC channel</link> - Allows live chat. Many developers hang out here and will try to field technical questions. This 
		is often the quickest way to get a solution to a specific problem. Just remember that while the channel is open 24/7, there are times when no one is available in the channel. The most 
		active times for the IRC channel seem to be weekday afternoons (Eastern Standard Time). There is also an archive of logs from the chat sessions available on the 
		<link xl:href="http://evergreen-ils.org/irc.php">IRC</link> page.</para><indexterm><primary>IRC chat</primary></indexterm>
		<para><link xl:href="http://planet.evergreen-ils.org/">Evergreen related community blogs</link> - Evergreen related blog entries from the community.</para>
		<para><link xl:href="http://rscel.evergreen-ils.org/">Resource Sharing Cooperative of Evergreen Libraries (RSCEL)</link> - Provides some technical documents and a means for the 
		Evergreen community to collaborate with other libraries.</para><indexterm><primary>Resource Sharing Cooperative of Evergreen Libraries (RSCEL)</primary></indexterm>
		<para><link xl:href="http://evergreen-ils.org/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=evergreen_libraries">List of current Evergreen libraries</link> - Locate other libraries who are  
		using Evergreen.</para>		
</appendix>


