<ils_events>
	<notes>
		This file describes the event codes that an ILS method might return.  Not all
		methods will return event codes and it is up to each method to define which
		types of events it may return.  The standard event procedure is to return an
		object (JSON hash) with a field called "ilsevent" which contains the event code
		below.

		If events need to be placed into groups for any reason, the segregation shall
		be defined below with the accompanying events.
	</notes>

	<event code='0' textcode='SUCCESS'>
		<desc>No errors or unexpected events occurred</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='1000' textcode='LOGIN_FAILED'>
		<desc>
			User login failed.  Why the login failed is not specified.
		</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='1001' textcode='NO_SESSION'>
		<desc>
			User login session has either timed out or does not exist.
		</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='1002' textcode='USER_NOT_FOUND'>
		<desc>
			Someone attempted to retrieve a user from the system and the user
			was not found.
		</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='1500' textcode='CIRCULATION_NOT_FOUND'>
		<desc>
			Someone attempted to retrieve a circulation object from the system and 
			the object was not found.
		</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='1501' textcode='BIBLIO_RECORD_NOT_FOUND'>
		<desc>
			Someone attempted to retrieve a biblio record entry object from the 
			system and the object was not found.
		</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='1502' textcode='COPY_NOT_FOUND'>
		<desc>
			Someone attempted to retrieve a copy object from the 
			system and the object was not found.
		</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='1503' textcode='HOLD_NOT_FOUND'>
		<desc>
			Someone attempted to retrieve a hold object from the 
			system and the object was not found.
		</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='1503' textcode='TRANSIT_NOT_FOUND'>
		<desc>
			Someone attempted to retrieve a transit object from the 
			system and the object was not found.
		</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='1503' textcode='BILLING_NOT_FOUND'>
		<desc>
			Someone attempted to retrieve a transit object from the 
			system and the object was not found.
		</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='1700' textcode='ROUTE_COPY'>
		<desc>
			A copy needs to be routed to a different location	
		</desc>
	</event>


	<event code='2000' textcode='BAD_PARAMS'>
		<desc>
			Invalid parameters were encountered in a method
		</desc>
	</event>

	<event code='5000' textcode='PERM_FAILURE'>
		<desc> 
			Permission Error.  * The object returning this code shall also 
			contain a field "ilsperm" containing the name of the permission which failed 
			and a field called "ilspermloc" defining the location at which the permission
			failed if available.
		</desc>
	</event>
</ils_events>




