<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="advancedsearch">
	<info>
	<title>Advanced Search</title>
		<abstract>
			<para>Advanced searches allow users to perform more complex searches by providing more options. Many kinds of searches can be performed from the 
			<emphasis>Advance Search</emphasis> screen. </para> 
        	</abstract>
	</info>    		
	 <para>You can access the Advanced Search by clicking <guilabel>Advanced Search</guilabel> on
         the catalogue Homepage or search results screen.</para>
      <informalfigure>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>The available search options are the same as on the Home page. But you may use one or
         many of them simultaneously. If you want to combine more than three search options, use
            <guibutton> Add Search Row</guibutton> button to add more search input rows. Clicking
         the <guibutton>X</guibutton> button will close the search input row.</para>
      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-advanced-search-sort-criteria">
         <title>Sort Criteria</title><indexterm><primary>advanced search</primary><secondary>sort criteria</secondary></indexterm>
         <para>By default, the search results are in order of greatest to least relevance. See <xref
               linkend="catalogue-search-methodology-order-of-results"/>. In the sort criteria box
            you may select to order the search results by relevance, title, author, or publication
            date.</para>
      </simplesect>
      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-advanced-search-group-formats-and-editions">
         <title>Group Formats and Editions</title><indexterm><primary>advanced search</primary><secondary>group formats and editions</secondary></indexterm>
         <para>This checkbox is at the bottom line of Sort Criteria. When it is checked, all formats
            and editions of the same title are grouped as one result. For example, the DVD and the
            first and second print editions of <emphasis>Harry Potter and the Chamber of Secrets
            </emphasis>will appear together.</para>
      </simplesect>


      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-advanced-search-search-library">
         <title>Search Library</title><indexterm><primary>advanced search</primary><secondary>search library</secondary></indexterm>
         <para>The current search library is displayed under <guilabel>Search Library</guilabel>
            box. Be default it is your library. The search returns results for your local library
            only. If your library system has multiple branches, use the <guilabel>Search
               Library</guilabel> box to select different branches or the whole library
            system.</para>

      </simplesect>


      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-advanced-search-limit-to-available">
         <title>Limit to Available</title><indexterm><primary>advanced search</primary><secondary>limit to available</secondary></indexterm>
         <para>This checkbox is at the bottom line of Search Library. Select <guilabel>Limit to
               Available</guilabel> to limit by item’s current circulation status. Titles without
            available items in the library will not be displayed.</para>
      </simplesect>


      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-advanced-search-search-filter">
         <title>Search Filter</title><indexterm><primary>advanced search</primary><secondary>search filter</secondary></indexterm>
         <para>You can filter your search by <guimenuitem>Item Form, Item Type, Literary Form,
               Language</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Audience</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Bib
               Level</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Publication Year</guimenuitem>. Publication year
            is inclusive. For example, if you set Publication Year Between 2005 and 2007, your
            result items will be published in 2005, 2006 and 2007.</para>
         <para>The <guibutton>Advanced </guibutton>button below the filter name creates a more
            detailed menu to choose from. For each filter type, you may select multiple criteria by
            holding down the <keycap>CTRL </keycap>key as you click on the options. If nothing is
            selected for a filter, the search will return results as though all options are
            selected.</para>
         <para>If you are searching a particular library or branch, you can also limit your search
            by items' shelving location, too.</para>
      </simplesect>



      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-advanced-search-quick-search">
         <title>Quick Search</title><indexterm><primary>advanced search</primary><secondary>quick search</secondary></indexterm>
         <para>If you have details on the exact item you wish to search for, use the <guilabel>Quick
               Search </guilabel>option on the left of the screen. Use the drop-down menu to select
            to search by <guimenuitem>ISBN, ISSN, Call Number, LCCN, TCN, or Item
               Barcode</guimenuitem>. Enter the information and click <guibutton>Submit</guibutton>
            under Quick Search.</para>
      </simplesect>


      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-advanced-search-marc-expert-search">
         <title>MARC Expert Search</title><indexterm><primary>advanced search</primary><secondary>MARC expert search</secondary></indexterm>
         <para>If you are familiar with the MARC system, you may search by tag in the <guilabel>MARC
               Expert Search</guilabel> option on the left of the screen. Enter the three-digit tag
            number, the subfield if relevant, and the value or text that corresponds to the tag. For
            example, to search by publisher name, enter 260 b Random House. To search several tags
            simultaneously, use the <guibutton>Add Row </guibutton>option. Click
               <guibutton>Submit</guibutton> to run the search.</para>
      
         <tip>
            <para  xml:id="catalogue-advanced-scope"><guilabel>Quick Search</guilabel> and <guilabel>MARC Expert Search</guilabel> scope to the 
               entire catalogue. Unlike <guilabel>keyword</guilabel>, <guilabel>author</guilabel>, and <guilabel>subject</guilabel>
               searches, they cannot be limited to items in a particular library. The only exception is
               the <guilabel>Quick Search</guilabel> by <guilabel>call number</guilabel>.</para>
         </tip>
      </simplesect>
</chapter>

