<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="MyAccount" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<info>
		<title>My Account</title>
		<abstract>
			<para>This chapter will explain how users can use the My Account feature of the OPAC to manage their accounts.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>
	<simplesect xml:id="myaccountloginpasswordupdate">
		
				<title>First Login Password Update</title><indexterm><primary>My Account</primary><secondary>first login</secondary></indexterm>
			<para>Patrons are given temporary passwords when new accounts are created, or forgotten passwords are reset by staff. Patrons MUST change their password to something more 
			secure when they login or for the first time. Once the password is updated, they will not have to repeat this process for subsequent logins.</para>
			
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Open a web browser and go to  your Evergreen OPAC</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <emphasis>My Account</emphasis></para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Enter your <guilabel>Username</guilabel> and <guilabel>Password</guilabel></para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>By default, your username is your library card number.</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>Your password is a 4 digit code provided when your account was created. If you have forgotten your password, contact your 
								 library to have it reset or use the online <xref linkend="myaccountpasswordreset" /> tool.</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <guibutton>Login</guibutton>. You will be prompted to change your password.</para>
						<substeps>
							<step>
								<para>Enter your <guilabel>current password</guilabel>.</para>
							</step>
							<step>
								<para>Enter a <guilabel>new password</guilabel>.</para>
							</step>
							<step>
								<para>Enter the <guilabel>new password again</guilabel>.</para>
							</step>
							<step>
								<para>Click <guibutton>Update Password</guibutton>.</para>
							</step>
							<step>
								<para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. You will be returned to the login screen.</para>
							</step>
						</substeps>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Enter your <guilabel>Username</guilabel> and <emphasis role="bold">new</emphasis> <guilabel>Password</guilabel></para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Your <guilabel>Account Summary</guilabel> page displays.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="myaccountlogin">
				<title>Logging In</title><indexterm><primary>My Account</primary><secondary>logging in</secondary></indexterm>
				<procedure>
				<title>Logging into your account from the online catalog</title>	
					<step>
						<para>Open a web browser and navigate to your Evergreen OPAC</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <guibutton>My Account</guibutton></para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Enter your <guilabel>Username</guilabel> and <guilabel>Password</guilabel></para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>By default, your username is your library card number.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>Your password is a 4 digit code provided when your account was created. If you have forgotten your password, contact your local 
							library to have it reset or use the <xref linkend="myaccountpasswordreset" /> tool.</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <guibutton>Login</guibutton></para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>At the first login, you will be prompted to change your password.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>After updating the password, you must enter your Username and Password again.</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Your <emphasis role="bold">Account Summary</emphasis> page displays</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
				<para>To view your account details, click one of the <guilabel>My Account</guilabel> tabs</para>
				<para>To start a search, enter a term in the search box at the top of the page and click <guibutton>Go!</guibutton></para>
				<caution><para>If using a public computer be sure to log out!</para></caution>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="myaccountpasswordreset">
				<title>Password Reset</title><indexterm><primary>My Account</primary><secondary>password reset</secondary></indexterm>
					<para>Evergreen 1.6.1 introduced a new feature to allow patrons to reset forgotten passwords from the My Account login screen.</para>  
					<para>To reset your password:</para> 
					<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>click on the the <guibutton>Forgot your password?</guibutton> link located under the <guibutton>login</guibutton> button</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Fill in the <guilabel>Barcode</guilabel> and <guilabel>User name</guilabel> text boxes.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>A pop up message should appear indicating that your request has been processed and that you will recieve an email with further instructions.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>An email will be sent to the email addressed you have registered with your Evergreen library. You should click on the link included in the email 
						to open the password reset page. Processing time may vary.</para>
						<note><para>You will need to have a valid email account set up in Evergreen for you to reset your password. Otherwise, you will need to 
						contact your library to have your password reset by library staff.</para></note>
					</step>
						<step>
						<para>At the reset email page you should enter the new password in the <guilabel>New password</guilabel> field and re-enter it in the 
						<guilabel>Re-enter new password</guilabel> field.</para>
						
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <guibutton>Submit</guibutton></para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>A message should appear on the page indicating that your password has been reset.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Login to your account with your new password.</para>
					</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="myaccountsummary">
				<title>Account Summary</title><indexterm><primary>My Account</primary><secondary>account summary</secondary></indexterm>
					<para>Users can view Staff Notes, home library, address, and phone numbers. They can also change their username, password, and email.</para>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="myaccountitemscheckedout">
				<title>Items Checked Out</title>
					<para>Users can manage items currently checked out, view overdue items and see how many renewals they have remaining for specific item.</para>		
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="myaccountitemsonhold">
				<title>Items On Hold</title><indexterm><primary>My Account</primary><secondary>items on hold</secondary></indexterm>
				<para>From My Account patrons can manage items currently being requested.</para>
					<para>Actions include:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Suspend</guimenuitem> - set a period of time during which the hold will not become active, such as during a vacation</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Activate</guimenuitem> - manually remove the suspension</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Set Active Date</guimenuitem> - specify a date at which the suspension will be lifted</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Cancel</guimenuitem> - remove the hold request</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				
					<para>Edit options include:</para>

					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Enable/disable phone notifications</guimenuitem> </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Change telephone number for notification</guimenuitem> </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Enable/disable email notification</guimenuitem> </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Change pick up library</guimenuitem> </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Change expiration date</guimenuitem> </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Suspend</guimenuitem> </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><guimenuitem>Activate date</guimenuitem> </para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				<procedure>
				<title>To edit items on hold:</title>
					<step>
						<para>Login to My Account, click the <emphasis>Items on Hold</emphasis> tab</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Select the hold to modify</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> or <guimenu>Actions for Selected Holds</guimenu></para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Select the change to make and follow the instructions.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="myaccountfines">
				<title>Fines</title><indexterm><primary>My Account</primary><secondary>fines</secondary></indexterm>
					<para>Clicking on the fines tab will allow you to see your <guilabel>Total Owed</guilabel>, <guilabel>Total Paid</guilabel> and <guilabel>Balance 
					Owed</guilabel>.</para>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="myaccountpreferences">
				<title>Preferences</title><indexterm><primary>My Account</primary><secondary>preferences</secondary></indexterm>
					<para>From here you can manage display preferences including:</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>Search hits per page - how many items to appear on each page in results.</listitem>
						<listitem>Default Font Size</listitem>
						<listitem>Default Hold Notification Method - What is the preferred method for being notified for a hold pick up: email or phone. </listitem>
						<listitem>Default Search Location - Which is the preferred default location for searching. By default youer home library is selected.</listitem>
						<listitem>Default Search Range - What is the range of your search (e.g. location, library, system, consortium, etc...)</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>After changing any of these settings, remember to click <guibutton>Save Preference Changes</guibutton>.</para> 					
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect xml:id="myaccountbookbags">
				<title>Bookbags</title><indexterm><primary>My Account</primary><secondary>bookbags</secondary></indexterm>
				<para>My Bookbags is a feature that allows you to create lists of library materials (books, audiobooks, videos, etc.) These lists create links to records in the 
				catalog, but are otherwise completely private and only accessible by you when logged in to your Account.</para>
				<para>You have the option to share specific lists with people whom you choose (send them the direct URL), or more generally via RSS feed. Shared bookbags do 
				<emphasis role="bold">NOT</emphasis> create a link to your personal library account information or private bookbags. You can share or un-share bookbags at any time.</para>
				<para>You can create as many bookbags and you want. Your bookbags will stay in your account until you delete them.</para>
				<para>Items remain in bookbags until you remove them. Even if the item record is removed from the catalog, the bookbag entry will remain (but there will be no link to 
				the catalog.)</para>
				<procedure>
				<title>Create a new Bookbag</title>
					<step>
						<para>Login to <guilabel>My Account</guilabel> , click <guibutton>My Bookbags</guibutton></para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>At <guilabel>Create a new Bookbag</guilabel>, enter the name of the new Bookbag</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Select <guilabel>yes</guilabel> or <guilabel>no</guilabel> for the <guilabel>Share this Bookbag</guilabel> option.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <guibutton>Submit</guibutton></para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton></para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
				<procedure>
				<title>Add items to a Bookbag</title>
					<step>
						<para>Search for an item, open the Title Record</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Open the <guilabel>More Actions...</guilabel> list; click the Bookbag name</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton></para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
				<procedure>
				<title>Share a Bookbag</title>
					<step>
						<para>Login to <guilabel>My Account</guilabel>, click <guibutton>My Bookbags</guibutton>.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Find the Bookbag to share, click <guibutton>Share this Bookbag</guibutton>.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click <guibutton>View</guibutton> to open the list as a webpage.</para> 
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>copy and send this URL to selected recipients or embed in another website.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click the <guiicon>RSS</guiicon> icon add the list to an RSS reader.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</simplesect>
</chapter>
