<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="catalogue-search-methodology">
	<title>Search Methodology</title>
     	 <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-search-methodology-stemming">
		 <title>Stemming</title><indexterm><primary>search methodology</primary><secondary>stemming</secondary></indexterm>
		 <para>A search for <emphasis>dogs</emphasis> will also return hits with the word
		       <emphasis>dog</emphasis> and a search for <emphasis>parenting</emphasis> will return
		    results with the words <emphasis>parent</emphasis> and<emphasis> parental</emphasis>.
		    This is because the search uses stemming to help return the most relevant results. That
		    is, words are reduced to their stem (or root word) before the search is
		    performed.</para>

		 <para>The stemming algorithm relies on common English language patterns - like verbs ending
		    in <emphasis>ing</emphasis> - to find the stems. This is more efficient that looking up
		    each search term in a dictionary and usually produces desirable results. However, it
		    also means the search will sometimes reduce a word to an incorrect stem and cause
		    unexpected results. To prevent a word or phrase from stemming, put it in
		    double-quotes.</para>

		 <para>Understanding how stemming works can help you to create more relevant searches, but
		    it is usually best not to anticipate how a search term will be stemmed. For example,
		    searching for <emphasis>gold compass</emphasis> does not return for <emphasis>golden
		       compass</emphasis> because the search does not recognize <emphasis>gold</emphasis> as
		    a stem of <emphasis>golden</emphasis>.</para>
      </simplesect>
      <simplesect>
		 <title>Truncation</title><indexterm><primary>search methodology</primary><secondary>truncation</secondary></indexterm>
		 <para>Truncation is not currently supported in Evergreen. </para>
      </simplesect>
      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-search-methodology-order-of-results"
		 xreflabel="Order of Results">
		 <title> Order of Results </title><indexterm><primary>search methodology</primary><secondary>order of results</secondary></indexterm>
		 <para>By default, the results are listed in order of relevance, similar
		    to a search engine like Google. The relevance is determined using a number of factors,
		    including how often and where the search terms appear in the item description, and
		    whether the search terms are part of the title, subject, author, or series. The results
		    which best match your search are returned first rather than results appearing in
		    alphabetical or chronological order.</para>
		 <para>In the <guilabel>Advanced Search </guilabel>screen, you may select to order the
		    search results by relevance, title, author, or publication date before you start the
		    search. You can also re-order your search results using the Sort Results dropdown list
		    on the search result screen. </para>
      </simplesect>
</chapter>

