<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="simpleselfcheck">
	<title>Simple Self Check Interface</title><indexterm><primary>self check</primary></indexterm>
	<note>
		<para>This section deals with the simple self check front end that comes with Evergreen. For information on setting up a SIP server for communicating with self check hardware, 
		please refer to <link linkend="sipserver">Setting up a SIP Server</link>.</para></note> 
     	 <section xml:id="usingselfcheck">
		 <title>Using the Self Check Interface</title>
		<simplesect>
			<title>Initializing the self check client.</title>
			<para>The selfcheck interface is run through a web browser. Before patrons can use the self check station, a staff member must initilize the interface by logging in.</para>  
			 <procedure>
				<step><para>Open a web browser and navigate to your self check interface page which is the location of the <filename>selfcheck.xml</filename> file. 
				By default, the url will be <uri>https://[<emphasis>hostname</emphasis>]/opac/extras/selfcheck/selfcheck.xml</uri>, where  [<emphasis>hostname</emphasis>] is your Evergreen 
				host.</para></step>
				<step><para>Login using a staff username or barcode and password.</para></step>			
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect>
			<title>Using the interface to check out books</title>
			<para>After a staff user has logged into the self check interface, the interface should be ready for patrons to scan their barcodes and check out books.</para>  
			 <procedure>
				<step><para>Scan your patron barcode to login</para></step>
				<step><para>Scan your books. The item titles should appear below the barcode field as you scan them.</para></step>
				<step><para>Click <guibutton>Done</guibutton> when you are finished. This will print the receipt and log out.</para></step>	
				<step><para>Select printer to print a receipt (if a printer is available).</para></step>		
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="customizingselfcheck">
		 <title>Customizing the Self Check Interface</title>
		 <para>The XML, CSS and JavaScript files for customizing the self check interface are located in the 
		<filename class="directory">/openils/var/web/opac/extras/selfcheck/</filename> directory.</para>
     </section>
</chapter>

