<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="acquistions">
	<title>The Acquisitions Module</title>	
	<simpara>Before beginning to use Acquisitions, the following must be configured by an administrator:</simpara>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><simpara>Currency Types (defaults exist)</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Exchange Rates (defaults exist)</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Funds</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Providers</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>EDI Accounts (optional)</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Claiming (optional)</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Invoices</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Distribution Formulas (optional)</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Line Item Features (optional)</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>Cancel/Suspend Reasons (optional)</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara>See the section on <link linkend="acquisitions-module_admin_functions">administrative functions in the acquisitions module</link> for details on acquisitions setup.</simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<section id="_brief_records">
		<title>Brief Records</title>
		<simpara>Brief records are short bibliographic records with minimal information that are often used as placeholder records until items are received.   Brief records can be added to 
		selection lists or purchase orders and can be imported into the catalog.  You can add brief records to new or existing selection lists.  You can add brief records to new, pending 
		or on-order purchase orders.</simpara>
		<simplesect id="_add_brief_records_to_a_selection_list">
			<title>Add brief records to a selection list</title>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>New Brief Record</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. You can also add brief records to an 
				existing selection list by clicking the <guilabel>Actions</guilabel> menu on the selection list 
				and choosing <guilabel>Add Brief Record</guilabel>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Choose a selection list from the drop down menu, or enter the name of a new selection list.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter bibliographic information in the desired fields.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Save Record</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_brief_record.png"/></imageobject>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_add_brief_records_to_purchase_orders">
			<title>Add brief records to purchase orders</title>
			<simpara>You can add brief records to new or existing purchase orders.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Open or create a purchase order. See the section on <link linkend="acq_purchase_orders">purchase orders</link> for more information.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Add Brief Record</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter bibliographic information in the desired fields.  Notice that the record is added to the purchase order that you just created.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Save Record</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_brief_record-2.png"/></imageobject>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section id="_cancel_suspend_acquisitions">
		<title>Cancel/suspend acquisitions</title>
		<simpara>You can cancel entire purchase orders, line items on the purchase orders, and individual copies that are attached to a line item.  You can also use cancel reasons to 
		suspend purchase orders, line items, and copies.  For example, a cancel reason such as Delayed Publication, would indicate that the item will be purchased when the item is 
		published.  The purchase is, in effect, suspended rather than cancelled, but the state of the purchase order, line item, or copy would still become cancelled.</simpara>
		<simplesect id="_cancel_suspend_copies">
			<title>Cancel/suspend copies</title>
			<simpara>You can cancel or suspend line items that are in a state of on order or pending order.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Select the <guilabel>Copies</guilabel> link.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click the <guilabel>Cancel</guilabel> link adjacent to the copy that you wish to cancel.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Select a cancel reason from the drop down menu that appears, and click <guibutton>Cancel copy</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_cancel_copy.png"/></imageobject>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_cancel_suspend_line_items">
			<title>Cancel/suspend line items</title>
			<simpara>You can cancel or suspend line items that are in a state of on order or pending order.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Check the boxes of the line items that you wish to cancel.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Cancel Selected Lineitems</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Select a cancel reason from the drop down menu.  Choose the cancel reason, and click <guibutton>Cancel Line Items</guibutton>.  The status of the line item 
				is now cancelled.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_cancel_line_items.png"/></imageobject>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_cancel_suspend_purchase_orders">
			<title>Cancel/suspend purchase orders</title>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Notice the Cancel column in the top half of the purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click the drop down arrow adjacent to <guilabel>Cancel order</guilabel>, and select a reason for cancelling the order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Cancel order</guibutton>.  The state of the purchase order is cancelled.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_cancel_order.png"/></imageobject>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section id="_claim_items">
		<title>Claim items</title>
		<simpara>Manual claiming of items can be accomplished in multiple ways, but electronic claiming is not available in the 2.0 release.
		You can apply claim policies to line items or individual copies.  You also can use the default claim policy associated with your provider to claim items.</simpara>
		<simplesect id="_apply_a_claim_policy">
			<title>Apply a claim policy</title>
			<simpara>You can apply a claim policy to an item in one of two ways: apply a claim policy to a line item when the item is created on the selection list or purchase order, 
			or use the default claim policy associated with the provider on the purchase order.  The default claim policy for a provider is established when the provider is created and 
			will be used for claiming if no claim policy has been applied.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Open a selection list or purchase order.  See the section on <link linkend="acq_purchase_orders">Purchase Orders</link> for more information.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> drop down menu on the line item.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guimenuitem>Apply Claim Policy</guimenuitem>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>A drop down menu of claim policies will appear.  Choose a claim policy to apply to the line item.  The claim policy will be applied to all 
				items that have not been received or cancelled.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click Save.</simpara></step>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_apply_claim_policy.png"/></imageobject>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_change_a_claim_policy">
			<title>Change a claim policy</title>
			<simpara>You can manually change a claim policy that has been applied to a line item.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Open a selection list or purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> drop down menu on the line item.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guimenuitem>Change Claim Policy</guimenuitem>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>A drop down menu of claim policies will appear.  Choose a claim policy to apply to the line item.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Save</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_claim_an_item">
			<title>Claim an item</title>
			<simpara>You can manually claim items at any time after the item has been ordered.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Open a purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> drop down menu on the line item.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guimenuitem>Claims</guimenuitem>. The number of existing claims appears in parentheses.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_claim_item.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
				<step><simpara>A drop down menu of items to be claimed and possible claim actions appears.  Check the boxes adjacent to the item that you want to claim 
				and the action that you will take.  You can claim items that have not been received or cancelled.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_claim_item-2.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Claim Selected</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Select a claim type from the drop down menu.  Entering a note is optional.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Claim</guibutton>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_claim_item-3.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
				<step><simpara>The number of existing claims on the line item updates, and a claim voucher appears.  The voucher can be printed and mailed to the vendor to initiate 
				the claim.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_produce_a_list_of_claim_ready_items">
			<title>Produce a list of claim-ready items</title>
			<simpara>If an item has not been received and meets the conditions for claiming according to the item’s claim policy, then the item will be eligible for claiming.  
			Evergreen can produce a list of items, by ordering branch, which is ready to be claimed.  You can use this list to manually claim items from your provider.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Claim-Ready Items</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Choose a branch from the drop down menu to claim items that were ordered by this branch.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Any items that meet the conditions for claiming will appear.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Check the box adjacent to the line items that you wish to claim.  Click <guibutton>Claim selected items</guibutton>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_claim_item-4.png"/></imageobject>


</step>
				<step><simpara>Select a claim type from the drop down menu.  Entering a note is optional.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Claim</guibutton>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_claim_item-5.png"/></imageobject>
</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section id="_export_single_attribute_list">
		<title>Export Single Attribute List</title>
		<simpara>You can export ISBNs, ISSNs, or UPCs as a file from the list of line item(s).  A list of ISBNs, for example, could be uploaded to vendor websites when placing orders.</simpara>
		<procedure>
			<step><simpara>From a selection list or purchase order, check the boxes of the line items with attributes that you wish to export.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Export Single Attribute List</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Choose the line item attribute that you would like to export from the drop down list of attributes.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Export List</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_export_list.png"/></imageobject>
			<step><simpara>Save the file to your computer.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Open the file.  Choose a program (e.g. Excel) to open the file.</simpara></step>
		</procedure>
	</section>
	<section id="_funds">
		<title>Funds</title>
		<simpara>You can apply a single fund or multiple funds to copies on a selection list or purchase order.  You can change the fund that has been applied to an item at any time on a 
		selection list.  You can change the fund that has been applied to an item on a purchase order if the purchase order has not yet been activated.</simpara>
		<simpara>Funds can be applied to items from the Copies link that is located on a line item.  Funds can also be applied to copies by batch updating line items and their attendant 
		copies.</simpara>
		<simplesect id="_apply_funds_to_individual_copies">
			<title>Apply funds to individual copies</title>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click the <guilabel>Copies</guilabel> link on the line item.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>To apply a fund to an individual item, click the drop down arrow in the <guilabel>Fund</guilabel> field.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_funds.png"/></imageobject>				
				<note><simpara>A yellow fund name indicates that the balance in the fund has dropped to the warning percent that was entered in the admin module.  
				A red fund name indicates that the balance in the fund has dropped to the stop percent that was entered in the admin module.  Funds that have been closed out will 
				no longer appear on the drop down list.</simpara></note>
				</step>
				<step><simpara>To apply a fund to multiple items, see the section on line items for more information.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_apply_funds_to_copies_via_batch_updates_to_line_items">
			<title>Apply funds to copies via batch updates to line items</title>
			<simpara>You can apply funds to all copies on a line item(s) from the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu on the selection list or the purchase order.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Check the boxes of the line items with copies to which you would like to apply funds.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Apply Funds to Selected Items</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Select the fund that you wish to apply to the copies.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Submit</guibutton>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_funds.png"/></imageobject>	
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section id="_invoice_acquisitions">
		<title>Invoice acquisitions</title>
		<simpara>You can create invoices for purchase orders, individual line items, and blanket purchases.  You can also link existing invoices to purchase orders.  In 2.0, all invoicing is 
		manual.</simpara>
		<simpara>You can invoice items before you receive the items if desired.  You can also reopen closed invoices, and you can print all invoices.</simpara>
		<simplesect id="_create_a_blanket_invoice">
			<title>Create a blanket invoice</title>
			<simpara>You can create a blanket invoice for purchases that are not attached to a purchase order.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Create invoice</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter the invoice information in the top half of the screen.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>To add charges for materials not attached to a purchase order, click <guibutton>Add Charge…</guibutton>  This functionality may also be used to add 
				shipping, tax, and other fees.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Select a charge type from the drop down menu.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Select a fund from the drop down menu.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter a <guilabel>Title/Description</guilabel> of the resource.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter the amount that you were billed.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter the amount that you paid.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Save the invoice.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_invoice_blanket.png"/></imageobject>	
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_create_an_invoice_for_a_line_item">
			<title>Create an invoice for a line item</title>
			<simpara>See the section on creating new invoices for line items for details.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_create_an_invoice_for_a_purchase_order">
			<title>Create an invoice for a purchase order</title>
			<simpara>You can create an invoice for all of the line items on a purchase order.  With the exception of fields with drop down menus, no limitations on the data that you enter 
			exist.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Open a purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Create Invoice</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter a <guilabel>Vendor Invoice ID</guilabel>.  This number may be listed on the paper invoice sent from your vendor.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Choose a <guimenuitem>Receive Method</guimenuitem> from the drop down menu.</simpara>
				<note><simpara>Only paper invoicing is available in the 2.0 release.  Electronic invoicing may be available in future releases.</simpara></note>
				</step>
				<step><simpara>The Provider is generated from the purchase order and is entered by default.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter a <guilabel>note</guilabel> (optional).</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Select a <guilabel>payment method</guilabel> from the drop down menu.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>The <guilabel>Invoice Date</guilabel> is entered by default as the date that you create the invoice. You can change the date by clicking in 
				the field.  A calendar drops down.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter an <guilabel>Invoice Type</guilabel> (optional).</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>The Shipper defaults to the provider that was entered in the purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter a <guilabel>Payment Authorization</guilabel> (optional).</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>The <guilabel>Receiver</guilabel> defaults to the branch at which your workstation is registered.  You can change the receiver by selecting an org unit 
				from the drop down menu.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_invoice_purchase_order.png"/></imageobject>	
				<note><simpara>The bibliographic line items are listed in the next section of the invoice.  Along with the <guilabel>title</guilabel> and <guilabel>author</guilabel> of 
				the line items is a <guilabel>summary of copies ordered</guilabel>, <guilabel>received</guilabel>, <guilabel>invoiced</guilabel>, <guilabel>claimed</guilabel>, 
				and <guilabel>cancelled</guilabel>.  You can also view the <guilabel>amounts estimated</guilabel>, <guilabel>encumbered</guilabel>, and paid for each line item.  Finally, 
				each line item has a <guilabel>line item ID</guilabel> and links to the <guilabel>selection list</guilabel> (if used) and the <guilabel>purchase 
				order</guilabel>.</simpara></note>
				</step>
				<step><simpara>Enter the number of items that were invoiced, the amount that the organization was billed, and the amount that the organization paid.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>You have the option to add <guilabel>charge types</guilabel> if applicable.  Charge types are additional charges that can be selected 
				from the drop down menu.  Common charge types include taxes and handling fees.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>You have three options for saving an invoice.  You can click <guibutton>Save</guibutton>, which saves the changes that you have made, but keeps the 
				invoice open.  You can click <guibutton>Save and Prorate</guibutton>, which enables you to save the invoice and prorate any additional charges, such as taxes, across funds, 
				if multiple funds have been used to pay the invoice.  You also can click <guibutton>Save and Close</guibutton>.  Choose this option when you have completed the 
				invoice.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
			<note><simpara>You can re-open a closed invoice by clicking the link, <guilabel>Re-open invoice</guilabel>.  This link appears at the bottom of a closed invoice.</simpara></note>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_link_an_existing_invoice_to_a_purchase_order">
			<title>Link an existing invoice to a purchase order</title>
			<simpara>You can use the link invoice feature to link an existing invoice to a purchase order.  For example, an invoice is received for a shipment with items on purchase order #1 
			and purchase order #2.  When the invoice arrives, purchase order #1 is retrieved, and the invoice is created.  To receive the items on purchase order #2, simply link the invoice 
			to the purchase order.  You do not need to recreate it.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Open a purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Link Invoice</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter the Invoice # and the Provider of the invoice to which you wish to link.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Link</guibutton>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_invoice_link.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_view_an_invoice">
			<title>View an invoice</title>
			<simpara>You can view an invoice in one of four ways:  view open invoices; view invoices on a purchase order; view invoices by searching specific invoice fields; 
			view invoices attached to a line item.</simpara>
			<simpara>To view open invoices, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Open invoices</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.  This opens the Acquisitions Search 
			screen.  The default fields search for open invoices.  Click <guibutton>Search</guibutton>.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_invoice_view.png"/></imageobject>
			<simpara>To view invoices on a purchase order, open a purchase order, and click the <guilabel>View Invoices</guilabel> link. The number in parentheses indicates the number of 
			invoices that are attached to the purchase order.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_invoice_view-2.png"/></imageobject>
			<simpara>To view invoices by searching specific invoice fields, see the section on <link linkend="acq_searching">searching the acquisitions module</link>.</simpara>
			<simpara>To view invoices for a line item, see the section on <link linkend="_view_invoice">line item invoices</link>.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section id="_line_items">
		<title>Line Items</title>
		<simpara>Line items represent bibliographic records on a selection list or purchase order.  One line item corresponds to one bibliographic record.  Line items contain attributes, 
		which are characteristics of the bibliographic record, such as ISBNs or Title.  Line items also contain copy information, price information, and notes and alerts.</simpara>
		<simplesect id="_add_alerts_to_a_line_item">
			<title>Add alerts to a line item</title>
			<simpara>Alerts are pop up messages that appear when an item is received.  Alerts can be printed on the line item worksheet.</simpara>
			<procedure>
			<step><simpara>Click the <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> link on the line item.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click the <guilabel>New Alert</guilabel> drop down button.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Choose an alert code from the drop down menu.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Add additional comments if desired.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Create</guibutton>.  The alert will display on the screen.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_alerts.png"/></imageobject>
			</step>
			<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Return</guibutton> to return to the line item.  When you return to the line item, a flag will appear to indicate 
			that an alert is on the line item.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_alerts-2.png"/></imageobject>
			</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_add_copies_to_a_line_item">
			<title>Add copies to a line item</title>
			<simpara>Use the <guilabel>Copies</guilabel> link to add copy information to a line item.  You can add copies to line items on a selection list or a purchase order.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click the <guilabel>Copies</guilabel> link on a line item.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_add_copies.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
				<step><simpara>Enter the number of items that you want to order in Item Count, and click <guibutton>Go</guibutton>.  The number of items that you want to order will 
				display below.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>If desired, apply a <guilabel>Distribution Formula</guilabel> from the drop down list.  Distribution formulas tell the ILS how many copies should be 
				distributed to each location.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>The owning branch and shelving location populate with entries from the distribution formula.  Click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Look back at the top gray row of text boxes above the distribution formula. Each text box in this row corresponds to the columns below.  Changes made here 
				will be applied to all copies below.  Click <guibutton>Batch Update</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Save Changes</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Return</guibutton> to return to the selection list or purchase order.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_add_copies-2.png"/></imageobject>				
				</step>
				<step><simpara>Add the item’s price to the line item in the <guilabel>Estimated Price</guilabel> field.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_add_copies-3.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_add_notes_to_a_line_item">
			<title>Add notes to a line item</title>
			<simpara>Notes on line items can include any additional information that you want to add to the line item.  Notes can be internal or can be made available to providers.  Notes 
			appear in a pop up box when an item is received.  Notes can be printed on line item worksheets, which can be printed and placed in books for processing.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click the <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> link on the line item.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click the <guilabel>New Note</guilabel> drop down button.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter a note.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>You have the option to make this note available to your provider. Click the check box adjacent to <guilabel>Note is vendor-public</guilabel>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Create</guibutton>.  The note will appear on the screen.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Return</guibutton> to return to the line item.  When you return to the line item, a number in parentheses adjacent to notes indicates 
				how many notes are attached to the item.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_add_notes.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_cancel_a_line_item">
			<title>Cancel a line item</title>
			<simpara>For more information, see the section on <link linkend="_cancel_suspend_acquisitions">cancelling/suspending acquistions</link>.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_line_item_actions">
			<title>Line item actions</title>
			<simplesect id="_claims">
				<title>Claims</title>
				<simpara>See the section on <link linkend="_claim_items">claiming</link> for more information.</simpara>
			</simplesect>
			<simplesect id="_holdings_maintenance">
				<title>Holdings maintenance</title>
				<simpara>After an item has been received, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Holdings Maintenance</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to edit holdings.  The 					Holdings Maintenance screen opens in a new tab.</simpara>
				
				<simpara>Use the <guimenuitem>Link to invoice</guimenuitem> menu item to link the line item to an invoice that already exists in the ILS.</simpara>
				<procedure>
					<step><simpara><menuchoice><guimenu>Click Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Link to Invoice</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
					<step><simpara>A pop up box appears.  Enter an <guilabel>invoice number</guilabel>.</simpara></step>
					<step><simpara>Enter a <guilabel>provider</guilabel>. The field will auto-complete.</simpara></step>
					<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Link</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				</procedure>
			</simplesect>
			<simplesect id="_mark_received">
				<title>Mark received</title>
				<simpara>See the section on <link linkend="_receiving">receiving</link> for more information.</simpara>
			</simplesect>
			<simplesect id="_new_invoice">
			<title>New invoice</title>
			<simpara>See the  <link linkend="_invoice_acquisitions">invoicing</link> section for more information.</simpara>
			</simplesect>
			<simplesect id="_un_receive">
			<title>Un-receive</title>
			<simpara>See the <link linkend="_receive_un_receive_copies">receiving/un-receiving</link> section for more information.</simpara>
			</simplesect>
			<simplesect id="_update_barcodes">
			<title>Update barcodes</title>
			<simpara>After an item has been received, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Update Barcodes</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to edit holdings.  
			The <guilabel>Volume and Copy Creator</guilabel> screen opens in a new tab.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_update_barcodes.png"/></imageobject>
			</simplesect>
			<simplesect id="_view_history">
			<title>View history</title>
			<simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>View history</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to view the changes that have occurred in the life of the line 
			item.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_view_history.png"/></imageobject>
			</simplesect>
			<simplesect id="_view_invoice">
			<title>View invoice</title>
			<simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>View invoice</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to view any invoices that are attached to the line item.</simpara>
			</simplesect>
			<simplesect id="_line_item_worksheet">
				<title>Line Item Worksheet</title>
				<simpara>The Line Item Worksheet is a printable sheet that contains details about the line item, including alerts and notes, and distribution of the copies.  This 
				worksheet could be placed in a book that is sent to cataloging or processing.</simpara>
				<procedure>
					<step><simpara>From a selection list or purchase order, click the <guilabel>worksheet</guilabel> link on the line item.</simpara>
					<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_worksheet.png"/></imageobject>				
					</step>
					<step><simpara>The line item worksheet appears.</simpara>
					<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_worksheet.png"/></imageobject>
					</step>
					<step><simpara>To print the worksheet, click the <guilabel>Print Page</guilabel> link in the top right corner.</simpara></step>
				</procedure>
			</simplesect>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section id="_link_line_items_to_the_catalog">
		<title>Link line items to the catalog</title>
		<simpara>You can link a MARC record or brief record on a selection list to the corresponding MARC record in the catalog.  This may be useful for librarians who have a brief MARC record 
		in their catalog and want to import a better record that is attached to their selection list.  No collision detection exists when importing an item into the selection list or catalog, so 
		the link to catalog option enables you to search for a matching record and link to it from the selection list or purchase order.  When you import the record from the purchase order, 
		the record will overlay the linked record in the catalog.</simpara>
		<procedure>
			<step><simpara>From the line item, click <guibutton>Link to catalog</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>In the text box that pops up, search terms, such as ISBN and title, are entered by default.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Search</guibutton>.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_link.png"/></imageobject>
			</step>
			<step><simpara>Result(s) appear.  Click the link to View MARC, or Select the record to link it to the record on the selection list or purchase order.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_line_items_link-2.png"/></imageobject>
			</step>
			<step><simpara>The screen will reload, and the line item displays with a catalog link.  The records are linked.</simpara></step>	
		</procedure>		
	</section>	
	<section id="acq_load_bib_records">
		<title>Load Bib Records and Items Into the Catalog</title>
		<simpara>You can load bib records and items into the catalog at three different locations in the acquisitions module. You can import bib records and items 
		(if holdings information is attached) when you upload MARC order records.  Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Load MARC Order 
		Records</guimenuitem></menuchoice>  and check the box adjacent to <guilabel>Load Bibs and 
		Items into the ILS</guilabel>.You can import bib records and items into the catalog when you create a purchase order from a selection list.  From the selection list, 
		click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Create Purchase Order</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Check the box adjacent to <guilabel>Load Bibs and Items into the 
		ILS</guilabel> to import the records into the catalog.
		You can import bib records and items into the catalog from a purchase order by clicking <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Load Bibs and 
		Items</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
		If you have not loaded bib records and items into the catalog before you activate a purchase order, then the ILS will automatically import the bib records and 
		items into the catalog when you activate the purchase order.</simpara>
	</section>
	<section id="acq_load_catalog_record_ids">		
	<title>Load Catalog Record IDs</title>
		<simpara>The Load Catalog Record IDs function enables you to create line items from a list of catalog records whose record IDs are saved in a CSV file.</simpara>
		<simpara>This would be useful if you want to batch order copies of items that your organization already owns.   For example, after gathering a list of needed titles from your OPAC 
		through a report, save the record IDs into a CSV file, upload the file into the ILS, and create a purchase order for the items.</simpara>
		<procedure>
			<step><simpara>Create a CSV file with the record ID of each catalog record in the first column of the spreadsheet. You can create this CSV file from a spreadsheet generated 
			by a report, as suggested in the aforementioned example.  You can also copy and paste record IDs from the catalog record into the CSV file.</simpara>
			<note><simpara>Record IDs are auto-generated digits associated with each record.  They are found in the Record Summary that appears at the top of each record.</simpara></note>
			</step>
			<step><simpara>Save the CSV file to your computer.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Load Catalog Record IDs</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Load More Terms</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>The screen will display the number of terms (record IDs) that have been loaded.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Retrieve Records</guibutton>.  The records will appear as line items to which you can add copies, notes, and pricing information.  Use the 				<guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu to save these items to a selection list or purchase order.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_load_records.png"/></imageobject>
</step>
		</procedure>
	</section>
	<section id="_load_marc_order_records">
		<title>Load MARC Order Records</title>
		<simpara>The Load MARC Order Records screen enables you to upload MARC records that have been saved on your computer into the ILS.  You can add the records to a selection list and/or 
		to a purchase order.  You can both create and activate purchase orders in one step from this interface.  Also, from this interface, you can load bibs and items into the catalog.</simpara>
		<procedure>
			<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Load MARC Order Records</guimenuitem></menuchoice></simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>If you want to upload the MARC records to a new purchase order, then click the check box adjacent to <guilabel>Create Purchase Order</guilabel>.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>If you want to activate the purchase order at the time of creation, then click the check box adjacent to <guilabel>Activate Purchase Order</guilabel>.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>If you want to load bibs and items into the catalog, then click the check box adjacent to <guilabel>Load Bibs and Items into the ILS</guilabel>.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Enter the name of the <guilabel>Provider</guilabel>.  The text will auto-complete.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Select an org unit from the drop down menu.  The context org unit is the org unit that <literal>owns</literal> the bib record.  You should select a physical 
			location rather than a political or administrative org unit as the context org unit.  For example, the <literal>Smith County Library System</literal> is funding purchase of a 
			copy of <literal>Gone with the Wind</literal>.  The system owns the bib record, but it cannot receive the physical item.  The acquisitions librarian will 
			choose a physical branch of that system, a processing center or an individual branch, to receive the item.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>If you want to upload the records to a selection list, you can select a list from the drop down menu, or type in the name of the selection list that you want 
			to create.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> to search for the file of bibliographic records.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Upload</guibutton>.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_load_marc_records.png"/></imageobject>
			</step>
			<step><simpara>A summary of the items that have been processed will appear.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click the links that appear to view the purchase order or the selection list.</simpara></step>
		</procedure>		
	</section>
	<section id="_marc_federated search">
		<title>MARC Federated Search</title>
		<simpara>The MARC Federated Search enables you to import bibliographic records into a selection list or purchase order from a Z39.50 source.</simpara>
		<procedure>
			<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>MARC Federated Search</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Check the boxes of Z39.50 services that you want to search.  Your local Evergreen Catalog is checked by default.  Click <guibutton>Submit</guibutton>.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_marc_search.png"/></imageobject>
			</step>
			<step><simpara>A list of results will appear.  Click the <guilabel>Copies</guilabel> link to add copy information to the line item.  
			See the <link linkend="_line_items">section on Line Items</link> for more 
			information.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click the <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> link to add notes or line item alerts to the line item.  See the <link linkend="_line_items">section on Line Items</link> for more 
			information.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Enter a price in the <guilabel>Estimated Price</guilabel> field.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>You can save the line item(s) to a selection list by checking the box on the line item and clicking <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Save 
			Items to Selection List</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.  You can also create 
			a purchase order from the line item(s) by checking the box on the line item and clicking <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Create Purchase 
			Order</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_marc_search-2.png"/></imageobject>
			</step>
		</procedure>
	</section>
	<section id="acq_patron requests">	
		<title>Patron Requests</title>
		<note><simpara>The patron requests interface will allow you to view requests that patrons make via the OPAC.  The functionality for OPAC requests is not currently available in 
		the native Evergreen interface, so the screen remains blank in 2.0.</simpara></note>
	</section>
	<section id="acq_purchase_orders"> 
		<title>Purchase Orders</title>
		<simpara>You can create a purchase order from a selection list, a batch upload of MARC order records, the <guilabel>View/Place Orders</guilabel> link in the catalog, or results 
		from a MARC Federated Search.  You can also create blanket purchase orders to which you can add brief records or generic charges and fees.</simpara>
		<simplesect id="_activate_a_purchase_order">
			<title>Activate a purchase order</title>
			<simpara>Before you can active a purchase order, the following criteria must be met:</simpara>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>The field, Activate Order?, is located in the top half of the purchase order.  The answer adjacent to this field must be <quote>Yes</quote>.</listitem>
				<listitem>Each line item must contain an estimated price.  If the <guilabel>Activate Order?</guilabel> field in the top half of the purchase order reads, 
				<quote>No: The 	lineitem has no price (ACQ_LINEITEM_NO_PRICE)</quote>, then simply enter a price in the <guilabel>estimated price field</guilabel>, tab out of the field, 
				and click <guibutton>Reload</guibutton>.</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<simpara>When the above criteria have been met, proceed with the following:</simpara>
			<simpara>Look at the <guilabel>Activate Order?</guilabel> field in the top half of the purchase order.  Click the hyperlinked <guilabel>Activate Order</guilabel>.  
			When you activate the order, the bibliographic records and copies will be imported into the catalog, and the funds associated with the purchases will be encumbered.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_add_brief_records_to_a_purchase_order">
			<title>Add brief records to a purchase order</title>
			<simpara>To add brief records to a purchase order, see the section on adding <link linkend="_brief_records">brief records</link> for more information.  You can add 
			brief records to new or existing purchase orders.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_add_charges_taxes_fees_or_discounts_to_a_purchase_order">
			<title>Add charges, taxes, fees, or discounts to a purchase order</title>
			<simpara>You can add charges, taxes, fees, or discounts to a purchase order.  These additional charges will be reflected in the amounts that are estimated and encumbered on 
			the purchase order.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Open or create a purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>New charge</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Select a <guilabel>charge type</guilabel> from the drop down menu.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Select a <guilabel>fund</guilabel> from the drop down menu.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter a <guilabel>Title/Description</guilabel>, <guilabel>Author</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Note</guilabel> if applicable.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter an <guilabel>estimated cost</guilabel>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Add another new charge, or click <guibutton>Save New Charges</guibutton>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_purchase_order_add_charges.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
			</procedure>
			<note><simpara>Discounts are not consistently supported in the 2.0 release.</simpara></note>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_add_notes_to_a_purchase_order">
			<title>Add notes to a purchase order</title>
			<simpara>You can add notes to each purchase order.  These can be viewed by staff and/or by the provider.  By default, notes are only visible to staff.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Open a purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>In the top half of the purchase order, you see a <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> field.  The number of notes that are attached to the purchase order is 
				hyperlinked in parentheses next to the Notes field.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click the hyperlinked number.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>New Note</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter the note.  If you wish to make it available to the provider, click the check box adjacent to <guilabel>Note is vendor-public</guilabel>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Create</guibutton>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_purchase_order_add_note.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_cancel_suspend_a_purchase_order">
			<title>Cancel/Suspend a purchase order</title>
			<simpara>To cancel or suspend a purchase order, see the <link linkend="_cancel_suspend_acquisitions">cancel/suspend acquisitions</link> section.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_create_a_purchase_order">
			<title>Create a purchase order</title>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Create Purchase Order</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>A pop-up box appears. Select an owning library from the drop down menu.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter a <guilabel>provider</guilabel> in the box.  The text will auto complete.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>As necessary, check the box adjacent to <guilabel>Prepayment Required</guilabel>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Save</guibutton>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_purchase_order_create.png"/></imageobject>			
				</step>
				<step><simpara>The purchase order has been created.  You can now create a new charge type or add a brief record.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
			<simpara>The <guilabel>Total Estimated</guilabel> is the sum of the prices.  The <guilabel>Total Encumbered</guilabel> is the total estimated that is 
			encumbered when the purchase order is activated.  The <guilabel>Total Spent</guilabel> column automatically updates when the items are invoiced.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_mark_ready_for_order">
			<title>Mark ready for order</title>
			<simpara>After an item has been added to a selection list or purchase order, you can mark it ready for order.  This step is optional but may be useful to individual 
			workflows.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>If you want to mark part of a selection list ready for selector, then you can check the box(es) of the line item(s) that you wish to mark ready for 
				selector.  If you want to mark the entire list ready for selector, then skip to step 2.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click<menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Mark Ready for Order</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>A pop up box will appear.  Choose to mark the selected line items or all line items.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Go</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>The screen will refresh.  The line item will be highlighted gray, and the status will change to order-ready.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_name_a_purchase_order">
			<title>Name a purchase order</title>
			<simpara>A new purchase order is given the purchase order ID as a default name.  However, you can change that name to any grouping of letters or numbers. You can reuse purchase 
			order names as long as a name is never used twice in the same year.</simpara>
			<procedure>
			<step><simpara>Open or create a purchase order.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>The Name of the purchase order is in the top left column of the purchase order.  The hyperlinked number is an internal ID number that Evergreen has 
			assigned.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>To change this number, click on the hyperlinked ID.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Enter a new purchase order number in the pop up box.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_purchase_order_name.png"/></imageobject>	
			</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect  id="_print_purchase_orders">
			<title>Print purchase orders</title>
			<simpara>You can print a purchase order from the purchase order screen.  If you add a note to a line item, the note will only appear in the <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> 
			column on the printed purchase order if you make the note vendor-public.  Currently, no notes appear in the <guilabel>Notes to the Vendor</guilabel> section of the printed 
			purchase order.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Open a purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Print Purchase Order</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_purchase_order_print.png"/></imageobject>			
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_receive_a_purchase_order">
			<title>Receive a purchase order</title>
			<simpara>See the section on <link linkend="_receiving">receiving acquistions</link> for more information on receiving a purchase order.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_split_order_by_line_items">
			<title>Split order by line items</title>
			<simpara>You can create a purchase order with multiple line items, and then split the purchase order so that each line item is on separate purchase orders.</simpara>
			<simpara>When a purchase order is in the status of pending, a link to <guilabel>split order by Lineitems</guilabel> appears in the bottom left corner of the top half of 
			the screen.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click Split Order by Lineitems.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>A pop up box will confirm that you want to split the purchase order.  Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to continue.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_purchase_order_split.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
				<step><simpara>The items will display by default as a virtual combined purchase order.  Future enhancements will allow you to activate the purchase order for each item 
				from this screen.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_purchase_order_split-2.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_view_on_order_purchase_orders">
			<title>View On-Order Purchase Orders</title>
			<simpara>You can view a list of on-order purchase orders by clicking <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Purchase Orders</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. 
			The ordering agency defaults to the branch at which your workstation 
			is registered.  The state of the purchase order defaults to on-order.</simpara>
			<simpara>You can add more search terms by clicking <guibutton>Add Search Term</guibutton>.  Search terms are <quote>ANDed</quote> together.  
			Click <guibutton>Search</guibutton> to begin your search.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_purchase_order_view.png"/></imageobject>
			<simpara>If you want to expand or change your search of purchase orders, you can choose other criteria from the drop down menus.  See  <link linkend="acq_searching">Searching 				Acquisitions</link> for more information.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_purchase_order_view-2.png"/></imageobject>
			<note><simpara>When searching by Org Unit, the exact ordering location must be selected.  Searching for a consortium or system does not also display purchase orders or line 
			items attached to child organizations.</simpara></note>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_view_edi_messages_on_a_purchase_order">
			<title>View EDI messages on a purchase order</title>
			<simpara>You can view electronic messages from your vendor about a specific purchase order.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Open a purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>In the top half of the purchase order, you see an <guilabel>EDI Messages</guilabel> field.  The number of messages that are attached to the purchase 
				order is hyperlinked in parentheses next to the <guilabel>EDI Messages</guilabel> field.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click the hyperlinked number to view the messages.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_view_purchase_order_history">
			<title>View Purchase Order History</title>
			<simpara>In the top half of the purchase order, you can view the history of the purchase order.  Click the <guilabel>View</guilabel> link in the 
			<guilabel>History</guilabel> field.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_purchase_order_history.png"/></imageobject>
	</section>
	<section id="_receiving">
		<title>Receiving</title>
		<simpara>You can receive and un-receive entire purchase orders, line items, and individual copies.  You can receive items before or after you invoice items.</simpara>
		<simplesect id="_receive_un_receive_copies">
			<title>Receive/un-receive copies</title>
			<simpara>To receive copies, click the <guilabel>Copies</guilabel> link on the line item, and click the <guilabel>Mark Received</guilabel> link adjacent to each copy.</simpara>
			<simpara>To un-receive copies, click the <guilabel>Copies</guilabel> link on the line item, and click the <guilabel>Un-Receive link</guilabel> adjacent to each copy.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_receive_un_receive_line_items">
			<title>Receive/un-receive line items</title>
			<simpara>To receive a line item, click the <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Mark Received</guimenuitem></menuchoice> link on the line item.</simpara>
			<simpara>To un-receive a line item, click the <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Un-receive</guimenuitem></menuchoice> link on the line item.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_receive_un_receive_purchase_orders">
			<title>Receive/un-receive purchase orders</title>
			<simpara>To receive a purchase order, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Mark Purchase Order as Received</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.  
			The purchase order will have a state of received.</simpara>
			<simpara>To un-receive a purchase order, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Un-Receive Purchase Order</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.  
			The purchase will have a state of on order.</simpara>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section id="acq_searching">
		<title>Searching</title>
		<simpara>In the acquisitions module, you can search line items, line items and catalog records, selection lists, purchase orders, and invoices.  To access the searching interface, 
		click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>General Search</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara>
		<simpara>Users may wish to begin their acquisitions process by searching line items and catalog records.  This ensures that they do not purchase an item that the library already owns or is 
		on another selection list or purchase order.</simpara>
		<procedure>
			<step><simpara>Choose the object that you would like to search from the drop down menu.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Next, refine your search by choosing the specific fields that you would like to search.  Click <guibutton>Add Search Term</guibutton> to add more fields.  
			Search terms are <quote>ANDed</quote>
			together.  Click the red <guilabel>X</guilabel> at the end of each row to delete search terms.  Some search terms will be disabled depending on your choice of items 
			to search.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>After you have added search term(s), click <guibutton>Search</guibutton> or click the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key.  A list of results appears.</simpara>
			<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_search.png"/></imageobject>
			</step>
			<step><simpara>If you want to edit your search, click the <guibutton>Reveal Search</guibutton> button in the top right corner of the results screen to display 
			your search.</simpara></step>
		</procedure>
		<note><simpara>When searching by <guilabel>Org Unit</guilabel>, the exact ordering location must be selected.  Searching for a consortium or system does not also display purchase orders or line items attached 
		to child organizations.</simpara></note>
	</section>
	<section id="_selection_lists">
		<title>Selection Lists</title>
		<simpara>Selection lists allow you to create, manage, and save lists of items that you may want to purchase.  To view your selection list, click 
		<menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>My Selection Lists</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.  Use the general search to view selection lists created by other users.</simpara>
		<simplesect id="_create_a_selection_list">
			<title>Create a selection list</title>
			<simpara>Selection lists can be created in four areas within the module.  Selection lists can be created when you Add Brief Records, Upload MARC Order Records, or find records 
			through the MARC Federated Search.  In each of these interfaces, you will find the Add to Selection List field.  Enter the name of the selection list that you want to create in 
			that field.</simpara>
			<simpara>Selection lists can also be created through the My Selection Lists interface:</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>My Selection Lists</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click the <guilabel>New Selection List</guilabel> drop down arrow.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter the name of the selection list in the box that appears.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Create</guibutton>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_selection_create.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_add_items_to_a_selection_list">
			<title>Add items to a selection list</title>
			<simpara>You can add items to a selection list in one of three ways: <link linkend="_brief_records">add a brief record</link>; <link linkend="_load_marc_order_records">upload 
			MARC order records</link>; add records through a <link linkend="_marc_federated search">federated search</link>; or use the 
			<link linkend="_view_place_orders">View/Place Orders</link> menu item in the catalog. </simpara>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_clone_selection_lists">
			<title>Clone selection lists</title>
			<simpara>Cloning selection lists enables you to copy one selection list into a new selection list.  You can maintain both copies of the list, or you can delete the previous 
			list.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>My Selection Lists</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Check the box adjacent to the list that you want to clone.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Clone Selected</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter a name into the box that appears, and click <guibutton>Clone</guibutton>.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_selection_clone.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_merge_selection_lists">
			<title>Merge selection lists</title>
			<simpara>You can merge two or more selection lists into one selection list.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>My Selection Lists</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Check the boxes adjacent to the selection lists that you want to merge, and click <guibutton>Merge Selected</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Choose the <guilabel>Lead Selection List</guilabel> from the drop down menu.  This is the list to which the items on the other list(s) will be 
				transferred.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_selection_merge.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Merge</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_delete_selection_lists">
			<title>Delete selection lists</title>
			<simpara>You can delete selection lists that you do not want to save.  You will not be able to retrieve these items through the General Search after you have deleted 
			the list.  You must delete all line items from a selection list before you can delete the list.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Acquisitions</guimenu><guimenuitem>My Selection Lists</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Check the box adjacent to the selection list(s) that you want to delete.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Delete Selected</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_mark_ready_for_selector">
			<title>Mark Ready for Selector</title>
			<simpara>After an item has been added to a selection list or purchase order, you can mark it ready for selector.  This step is optional but may be useful to individual 
			workflows.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>If you want to mark part of a selection list ready for selector, then you can check the box(es) of the line item(s) that you wish to mark ready for 
				selector.  If you want to mark the entire list ready for selector, then skip to step 2.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Mark Ready for Selector</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>A pop up box will appear.  Choose to mark the selected line items or all line items.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Go</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>The screen will refresh.  The marked line item(s) will be highlighted pink, and the status changes to selector-ready.</simpara>
				<imageobject role="fo"><imagedata scalefit="1" fileref="../media/acq_selection_mark_ready.png"/></imageobject>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
		<simplesect id="_convert_selection_list_to_purchase_order">
			<title>Convert selection list to purchase order</title>
			<simpara>Use the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu to convert a selection list to a purchase order.</simpara>
			<procedure>
				<step><simpara>From a selection list, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Create Purchase Order</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>A pop up box will appear.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Select the ordering agency from the drop down menu.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Enter the <guilabel>provider</guilabel>.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Check the box adjacent to <guilabel>prepayment required</guilabel> if prepayment is required.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Choose if you will add <guilabel>All Lineitems</guilabel> or <guilabel>Selected Lineitems</guilabel> to your purchase order.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Check the box if you want to <guilabel>Import Bibs</guilabel> and <guilabel>Create Copies</guilabel> in the catalog.</simpara></step>
				<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Submit</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			</procedure>
		</simplesect>
	</section>
	<section id="_view_place_orders">
		<title>View/Place Orders</title>
		<procedure>
			<step><simpara>Open a bib record.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Actions for this Record</guimenu><guimenuitem>View/Place Orders</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>Click <guibutton>Add to Selection List</guibutton>, or click <guibutton>Create Purchase Order</guibutton>.</simpara></step>
			<step><simpara>See the documentation on purchase orders and/or selection lists for instructions to proceed.</simpara></step>
		</procedure>
	</section>
</chapter>
