<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cataloging">
  <info>
    <title>Cataloging</title>
    <abstract>
      <para>This chapter explains the cataloging procedures carried out from
      the staff client.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="addingnewbibliographicrecords">
    <title>Adding New Records via Built In Z39.50 Client</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Z39.50</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The Z39.50 client is used to search bibliographic databases and
    examine or download bibliographic records. Open the client with <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Cataloging</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Import Record from Z39.50</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice></para>
    <simplesect xml:id="z39.50screenfeatures">
      <title>Z39.50 Screen Features</title>
      <para>Initially, or when you want to change targets, start with the
      <guilabel role="bold">Service and Credentials</guilabel> area. Here you 
      choose the remote databases you wish to search. Preconfigured servers are 
      listed under Services. If any require authentication to access, you will 
      see username and password boxes to the right. </para>
      <procedure>
        <step>Click all the databases you wish to search simultaneously (see the 
        Note about which fields can be used).</step>
        <step>Fill in user information for any that require it.</step>
        <step>Click <guibutton>Save as Default</guibutton> to preserve these 
        settings for next time.</step>
      </procedure>
      <para>The <guilabel role="bold">Query</guilabel> section is where you 
      enter a search. The databases you select control which search fields you 
      can use. You may use any combination of fields that are active (not grayed 
      out), but be aware that not all fields are active for every database. 
      Select just one database to see which fields are active for that database.
      </para>
      <note>
        <para>If you are searching multiple databases, you will only get results 
        from those that support the fields you&apos;re searching! For example, 
        <guilabel>Keyword</guilabel> and <guilabel>Subject</guilabel> are only 
        active if the local catalog is selected, so using those fields in a 
        combined database search guarantees that you will only get results from 
        the local catalog.</para>
      </note>
      <para>The <guilabel>Query</guilabel> section has three buttons.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem><guibutton>Search</guibutton> begins searching on 
       the criteria entered in the search fields.</listitem>
       <listitem><guibutton>Clear Form</guibutton> resets all fields to empty.
       </listitem>
       <listitem><guibutton>Raw Search</guibutton> is an advanced interface for 
       using Prefix Query Format to build complex searches. See 
       <xref linkend="rawsearches" />.</listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      <para>The <guilabel role="bold">Results</guilabel> pane displays the results from the 
      most recent search.  Information about each record retrieved appears on a
          separate summary line, with various columns of information.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>If more than the default number of results is available, use 
        <guibutton>Fetch More Results</guibutton> to add the next set to the 
        screen.</listitem>
        <listitem>Click List Action to view options for exporting and saving 
        from the list:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>Copy Field from selected row to Clipboard</listitem>
            <listitem>Print List CSV</listitem>
            <listitem>Copy List CSV to Clipboard</listitem>
            <listitem>Save List CSV to File</listitem>
            <listitem>Save List Configuration</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>Select an item and click <guibutton>MARC View</guibutton> to 
          toggle viewing the MARC record. <guibutton>Results View</guibutton>
          </listitem>
          <listitem><guibutton>MARC Editor for Overlay</guibutton></listitem>
          <listitem><guibutton>MARC Editor for Import</guibutton></listitem>
        <listitem>To view long lists of results, use <guibutton>Hide Top Pane
        </guibutton> to view the results. </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect xml:id="importingarecordviaz39.50">
      <title>Importing a record via Z39.50</title>  
</simplesect>
    <simplesect xml:id="recordcollisions">
      <title>Record Collisions</title>  
</simplesect>
    <simplesect xml:id="fastitemadds">
      <title>Fast Item Adds</title>  
</simplesect>

   <simplesect xml:id="rawsearches">
      <title>Raw Searches</title>  
<tip>
            <para>Visit <xref xlink:href="http://www.indexdata.com/yaz/doc/tools.html"/> 
            for more details on PQF and examples you can copy/paste into the 
            search box.</para>
          </tip>
          </simplesect>
</section>
 </chapter>
