<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="catalogue-search-tips">
	<title>Search Tips</title>
	 <para>You do not need to enter authors last name first, nor do you need an exact title or
         subject heading. Evergreen is also forgiving about plurals and alternate verb endings, so
         if you enter <emphasis>dogs</emphasis>, Evergreen will also find items with
            <emphasis>dog</emphasis>.</para>
   	<itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Do not use an AND operator to join search terms. </para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>An AND operator is automatically used to join all search terms. So, a search<indexterm><primary>boolean</primary><secondary>AND operator</secondary></indexterm>
                     for <emphasis>golden compass </emphasis>will search for entries that contain
                     both <emphasis>golden </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">and
                        </emphasis><emphasis>compass</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>o Boolean operators such as <emphasis>and, or, not </emphasis>are not
                     considered special and are searched for like any other word. So, a search for
                        <emphasis>golden and compass </emphasis>will not return the title
                        <emphasis>golden compass</emphasis>. Putting it another way, there are no
                        <emphasis>stop </emphasis>words that are automatically ignored by the search
                     engine. So, a title search for <emphasis>the and or not </emphasis>of (and in
                     any order) yields a list of titles with those words. </para><indexterm><primary>boolean</primary></indexterm>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Don’t worry about white space, exact punctuation, or capitalization.</para>
            <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
               <listitem>
                  <para>White spaces before or after a word are ignored. So, search for
                        <emphasis>golden compass</emphasis> gives the same results as a search for
                        <emphasis>golden compass</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>A double dash or a colon between words is reduced to a blank space. So, a
                     title search for <emphasis>golden:compass </emphasis> or <emphasis>golden --
                        compass </emphasis>is equivalent to <emphasis>golden
                     compass</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Punctuation marks occurring within a word are removed; the exception is _.
                     So, a title search for <emphasis>gol_den com_pass </emphasis>gives no result.
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Diacritical marks, &amp;, or | located anywhere in the search term are
                     removed. Words or letters linked together by . (dot) are joined together
                     without the dot. So, a search for <emphasis>go|l|den &amp; comp.ass
                     </emphasis>is equivalent to <emphasis>golden compass</emphasis>. </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para> Upper and lower case letters are equivalent. So, <emphasis>Golden
                        Compass</emphasis> is the same as <emphasis>golden
                     compass</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Enter your search words in any order. So, a search for <emphasis>compass
                  golden</emphasis> gives the same results as a search for <emphasis>golden
                  compass</emphasis>. Adding more search words gives fewer and more specific
               results. </para>

            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>This is also true for author searches. Both <emphasis>David Suzuki
                     </emphasis>and <emphasis>Suzuki, David</emphasis> will return results for the
                     same author.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Use specific search terms. Evergreen will search for the words you specify, not
               the meanings, so choose search terms that are likely to appear in an item
               description. For example, the search <emphasis>luxury hotels </emphasis>will produce
               more relevant results than <emphasis>nice places to stay</emphasis>.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Search for an exact phrase using double-quotes. For example <emphasis>“golden
                  compass”</emphasis>. </para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>The order of words is important for an exact phrase search.
                        <emphasis>“golden compass”</emphasis> is different than <emphasis>“compass
                        golden”</emphasis>. </para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para>White space, punctuation and capitalization are removed from exact phrases
                     as described above. So a phrase retains its search terms and its relative
                     order, but not special characters and not case. </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Two phrases are joined by and, so a search for <emphasis>“golden compass”
                        “dark materials” </emphasis>is equivalent to <emphasis>“golden compass”
                           <emphasis role="bold">and</emphasis> “dark materials”</emphasis>. </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>To prevent <link linkend="catalogue-search-methodology-stemming"
                        >stemming</link> , use double quotes around a single word or a phrase. So, a
                     search for <emphasis>parenting</emphasis> will also return results for
                        <emphasis>parental</emphasis> but a search for
                        <emphasis>“parenting”</emphasis> will not. </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Do not use wildcards. Truncation using wildcards is not supported in Evergreen.
               So, searching for <emphasis>comp*</emphasis> will not return results for
                  <emphasis>compass</emphasis>. </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Exclude a term from the search, using <emphasis>-</emphasis> (minus) or !
               (exclamation point). For example, <emphasis>vacations –britain</emphasis> or
                  <emphasis>vacations !britain</emphasis> will search for materials on vacations
               that do not make reference to Britain. </para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Two excluded words are joined by <emphasis>and</emphasis>. So, a search for
                        <emphasis>!harry !potter</emphasis> is equivalent to
                        <emphasis>!harry</emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">and</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>!potter</emphasis>. </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>A + (plus) leading a term has no role and is removed. So,
                        <emphasis>+golden</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>+compass</emphasis> is equivalent to <emphasis>golden
                        compass</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>You can form more complex searches using the Advanced Search features.</para>
      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-search-tips-improving-a-search-with-few-results">
         <title>Improving a Search With Few Results</title>
         <para>If few hits were returned for your search is displayed, you may see some suggestions
            for expanding or altering your search at the bottom of the s earch results list. These
            alternate search terms are words that are similar to your search terms in spelling or
            sound. Selecting one of the links performs a search with the new search terms.</para>
      </simplesect>
</chapter>

