<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="catalogue-search-results">
	
	<title>Search Results</title>
		
	 <informalfigure>
         <para>The search results are a list of relevant works from the catalogue. If there are many
            results, they are divided into several pages. At the top of the list, you can see the
            total number of results and go back and forth between the pages by clicking the double
            arrow on top or bottom of the list. Here is an example: </para>

         <para>
            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/catalogue-3.png"/>
               </imageobject>

            </mediaobject>
         </para>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>Brief information about the title, such as author, edition, publication date, etc. is
         displayed under each title. The icons under the brief information indicate formats such as
         books, audio books, video recordings, and other formats. Hove your mouse over the icon,
         text explanation will show up in a small pop-up box. </para>
      <para>Clicking a title goes to the title details. Clicking an author searches all works by the
         author. If you want to place a hold on the title, click <guibutton>Place Hold</guibutton>
         beside the format icons.</para>

      <para>On the top right corner, there is a <guilabel>Limit to Available</guilabel> checkbox.<indexterm><primary>search results</primary><secondary>limit to available</secondary></indexterm>
         Checking this box will filter out those titles with no available copies in the library or
         libraries at the moment. Usually you will see your search results are re-displayed with
         fewer titles</para>
      <para>The Sort Results dropdown list is beside the <guilabel>Limit to Available</guilabel><indexterm><primary>search results</primary><secondary>sort criteria</secondary></indexterm>
         checkbox. Clicking an entry on the list will re-sort your search results
         accordingly.</para>

      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-search-results-formats-and-editions"><indexterm><primary>search results</primary><secondary>sort criteria</secondary></indexterm>
         <title>Formats and Editions</title><indexterm><primary>search results</primary><secondary>group formats and editions</secondary></indexterm>
         <informalfigure>
            <para>If you have selected <guilabel>Group Formats and Editions</guilabel> with your
               search, your search results are grouped by various formats and editions of the same
               title. Multiple format icons may be lit up. Clicking a title will show you the
               records of all formats, while clicking an icon will show you the particular
               format.</para>

            <para>
               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/catalogue-4.png"/>
                  </imageobject>

               </mediaobject>
            </para>
         </informalfigure>
      </simplesect>



      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-search-results-related-subjects-authors-and-series">
         <title> Related Subjects, Authors, and Series</title><indexterm><primary>search results</primary><secondary>related subjects, authors, and series</secondary></indexterm>
         <informalfigure>
            <para>At the left, you may see a list of <guimenuitem> Related Subjects,
                  Authors</guimenuitem>, and <guimenuitem>Series</guimenuitem>. Selecting one of
               these links searches the catalogue again using that subject, author, or series to
               find additional items. This begins a new search rather than further refining the
               current search.</para>

            <para>
               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata scalefit="0" fileref="../media/catalogue-5.png"/>
                  </imageobject>

               </mediaobject>
            </para>
         </informalfigure>

      </simplesect>


      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-search-results-availability">
         <title>Availability</title><indexterm><primary>search results</primary><secondary>availability</secondary></indexterm>

         <informalfigure>
            <para>The number of available copies and total copies are displayed in the right-hand
               columns. If you are using a catalogue inside a library or accessing a library’s
               online catalogue from its homepage, you will see how many copies are available in the
               library under the library’s name. If the library belongs to a multi-branch library
               system you will see an extra column under the library system’s name showing how many
               copies are available in all branches</para>
            <para>
               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/catalogue-6.png"/>
                  </imageobject>

               </mediaobject>
            </para>
         </informalfigure>
         <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                  <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/catalogue-7.png"/>
               </imageobject>

            </mediaobject>
         </informalfigure>
      </simplesect>

      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-search-results-viewing-a-record">
         <title>Viewing a record</title>

         <informalfigure>
            <para>Click on a title to view a detailed record of the title, including descriptive
               information, location and availability, and options for placing holds.</para>
            <para>
               <mediaobject xml:id="screenshot-view-a-record">
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata width="100%" scalefit="1" fileref="../media/catalogue-8.png"/>
                  </imageobject>

               </mediaobject>
            </para>
         </informalfigure>
      </simplesect>

      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-search-results-detials">
         <title>Details</title>
         <para>The record shows details such as the cover image, title, author, publication
            information, and an abstract or summary, if available.</para>
         <para>At the bottom of the record, the <guibutton>Copy Summary </guibutton>shows how many
            copies are at the library or libraries you have selected, and whether they are available
            or checked out. It also displays the <guilabel>Callnumber</guilabel> and <guilabel>Copy
               Location</guilabel> for locating the item on the shelves. You can select
               <guibutton>Shelf Browser </guibutton>to view items appearing near the current item on
            the library shelves. Often this is a good way to browse for similar items. You can
            select <guibutton>Table of Contents</guibutton> to see the book’s table of contents
            online (if available). You can select <guibutton>MARC Record</guibutton> to display the
            record in MARC format.</para>
      </simplesect>

      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-search-results-placing-holds">
         <title>Placing Holds</title><indexterm><primary>Holds</primary></indexterm>
         <para>Holds can be placed on either title results or title details page. If the item is
            available, it will be pulled from the shelf and held for you. If all copies at your
            local library are checked out, you will be placed on a waiting list and you will be
            notified when items become available. </para>

         <para> On title details page, you can select the <guibutton>Place Hold</guibutton>link in
            the upper right corner of the record to reserve the item. You will need your library
            account user name and password. You may choose to be notified by phone or email and set
            up an expiration date for your hold by selecting the respective checkboxes. Hold
            expiration date means after this date, even though your hold has not been fulfilled you
            do not need the item anymore. </para>

         <para> In the example below, the phone number in your account will automatically show up.
            Once you select the <guilabel>Enable phone notifications for this hold?</guilabel>
            checkbox, you can supply a different phone number for this hold only. The notification
            method will be selected automatically if you have set it up in your account preferences.
            But you still have a chance to re-select on this screen. You may also suspend the hold
            temporarily by checking the <guilabel>Suspend</guilabel> box. Click the
               <guibutton>Help</guibutton> beside it for details. </para>

         <para>You can view and cancel a hold at anytime. Before your hold is captured, which means
            an item has been held waiting for you to pick up, you can edit, suspend or activate it.
            You need log into your account to do it. </para>

         <para>
            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                  <imagedata scalefit="0" fileref="../media/catalogue-9.png"/>
               </imageobject>

            </mediaobject>
         </para>



      </simplesect>

      <simplesect xml:id="catalogue-search-results-going-back">

         <title>Going back</title>
         <informalfigure>
            <para>When you are viewing a specific record, you can always go back to your title list
               by clicking the link <guilabel>My Title Results</guilabel> on the left of the
               page.</para>
            <para>

               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata scalefit="0" fileref="../media/catalogue-10.png"/>
                  </imageobject>


               </mediaobject>
            </para>

         </informalfigure>

         <informalfigure>
            <para>If you have selected <guilabel>Group Formats and Editions</guilabel> with your
               search, your search results are grouped by various formats and editions of the same
               title under <guilabel>My Search Results</guilabel>. You can always go back to this
               page by selecting the link to <guilabel>My Search Results</guilabel>
            </para>

            <para>

               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata scalefit="0" fileref="../media/catalogue-11.png"/>
                  </imageobject>


               </mediaobject>
            </para>
         </informalfigure>

         <para>You can start a new search at any time by entering new search terms in the search box
            at the top of the page, or by selecting the <guilabel>Home</guilabel> or
               <guilabel>Advanced Search</guilabel> links in the left-hand sidebar.</para>
         <para/>
      </simplesect>
</chapter>

