<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="advancedsearch">
	<info>
	<title>Advanced Search</title>
		<abstract>
			<para>Advanced searches allow users to perform more complex searches by providing more options. Many kinds of searches can be performed from the 
			<emphasis>Advance Search</emphasis> screen. </para> 
        	</abstract>
	</info>    		
	<section xml:id="Quicksearch">
		<title>Quick Search</title>
		<para>You can see from the drop down list below, that Quick Search also allows you to search by:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>ISSN (International Standard Serial Number)</listitem>
				<listitem>Call Number</listitem>
				<listitem>LCCN (Library of Congress Card Number)</listitem>
				<listitem>TCN (Title Control Number)</listitem>
				<listitem>Item Barcode</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<note>
				<para>To search by LCCN, replace the hyphen with a 0 (zero). To search by ISSN, replace the hyphen with a space.</para> 
				<para>When using <emphasis>Quick Search</emphasis>, only that field is used for the search.</para> 
 				<para>Anything entered in other search fields does not affect your search, and the other fields will not be cleared after a <emphasis>Quick Search</emphasis> 
				is performed.</para>  
				<para>The <emphasis>Quick Search</emphasis> function cannot be limited to your local library.  A <emphasis>Quick Search</emphasis> searches all of Evergreen.</para>
			</note> 
	</section>
	<section xml:id="UsingSearchInput">
		<title>Using Search Input</title>
		<para>The search input boxes allow you to search by Keyword, Title, Author, Subject, and Series, and to combine these searches to narrow your results.</para> 
		<para>The default setting displays three boxes for keyword searches.  You can click on the down arrows to select Title, Author, Subject or Series as well.   
		If desired, you can use different searches in the different boxes. For instance, you can enter the title of a book in one box, and the author in another. </para> 
		<para>More search rows may be added by clicking the <guibutton>Add Search Row</guibutton> button.  You can delete search rows by clicking the <guibutton>X</guibutton> button next to the 			search row.</para>
		<para>Keyword searches are very general and will give you many results.</para>
		<para>You can also adjust your searches by changing your selection from <guilabel>Contains</guilabel>  to <guilabel>Matches Exactly</guilabel> or 
		<guilabel>Does not contain</guilabel> .</para>
		<para>Since Evergreen uses stem searching, doing a Keyword search with <guilabel>Contains</guilabel> will give you results with words related to the search term.</para> 
		<note><para>Limiting your title search to <guilabel>Matches Exactly</guilabel> will not limit to titles that contain nothing but your search string, but rather titles that 
		contain your exact search string.</para></note> 
		<tip><para>When doing searches for one word titles, it is extremely useful to limit by author as well. </para></tip> 
		<para>If you go back to the search screen, your last search will be retained. However, the display reorders the search categories. <emphasis>Author</emphasis> 
		will be displayed on the top.</para>
	</section>
	<section xml:id="SortCriteria">
		<title>Sort Criteria</title>
		<para>Below the <guilabel>Search Input</guilabel> box are the <guilabel>Sort Criteria</guilabel> and <guilabel>Search Library</guilabel> boxes. The <guilabel>Sort Criteria</guilabel> 
		box is on the left, and allows you to change the way your search results are sorted.</para> 
		<para>The default Sort Criteria is <emphasis>by Relevance</emphasis>.  Generally items are considered more relevant the more often your search terms show up within a 
		bibliographic record.</para> 
		<para>You can also choose to sort your results alphabetically by author or title, or chronologically by publication date.</para>
		<para>When you select <guilabel>Title</guilabel>, <guilabel>Author</guilabel> or <guilabel>Publication Date</guilabel>, the drop down box below becomes active.  
		You can then select <guilabel>Ascending / A to Z</guilabel> or <guilabel>Descending / Z to A</guilabel>.</para>  
		<note><para>For Publication Date, selecting Ascending give you the oldest works first, and Descending will give you the most recent works first.</para></note> 
		<para>The <guilabel>Sort Criteria</guilabel> box also allows you to group titles and formats, so that they all display on one line in your search results.</para> 
		<note><para>Limiting your title search to <guilabel>Matches Exactly</guilabel> will not limit to titles that contain nothing but your search string, but rather titles that contain 
		your exact search string.</para></note>
		<para>When <guilabel>Group Formats and Editions</guilabel> is selected, most manifestations of a work will be grouped together in one line in your search results. Below the first 
		line includes both print and sound recordings. When the same search is performed with out the box checked, the results show 14 different records including various manifestations, 
		as well as some records which probably need to be merged. The <guilabel>Group Formats and Editions</guilabel> will remain checked or unchecked until you change it again.</para> 
	</section>
	<section xml:id="SearchLibrary">
		<title>Search Library</title>
		<para>The <guilabel>Search Library</guilabel> box allows you to change the search range, and to limit searches to available items.</para> 
		<para>In addition to changing the search range to your branch, your local library system, or the entire system, you can limit your search to a particular library other 
		than your home library. Select <guilabel>Choose a different library</guilabel>, to select from a list of libraries in the system.</para> 
		<para>You can click on the library system name on the list, or click the arrow next to the system name to choose a particular branch.  
		When you select a name from the list, you will return to the search screen and that library will show in the <guilabel>Search Library</guilabel> box.</para>
		<para>The <guilabel>Search library</guilabel> box also allows you to limit your search to items that are available for checkout. Place a check mark in the 
		<guilabel>Limit to Available box</guilabel>.</para> 	
		<para>If your search range is <emphasis>Everywhere</emphasis>, then the items just have to be available at one location.</para> 	
		<para>If you use the <emphasis>Limit to Available</emphasis> function and limit your search range to a particular branch, your results will include only items available 
		at that branch.</para> 
	</section>
	<section xml:id="UsingSearchFilters">
		<title>Using Search Filters</title>
		<para>Another way to limit your search results is to use <emphasis>Search Filters</emphasis>.  You can limit by <guilabel>Item Form</guilabel>, <guilabel>Item Type</guilabel>, 		<guilabel>Literary Form</guilabel>, <guilabel>Language</guilabel>, <guilabel>Audience</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Shelving Location</guilabel>.  
		All of these searches except for Shelving Location are based on data from the MARC record fixed fields. </para> 
		<para>To limit your search, simply click on your choices to highlight them in blue. Your search results will include only records which are coded to your choices.</para> 
		<para>There are blue arrows on the left side of the boxes, you can scroll up and down on to see more choices by clicking the up and down arrows.</para>
		<para>You can also select multiple items in the same box.  To select items which are all in a row, click the first item you wish to select, then press the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key while 
		clicking the bottom item.</para> 	
		<para>To select items which are not in a row, press the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while clicking on the items you wish to select. If you do not press the 
		<keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key, any previous selections will be unselected when you click something new. </para> 		
		<para>To change your selection, you can click a line in the box to remove any other selections.</para> 
		<para>To unselect something you have highlighted, when you do not want to select anything from that box, press the Ctrl key while clicking on that selection.</para>
		<note><para>Clicking <guibutton>Reset Form</guibutton> under <guilabel>Search Input</guilabel> will not reset your search filters.  You can unset the filters individually</para></note> 
		<para><guilabel>Item Type</guilabel>, <guilabel>LiteraryForm</guilabel> and <guilabel>Audience</guilabel> also have advanced optionsfor search filters.  
		These also depend on the coding of the MARC fixed fields, and results with advanced options will be even less precise since for instance, juvenile items that 
		could be coded for a specific age group may simply have a <emphasis>j</emphasis>. To see the advanced options, click on <guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> next to the field where you 
		wish to expand your options.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>

